<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 1</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-15 15:40:20</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-1.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-1.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In prepping for a new upcoming cross country season (with what will hopefully also be a good ramp up with summer training sessions for the team), I'm reading Daniels' Running Formula, and also would like to restart <em>Lore of Running</em> by Tim Noakes. <em>Lore</em> is a much larger and more technical book. In the meantime though, I feel like the best way to absorb this information is not only to read and mark up the book but also jot down notes from the chapter in summary to help it stick in my brain and refer back to when I need some guidance during the season.</p>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<h3>The Basic Ingredients</h3>

<p>There are four basic ingredients of success for runners: inherent ability, intrinsic motivation, opportunity, and direction.</p>

<p>Inherent ability is a "no-brainer" kind of factor. One that is likely the most important and cannot be changed. But when paired with motivation, opportunity, and direction, lower inherent ability can be trumped.</p>

<p>For runners who have a lot of inherent ability but low intrinsic motivation, one way to increase motivation is "asking... runners to feel the workouts and to feel the same workout getting easier before increasing training stress." (7)</p>

<p>For the opposite runner -- lower ability, higher motivation -- it can be important to emphasize that success and growth can happen in different time frames for different runners for a variety of reasons. Therefore "Every runniner should have short-term and long-term goals to shoot for." (7)</p>

<p>Opportunity, fortunately, is there for nearly all people. Running is neither expensive nor does it require specific weather or situations.</p>

<p>Direction largely has to do with coaching:</p>

<ul>
<li>"A good coach can always answer the questions 'What is the purpose of this workout?' and 'Why are we doing this workout today?'" (11)</li>
<li>"What coaches tend to overlook is the importance of giving positive individual attention to each athlete on the team. Nthing can replace encouraging comments or understanding words from a coach." (11)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Daniels' Basic Laws of Running:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Every runner has specific individual abilities. </li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "the main emphasis should be taking advantage of known strengths" (12)</p>

<ul>
<li>A runner's focus must stay positive.</li>
<li>Expect ups and cowns; some days are better than others</li>
<li>Be flexible in training to allow for the unexpected.</li>
<li>Set intermediate goals. (nb: try "smaller goals" that might lead to failure but provide a learning experience)</li>
<li>Concentrate on the task at hand.</li>
<li>Most mistakes in races are made early in the race.</li>
<li>Training should be rewarding</li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "It's not always fun, but it should always be rewarding." (13)</p>

<ul>
<li>Eat and sleep well.</li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "If you regularly eat and sleep well, one bad meal or poor night's sleep will ot have a negative effect on you." (13)</p>

<ul>
<li>Don't train when sick or injured.</li>
<li>Chronic health issues should be checked by a professional.</li>
<li>A good race or run is never a fluke.</li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "Sometimes a bad run is a fluke, but if you do run a great race, it is because you are capable of doing it." (14)</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>"Consistency in training is the single most important thing that leads to success." (14)</p>

<hr />

<p>I'm happy to say after reading through the first chapter, much of the training philosophy here is what has guided my own approach to coaching. That's not to say I haven't had my failures, but I think that's more because of a lack of a formula or guiding principle &amp; scientific research to undergird how I'm training athletes. I'm hoping the next chapters will help me build on that foundation of what I already know and am doing. And perhaps help correct me where I have been wrong.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Various Running Links and Quotes</title>
            <pubDate>2025-04-14 10:37:01</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/various-running-links-and-quotes.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/various-running-links-and-quotes.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well it's definitely been a while since my last post. As per usual in my own life, I go through different seasons where my focal length (to borrow a technical metaphor from photography) narrows and I can only do so much.</p>

<p>Cue track and field since February... and, you know, all of Elaine's vestibular migraine ups and downs. More on that later, I supposed.</p>

<p>Anyway, because I'm a learner at heart, I've consistently got a backlog of links and quotes I've gathered. I want to be better about tracking that and storing it, but it can sometimes get away from me. The purpose of this post is just to track a few of the links, quotes, and resources I've come across in the last month or so when trying to learn some better coaching methods or thinking about what a summer cross country training program should look like.</p>

<p><a href="https://run.wxm.be/summer-of-malmo/">Summer of Malmo</a></p>

<p>There seems to be a longer resource somewhere out there ("Malmo's Manifesto") that I can't access without paying for a subscription to Scribd. Malmo has a summer program of sorts for runners prepping for the fall. The gist:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Aimed at people with enough time in their summer (e.g., students on summer break)
    Run more
    Double 4+ days a week
    Meet up with others twice a week at the track
    Once for ~threshold (6.5 - 10 km total)
    Once for longer intervals, either
    4-6x1200-2000, one lap jog
    16-24x150-300m with 300m full recovery
    Slower people can just take a break more often and hop back in, because track</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Also in the manifesto:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Run twice a day, as many days as you can. Hopefully five, six or seven days a week.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Run more. How much? I dunno. You figure it out, but find out for yourself.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Run it faster.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Love running and LOVE racing.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Stay focused.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Set goals and don't be afraid to fail.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Listen to your body and don't be afraid to rest.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Compete WITH your comrades in sweat - never AGAINST them.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Smile a lot.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/running/comments/wi43kw/comment/ij9pfvp/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button">A user on Reddit about what should count as "tempo pace."</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Threshold pace usually refers to the (upper) lactate threshold. As a rule of thumb, it is the pace you can hold for about one hour at race conditions, e.g., well rested and tapered, on a fast course. In training, you can hold that pace for 15-40 minutes at a rather hard effort. At 6:20/mile for your recent 1:23 half, threshold pace is a just a tiny little bit faster than that, but still closer to your HM race pace that to your 10k race pace.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Some people then use this backwards: they refer to the pace you can hold for a one hour race as threshold pace, and use that as an indication for where your lactate threshold is.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>In reality, your average training loop likely will be slower than that HM race course where some nice flat roads have been blocked off for the runners, and that needs to be taken into account. When I was much younger and able to run such paces, my threshold runs actually ended up slightly slower than HM race pace, simply because of terrain and cumulative fatigue.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>In any case, threshold runs are longer runs at approximately (upper) lactate threshold pace, perhaps with very short breaks. For example, Daniels might have you do 4x6 minutes at T-pace with 1 minute rest.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Tempo run is a poorly defined term. It will have different meanings for different people. It will depend very heavily on what your training goals are. Say, are you preparing for an 800m race, or for an ultra in the mountains? Some people simply use "tempo run" as a synonym for a threshold run. After all, both words begin with a T.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Finally, any such workouts are effective half marathon training, but quite demanding. Don't do too many of those, there is a relevant injury risk.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>^I thought that was a pretty good descriptor, though perhaps I should do some more reading of the literature. The often frustrating thing about running and training is that there are elements of what we understand about training that are evidence-based, and then there is the "feel" of it. Sometimes you just gotta let it rip and see what happens.</p>

<hr />

<p>I discovered a runner/coach named John Lydiard who seems to have been a pioneer from the 60s of the ways we think about training now for distance racing (e.g., building an aerobic base, then building speed and strength, then "sharpening").</p>

<p>See this Reddit comment <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AdvancedRunning/comments/nglu42/comment/gyv8r6x/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button">here</a>, this article on Runner's World(<a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20825109/training-the-lydiard-way-28-weeks-to-a-pr/">"Training the Lydiard Way"</a>), and the John Kellogg article on page 14 of this USATF publication (<a href="https://trackandfieldnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/TC216-1.pdf">"Revving the Cardiovascular Engine"</a>).</p>

<hr />

<p>Teaching hurdles is a new thing for me this year. The best resource by far that I found is ACE Method Coaching (run by Mike Caton)</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1P3jB2YRfJySaeiXy56TYgNzFhHHbxEt6kEIZRHeqwzM/edit?gid=0#gid=0">Hurdle Technique &amp; Drill Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLKwbFInCAQIckoJorQmY_vXUiew5bypIL">An excellent playlist for general coaching</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>From Outside Online, <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/health/running/training/training-plans/blueprint-master-the-mile/?scope=anon">how to train for a 1600m race</a> (for an older runner like me!)</p>

<hr />

<p>Books or certifications I'm looking at to read or complete:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.fixingyourfeet.com/fixing-your-feet/">Fixing Your Feet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.coachjayjohnson.com/">Coach Jay Johnson</a> - for his XC and Track Training Systems</li>
<li><a href="https://www.usatf.org/programs/coaches/usatf-campus-online">USATF's online campus</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nfhslearn.com/courses/first-aid-health-and-safety">NFHS First Aid Health and Safety</a></li>
<li><a href="https://acemethodcoaching.com/product/bronze-bundle/">ACE Method's Hurdle Mastery series</a></li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Best of 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-12-27 13:15:29</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Another year, another review. I'll be 100% honest, I both want and don't want to do this right now. Elaine just got back from the hospital yesterday after an extreme migraine that presented with stroke-like symptoms. I want to remember this year though, and don't want this to get lost in the static. Maybe another post will be forthcoming, but I don't know how much I want to relive a somewhat traumatic Christmas Day.</p>

<h1>Music</h1>

<p>2024 was Kendrick's year, no question.</p>

<h3>Favorite Songs</h3>

<p>Yet again, I don't feel like Spotify Wrapped captured the musical year for me. It may have even been worse than <a href="https://cbaca.blog/best-of-2023.html">last year</a>. But! Regardless of what they said I mostly listened to, I feel like we had a pretty great musical year. Here's another Spotify playlist of my favorites:</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/0NF9z5n8gXskwcb1w26HD7?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="352" frameBorder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3>Favorite Albums (and a word about big "moments")</h3>

<p>The beginning of the year was filled with boygenius's <em>the record</em>, and Tyler Childers's <em>Live on Red Barn Radio I &amp; II</em>. </p>

<p>After that, I think it was primarily a hip-hop year, with some incredible releases:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Ultra 85</em> - Logic</li>
<li><em>Chromakopia</em> - Tyler, the Creator</li>
<li><em>Bando Stone and the New World</em> - Childish Gambino</li>
<li><em>Samurai</em> - Lupe Fiasco</li>
</ul>

<p>and OF COURSE:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>GNX</em> - Kendrick Lamar</li>
</ul>

<p>The Kendrick and Drake beef was the highlight of the year. It's been talked about a bajillion times online and I do not need to repeat the story. But waking up every day or every other day for over a week to new diss tracks, and watching Kendrick just completely dominate from "eupohoria" forward was thrilling.</p>

<p>Three other albums worth mentioning:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Weezer (blue)</em> - Weezer (there was a 30 year deluxe release and it was fun to rediscover the album)</li>
<li><em>No Name</em> - Jack White (this album just absolutely rips)</li>
<li><em>Beethoven Blues</em> - Jon Batiste</li>
</ul>

<h1>Movies</h1>

<p>The standout movies this year for me were:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Dune, part II</em> - movie of the year for me. The sandworm scene, the end fight scene, and of course Paul's speech when he fully embraces his role as the Lisan al-Gaib (that scene gives me goosebumps every time I watch it)</li>
<li><em>Wicked</em> - I'm starting to realize just how much I like musicals</li>
<li><em>Midsommar</em> - Not released this year, but we watched it for the first time. Insane movie. Not a "favorite" but it really stuck in my head.</li>
<li><em>Deadpool and Wolverine</em> - just super fun</li>
<li><em>Wild Robot</em> - also fun, and quite touching</li>
<li><em>Wonka</em> - continuing the Timothée love</li>
<li><em>Poor Things</em> - So strange. Another "not a favorite" but it stuck in my head movie.</li>
<li><em>Interstellar</em> - IMAX re-release. It was amazing and overwhelming. Standout scene was the moment when Cooper had to re-align the two spaceships. It was <em>almost</em> too much to watch.</li>
</ul>

<h1>TV</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>The Penguin</em></li>
<li><em>No Good Deed</em></li>
<li><em>Nobody Wants This</em></li>
<li><em>Sopranos (season 1)</em> - I watched this when I had the flu in September, great TV.</li>
<li><em>The Joy of Painting with Bob Ross</em> - Silly, but we turn this on for Cooper every time we leave the house, and then we inadvertently watch it for one or two episodes at some point during the day.</li>
<li><em>Seinfeld</em></li>
<li><em>Six Feet Under</em> - we're still in the middle of watching season 1, but it's good
-<em>Love is Blind, seasons 6 and 7</em> - trash, but great trash?</li>
<li><em>3 Body Problem</em> - not as good as the book, of course, but fun anyway</li>
</ul>

<h1>Books</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>Shift</em> - Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Dust</em> - Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Four Thousand Weeks</em> - Oliver Burkeman</li>
<li><em>On the Edge of the Dark Sea of Darkness</em> - Andrew Peterson</li>
<li><em>Station Eleven</em> - Emily St. John Mandel</li>
<li><em>Cibola Burn</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Nemesis Games</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Babylon's Ashes</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Moonbound</em> - Robin Sloan</li>
<li><em>Fellowship of the Ring</em> - J.R.R. Tolkien</li>
<li><em>When We Cease to Understand the World</em> - Benjamin Labatut</li>
<li><em>Demon Copperhead</em> - Barbara Kingsolver</li>
<li><em>Piranesi</em> - Susanna Clarke</li>
<li><em>The Silent Patient</em> - Alex Michaelides</li>
</ul>

<h1>Everything Else</h1>

<p>Notable events and things from the year:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>We started attending <a href="asd.church">All Saints Dallas</a> around July of this year, and this is the first time is a family in a few years that we have all <em>wanted</em> to be attending somewhere regularly.</p></li>
<li><p>This was my first year coaching cross country in a long time. There were so many cool moments, and it was great to be able to coach a team again. Despite some of its difficulties, coaching brings me joy in a way that many things do not.</p></li>
<li><p>I spent such a large portion of the year training for the Dinosaur Valley Endurance Run (25K). Lots and lots of weeks with lots and lots of miles. But I felt so strong and good overall. To make a long story short, I was going to run on the Saturday of the race, but nerves got the better of me, and I was up until about 2:30 AM. I was so lucky that the race organizers allowed shorter distances to run on either Saturday or Sunday without pre-notification, so I punted, moved to Sunday, and ran a great race (4th overall, 1st in my age group).</p></li>
<li><p>We took a little weekend trip to Kansas City in July to visit some good friends up there. It was filled with good food, lake relaxing, and just space to be friends. (Also, I'll probably always remember this was the weekend of the attempted assassination. Wild.)</p></li>
<li><p>We have a 13 year old 😵‍💫</p></li>
<li><p>I shot my first ducks this year! Hoping to become (albeit intermittently) something of a small game hunter in the coming years.</p></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>There was, of course, so much more. I'll address a couple of those things in the looking forward to 2025 post. But also, you just can't capture a year in words. These are the things that stand out now. As always, I'm grateful for another year with my beautiful family, another year of joy, sadness, grief, excitement, and all the things in between.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>A Quote On 'Seeing'</title>
            <pubDate>2024-12-12 11:41:29</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/a-quote-on-seeing.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/a-quote-on-seeing.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>A long quote incoming:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>And where do the symbols come from? From the years of childhood drawing during which every person develops a system of symbols. The symbol system becomes embedded in the memory, and the symbols are ready to be called out, just as you called them out to draw your childhood landscape.</p>
    
    <p>...</p>
    
    <p>To sum up, adult students beginning in art generally do not really see what is in front of their eyes -- That is, they do not perceive in the special way required for drawing. They take note of what's there, and quickly translate the perception into words and symbols mainly based on the symbol system developed throughout childhood and on what they know about the perceived object.</p>
    
    <p>What is the solution to this dilemma? Psychologist Robert Ornstein suggests that in order to draw, the artist must 'mirror' things or perceive them exactly as they are. Thus, you must set aside your usual verbal categorizing and turn your full visual attention to what you are perceiving -- to all of its details and how each detail fits into the whole configuration. In short, you must see the way an artist sees.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--Betty Edwards, <em>The New Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain</em>, p. 82</p>

<p>Edwards is obviously talking about pragmatic "how" of drawing here, but I found this quote remarkably in line with philosophical inquiry regarding seeing the world "as it is" and how our pre-built categories affect what it is we perceive when we look at the world.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 7 - 2 to 15 Nov 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-11-18 10:02:41</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-7-2-to-15-nov-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-7-2-to-15-nov-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>Duck hunting was such a blast! It's been about a week now since I went, but man I had such a good time. We did an evening hunt that was really just more of a practice run for the morning (no ducks were killed, only shot at). But it was a good chance to get a feel for the rhythm of things, what to expect, and so on. In the morning, we arrived at the hunting location at about 5 AM, walked in with our layout blinds, got all set up and brushed in, and waited for shooting light. The stars were truly magnificent -- light pollution is pretty bad where I am so it was wonderful to see (and remember) what the stars really look like. I walked away with three birds from the hunt, and I was the first to kill one that day, so it was a special experience for sure. Now I'm trying to figure out how to get back out where I'm at. The closest location is Lake Bardwell, which is not difficult to get to.</p>

<p>Other than that, things have just seemed to be transitioning with the season, I think. My training cycle is nearly complete (the Dino Valley 25K is this Saturday), so I moved into my training taper period last week. I'm excited and nervous, but mostly excited I think!</p>

<p>The days blur together somewhat from the last two weeks -- there has just been a lot of that "everyday busy-ness" thing going on. Cassandra was here for about 5 days, which was great. </p>

<p>P's 11th birthday is TODAY! 11 years with that kiddo, and it has been a ride, let me tell you. I find myself thankful for her, though, more and more. We went rock climbing yesterday to celebrate and she did a lot of fear-conquering, which was really neat to see.</p>

<p>I'm currently reading Barbara Kingsolver's <em>Demon Copperhead</em>, which is sad and a bit tragic but with which I feel a strange familiarity. I did not grow up an orphan, but the setting of southern poverty gives it a sense of reality to me.</p>

<p>Personally, I'm trying and trying to stay away from general media, news, and feeds as much as possible. A habit this sticky is hard to break, though. Chrome is often deleted from my phone but I re-download it for practical reasons, and then that often leads to checking out Reddit or something else for a few minutes, so I haven't been fully disconnected. The goal is to continue to figure this out, however, because the moments when I'm not actively engaged with media and feeds are much calmer. My blog and the RSS reader are a much different story -- this continues to be a place where I want to be. It's the kind of web I want.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Unforunately, I think the Prius's power brakes are going out. A strange noise occurs when pushing down the brakes at a full stop, and the Prius forums indicate that this is a known issue on my Prius version. It usually results in a hefty repair bill, which will likely cost more than the car is worth. The long story short is, we need to take it into the dealer.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I don't want to say "nothing" here but... nothing I can think of, at least.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>