<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Spotify the Time Machine</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-23 09:08:14</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/spotify-the-time-machine.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/spotify-the-time-machine.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>One of my consistent tech habits that I'm actually glad about is my obsession with trying to keep up with new music that I come across. It's not always "new" music -- more "new to me." Generally, if I come across an album or single or something that I think I might enjoy, I throw it into this month's folder in Spotify.</p>

<p>Every year, at the beginning of the year, I make a new playlist folder titled "New Music [insert year]." Within that folder, each month gets its own playlist, so, January 2023 all the way through December 2023, for example.</p>

<p>I'm not willy-nilly about what goes in the playlists, but I'm also not overly picky. Basically, I scour the New Releases every Friday to see if anything has released that's interesting (Blink-182's new album is a good example of this). If it looks like something I might listen to, it gets thrown into this month's playlist. I also use these playlists for music that's new to me, so anytime I come across an album or single song I enjoy, I move the album into this month's playlist as well.</p>

<p>This has actually been really fun, because I can look back on a year and see what "stuck" and what didn't I can also find stuff that I meant to listen to but forgot that I found. This helps to keep me paying attention to new music as well. I wouldn't call myself obsessed with music, but I certainly love it about 1000x more than podcasts or audiobooks.</p>

<p>I was also thinking this morning about how much I enjoy the fact that I can look back at older years and see what caught my attention. There is plenty of music that was released back in 2017, for example, that I listened to a lot that year but then it slowly faded away. This morning, I'm listening to the soundtrack from the iPhone game <em>Monument Valley 2</em>. The soundscapes are great; it's synth-y, emotional, and instrumental, so it makes for great focus music. But on top of that, my yearly new music playlists turn into a bit of a time machine. Not to put too fine a point on it, but there is some sense of being "taken back" to that time when I first discovered the album, and all the subsequent times I listened to it.</p>

<p>There are lots of ways current tech lends itself to poor habits of the mind. But sometimes, I do think new technology makes our lives just a little bit better. This focused way of using Spotify is definitely something I appreciate.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Not Informed, but Stimulated</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-20 16:51:19</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/not-informed-but-stimulated.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/not-informed-but-stimulated.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>If you’re reading the news several times a day, you’re not being <em>informed</em>, you’re being <em>stimulated</em>. Try giving yourself a break from it. Look at this stuff at wider intervals, and in between sessions, give yourself time to think and assess. </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--Alan Jacobs, <a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/periodicity/">"Periodicity"</a></p>

<p>A good point in a week of terrible news. Leaving social media (including, for the most part, Reddit) has been really beneficial for my mental well being. And I often wonder about the notion of "being informed." Being informed <em>about what</em>? <em>By whom</em>? And <em>for what purpose</em>? </p>

<p>With what seems to be a literally insane amount of misinformation (read: lies and ignorant claims) being promulgated on social media platforms and news sites, I'm just not convinced it is good or right for any of us to be aware on an hour by hour basis about what's going on outside of our immediate, local communities.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Addiction to Audience</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-18 10:05:52</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/addiction-to-audience.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/addiction-to-audience.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>every tweet, every selfie is a chance to virtue signal, an opportunity to market yourself as someone — pundit, guru, genius, or goofball. There is no other way of putting it — we are addicted to the idea of an audience. When we go online, we are programmed to react to engagement triggers — likes, shares, retweets, hearts, and thumb-ups. Social and this addiction of audience have made us addicted to something even harder to give up once tasted: a constant feeling of self-importance. To live in this post-social future, one has to embrace ideas that are the antithesis of self-importance. After two decades of being trained by micro-dosing on dopamine, I am not sure we can!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>--Om Malik, <a href="https://om.co/2022/01/12/can-we-ever-become-post-social/">"Can We Ever Become Post-Social?"</a></p>

<p>Like I said yesterday, the internet's transformations over the last two decades has formed us into not wanting to write or create or do on the web without an audience. And that sucks.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Status Update - 10.17.23</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-17 08:25:54</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/status-update-10-17-23.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/status-update-10-17-23.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Just because I feel like blogging. I was listening to a talk (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DNwaChz8xRY">here</a>) where the speaker was talking about personal blogs and how we should think about them. They said -- among many things -- that one shouldn't apologize for not blogging... a trend I see all over the place. People starting blogs, abandoning them for a while because life gets in the way or whatever, and their next post starts with "Sorry I haven't posted in a while..." I remember doing this all the way back in 2004/5/6, because I knew there were at least a few visitors to the blog daily or weekly.</p>

<p>The truth is, if I want this blog to be <em>my</em> space and not a space for other people, I need to stop with that shit. I probably ought to feel free to curse, to say anything, to say nothing. No one's reading, and if they are, I'm not writing for them. I want this space to be more than some digital area where I'm trying to build something. As much as I think there are good things that come out of big tech (without Google and Microsoft and all these other big companies, there are so many things we <em>wouldn't</em> have), I also think what they have provided come with a price. We now can't blog without a thought about an ~audience~, about building a ~brand~, about how we could ~monetize~ something like this.</p>

<p>That fucking sucks. Because I'm just a human being that wants to live life, to learn cool things and remember the things I was thinking about. I want to blog regularly and <em>enjoy</em> it, without a thought about what it will mean to anyone else but me.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Anyway, as for a status update -- lots of things going on:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>We sold our house! We lived in the same place for nearly a decade. When we moved in, we had to borrow money for a down payment, and could barely afford monthly payments. Lyla was 2 and Paisley was 4 months old. Elaine and I had just gone through a little bit of hell in our relationship, and my stepdad was diagnosed with cancer that same month. We renovated the entire interior of the house over our time there, did lots of things in the backyard, but never could quite get our hands around landscaping. That house saw us grow and change and live. It was beautiful. We all miss it dearly already but it was also time to let it go.</li>
<li>We are in the middle of a house purchase. The beginning of this was a bit of a debacle, but we seem to be back on track, and we're hoping to move in around November 9. There's a bit of a familiar feeling money-wise. We have a lot of equity we can push into the new house, but our monthly payment will definitely be a good bit more -- we're reaching but if my spreadsheet reads right, we should be good (sweating/smiling emoji).</li>
<li>I'm still a data analyst working for a digital ad agency -- most of my work revolves around web and paid media analytics. It can be frustrating some days, but I've also learned SO much so far. I'm finding that I'm interested in the nuts and bolts of the job more and more. This is leading me to think about data engineering more often.</li>
<li>I beat TOTK recently, though still also playing it on and off because there are lots of side quests and it's pretty relaxing.</li>
<li>I recently reread <em>The Three Body Problem</em> and <em>The Dark Forest</em> by Cixin Liu. Currently in the middle of <em>Death's End</em>. I don't reread books that often but I do enjoy the experience -- especially when books are complex like this trilogy.</li>
<li>Listening to a lot of <em>GUTS</em> by Olivia Rodrigo, which has grown on me. </li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>There is a lot more to say, but that's what is on my mind this morning. It felt good to get a little bird's-eye perspective. Assuming I'm good about making this a priority, which I'd genuinely like to do, I'd like to dive a little deeper on some other thoughts and ideas I think are worth exploring.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>QOTD - 9/6/2023</title>
            <pubDate>2023-09-06 09:38:47</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/qotd-9-6-2023.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/qotd-9-6-2023.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Real knowldge arises through confrontations with real things. Work, then, offers a broadly available premonition of philosophy. Its value, however, does not lie solely in pointing to some more rarefied experience. Rather, in the best cases, work may itself approach the good sough in philosophy, understood as a way of life: a community of those who desire to know.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--Matthew B. Crawford, <em>Shop Class as Soul Craft</em></p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>