<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Mary Harrington on 'Cringemaxxing'</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-13 09:56:31</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mary-harrington-on-cringemaxxing.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mary-harrington-on-cringemaxxing.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>But the absolute opposite of “cool” is not “uncool” but “cringe”: the wincing, jaw-clenching feeling you get when you do, or witness, something that you know the cool people would regard not just as uncool, but actively anti-cool: embarrassing, awkward, social Kryptonite. And while babies merely uncool, probably the most cringe thing you can do is going to church. There, you show up regularly to join a group of others you didn’t choose, and some of whom are probably old, or weird, or awkward, or otherwise uncool. The purpose of showing up is prayer: again, the opposite of cool, because to pray is to declare, openly, that you are not completely self-contained.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://reactionaryfeminist.substack.com/p/you-need-to-be-cringemaxxing">"You Need to be Cringemaxxing"</a></p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Blogs and Websites, Gaining Traction</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-11 09:32:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/blogs-and-websites-gaining-traction.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/blogs-and-websites-gaining-traction.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Some links on the state of personal websites and blogging:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many people are now desperately waiting for their Twitter archives, hoping that they’ll arrive before all their content is lost for good. For those who were using Twitter primarily for ephemeral chatter, all this isn’t that tragic. But for others, all their posts, conversations, and connections on the social network were a significant part of their online identity. They are about to lose a place on the Web into which they put a huge amount of time, attention, and energy...</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>So how about we make 2023 the year of the personal website? The year in which we launch our first site or redesign our old one, publish a little more often, and add RSS and Webmentions to our websites so that we can write posts back and forth. The year we make our sites more fussy, more quirky, and more personal. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://matthiasott.com/notes/the-year-of-the-personal-website">"The Year of the Personal Website"</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In those days, it was really simple. You could sign up for a free site on GeoCities, Yahoo, Blogger, Diaryland, or any of a number of free hosting sites that allowed you to set up your blog, get going with a WYSIWYG editor, and send your thoughts out into the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>For those who were a little more adventurous, you could purchase an actual domain name, pay for website hosting, and go for it that way...</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Bring back personal blogging in 2023. We, as a web community, will be all that much better for it. </p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/23513418/bring-back-personal-blogging">"Bring back personal blogging"</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The real web is built on links. Hyper ones, in fact. Links you can share on your website. Links you can send to your mates. Links to pages that can be indexed by search engines so you can find things again (in theory)...</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The real web, the small web, the indie web is amazing. Don't give Facebook and the rest of these clowns your content. Don't give them the time or your attention. Get a blog, a website, a Mastodon account, something you control, and share links to cool things you find.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>--<a href="https://rknight.me/blog/the-web-is-fantastic/">The Web is Fantastic</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>My only quibble (and I believe I've noted this before) is that personal blogging / having a personal website needs to be <em>easy</em> for regular people. If we're going to really push this personal web thing again, blogging shouldn't be inaccessible to people that aren't bent towards wanting to mess around with markup and code. I happen to like that stuff, so building this was fine for me. But there are other people with other thoughts that should find it ultra-easy, even frictionless, to build a site and a blog. To that end, here is a list of resources for doing so from Robb Knight:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://micro.blog/">Micro.blog</a> - $5 a month, has cross-posting to a whole load of places
  <a href="https://www.wordpress.com">Wordpress.com</a> - Free
  <a href="https://home.omg.lol/referred-by/robb">weblog.lol via omg.lol</a> - $20 a year also includes a &gt;Mastodon server, pastebin, profile page, now page, and some other cool things
  <a href="https://bearblog.dev/">Bear</a> - free
  <a href="https://neocities.org/">Neocities</a> - free
  <a href="https://pika.page/">Pika</a> - free
  <a href="https://www.11ty.dev/">Eleventy</a> if you want to dig into code and run your own thing.</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Richard Beck on Existentialism and Death</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-10 09:24:39</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/richard-beck-on-existentialism-and-death.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/richard-beck-on-existentialism-and-death.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>Because of these deep resonances with existentialism, I was also attracted to, and am still attracted to, the existentialism in the theology of Paul Tillich. I vibed for a long time with the existential "death of God" theologies. There was a similar attraction for me in the theologies of William Stringfellow and Arthur McGill. I've always been interested in theologians who place death (rather than guilt) at the existential center of the human predicament. Death is also what drew me toward Orthodox theology as seen in my book The Slavery of Death. </p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>--<a href="https://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2024/01/reclaiming-existential-theology-part-1.html">"Reclaiming Existential Theology: Part 1, The Guru of Death"</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Excited for this series from Richard Beck. His earlier work that sought to make connections between existential psychology and theology were compelling to me as I was working out a way to maintain faith in my mid-to-late twenties.</p>

<p>Also, I don't think I ever made such a clear connection in my head as to why both existentialism and "death" as a concept or centering idea were both equally fascinating to me. Death disturbs me much like it probably does anyone else, but I also find the idea of "memento mori" in the Stoic and Christian traditions incredibly helpful for orienting and reorienting one's life. And existentialism, especially the proto-existentialism of Kierkegaard still animates my reason for considering faith to be a primary part of my life. I just never connected the two together in such a clear way.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Six Arrows for Naydra</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-05 08:37:30</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/six-arrows-for-naydra.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/six-arrows-for-naydra.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Hell yeah. <a href="https://blacktaffy.bandcamp.com/album/six-arrows-for-naydra">"Six Arrows for Naydra"</a>, a reimagining of BOTW/TOTK music by Black Taffy. H/T <a href="https://austinkleon.substack.com/p/exact-revenge">Austin Kleon's 10 things Friday newsletter</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>A Lack of Theology</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-03 08:50:48</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/a-lack-of-theology.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/a-lack-of-theology.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I was doing my normal morning peel through my RSS feeds (thanks Feedly), and I realized my own personal blogosphere has changed significantly from what it was many years ago. A decade ago, or perhaps more, was somewhat of a golden age of the wider blogosphere in general and the Christian / theological blogosphere in particular.</p>

<p>It felt like important conversations were happening. Facebook and Twitter loomed large but those places were built to funnel you to the blogs that people operated on their own or as part of larger networks of blogs like Patheos (which from what I can tell is just a shitty website now, but I digress).</p>

<p>Anyway, to my point. I realized this morning that nearly my entire feed now is taken up by non-theological posts. Probably the most prominent ones I follow are culture and tech related -- e.g., Marginal Revolution, Manuel Morreale, Austin Kleon, Maggie Appleton, David Perrell, Alan Jacobs (though his can be somewhat theological at times).</p>

<p>In fact, the only explicitly theological blog that I can think of that I receive posts from regularly is Richard Beck's Experimental Theology blog. And the truth is I mostly skim his posts now. (Though I should  note that he is the most consistent blogger in my feed aside from Tyler Cowen. Richard Beck has a daily post on weekdays and hasn't missed, I think, ever since I started following him probably a decade ago.)</p>

<p>I wonder, does that say something about me? About the state of theological blogs in 2024? Maybe both. Even before I backed away from the faith trajectory I was on for several years though, I remember seeing the Christian blog scene fade away almost completely. Everything went to big walled gardens that were only accessible with a login somewhere.</p>

<p>But, enough about the tech side. I feel I have said my piece on this many times before and I don't need to always make the same point again and again. </p>

<p>The interesting thing that I think is happening to me is I'm feeling some renewed interest in exploring faith again. I know that it will not feel this way always. This feeling has ebbed and flowed in me just like this many times before. But, with the family Bible study we're doing weekly, listening to some Bible Project podcasts, and a little more open discussion with family about faith in general, I think my attention is turning yet again towards faith, theology, and philosophy. The "big questions" are still not only important to me but also still worth thinking about and wrestling with.</p>

<p>I don't want to make 2024 some big year where I'm trying to become another version of who I was before, or make some outlandish goals that are impractical. But maybe 2024 can be somewhat of a comeback year for my own orientation/lens for how I perceive life.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>