<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>On Losing an Election</title>
            <pubDate>2024-11-06 08:05:21</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/on-losing-an-election.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/on-losing-an-election.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Talking with Elaine this morning after seeing the results, I had a (re-)realization that my daily life and my internet media consumption are in such strong contrast. I live in MAGA country (always have, basically, at least here in Texas). I'm surrounded by committed Republican voters who generally assume that everyone around them votes the same as they do.</p>

<p>But my internet consumption is clearly, <em>clearly</em> left of that. By a wide margin. Despite the fact that I live in MAGA-world, I really thought there was a good shot at a Democrat win across the board. (That is clearly <em>not</em> what happened.)</p>

<p>Two things are on my mind this morning in response to this. Of course I have some political opinions and have some generalized anxiety about how the next four year presidential term will play out. But even more than that:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>It's become increasingly clear (and stark after this morning) that my current media consumption habits are simply not serving me. Scrolling through Reddit feeds a few times a day, checking NYT and NPR, etc. are simply not giving me an accurate view of reality. They are also not helping my mental state... probably at all. I'm going to make it a goal over the coming weeks to devise a plan to change these habits for myself. I want to be a kind person, a good citizen, a loving husband and father, and a thoughtful, <em>well-informed</em> human being.</p></li>
<li><p>Richard Beck has been in my RSS feed for years. While I don't read everything he writes, there are occasions where he writes something that genuinely hits home and makes me feel sane. <a href="https://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2024/11/planting-gardens-in-babylon-on-how-to.html">This, from a sermon he wrote years ago</a>, titled "How to Lose an Election," is a gentle reminder that human history is peppered with situations where they lack political power (long quote incoming):</p></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>In my Bushnell talk, one of the points I made comes from Jeremiah 29. Some of the Israelites have returned home from their Babylonian exile. But many remain behind in Babylon. These write to the prophet Jeremiah asking if they should come home. But Jeremiah writes back to say, no, you should stay in Babylon. And not just stay, to multiply and thrive:</p>
    
    <p>Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, to all the exiles whom I have sent into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon: Build houses and live in them; plant gardens and eat what they produce. Take wives and have sons and daughters; take wives for your sons, and give your daughters in marriage, that they may bear sons and daughters; multiply there, and do not decrease. But seek the welfare of the city where I have sent you into exile, and pray to the Lord on its behalf, for in its welfare you will find your welfare. </p>
    
    <p>Seek the welfare of the city, for it its welfare you will find your welfare. Crucially, the Israelites remain in Babylon as a marginalized, disenfranchised, exilic people. They do not control Babylon, nor will they ever control Babylon. Political power is not in their hands. And yet, there is work to do! Seek the welfare of the city.</p>
    
    <p>And let's be clear on this point, this is Babylon we are talking about. Babylon, the epitome of wickedness, oppression, injustice, violence, and evil in Biblical history and imagination. The point here is that the People of God thrive in places of political marginalization. The People of God thrive in Babylon. So there's no excuse for us not to thrive, even if we lost the election. No matter the outcome today, there is good, creative, generative, and beautiful work to do.</p>
    
    <p>How do you lose an election? It's simple.</p>
    
    <p>You plant gardens in Babylon.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>So how am I planting a garden? Well,  I'll probably literally plant a garden, but I'm raising my kiddos a certain way, I'm disengaging from the shit show that is national politics, and I'm looking to the community around me to build a life together.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 6 - 26 Oct to 1 Nov 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-11-01 15:50:34</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-6-26-oct-to-1-nov-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-6-26-oct-to-1-nov-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>The big thing this week has been prepping for my first duck hunt (🦆)! I went last year with Zack right after Thanksgiving, but didn't have a license so I was just a bystander. We didn't bag anything last year either, so I'm hoping this is a good little trip for me. I'm SO excited, this is an experience out of my norm. I finished up my hunter's education, got my license, and set up my shotgun/accessories situation.</p>

<p>Halloween was also a fun time! I dressed as Miguel from Coco, and the girls were traditional skeletons from Dia de los Muertos. Lots of folks from the girls' school came over and we ate, passed out candy, and the girls were able to go trick or treating with their friends.</p>

<p>I'm getting reallllll close to the race (I think I'm right at 3 weeks out). My legs are a bit tired and I'm definitely feeling worn down some from training. But overall I think I am ready for the race -- my goal is still to place in the top 3 overall, but I'll be happy with a good race no matter what.</p>

<p>I took the step of deleting internet browser access from my phone, just to mitigate access to stupid feeds and news or whatever. It hasn't fully removed my proclivity for doomscrolling, but it's definitely better than it was, and my mood is anecdotally better as well.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Got the grass mowed last weekend, and that should be the last big mow for the season, thank goodness.</p>

<p>Just wanting to get through this next week mostly -- should be quick as I'm taking Thursday and Friday off, and we're hunting next Monday.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>Just bingeing <a href="https://www.themeateater.com/shows/duck-camp-dinners">Duck Camp Dinners</a>, Jean-Paul Bourgeois is the man, and it's just hyping me up for hunting season.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 5 - 19 to 25 Oct 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-10-25 12:57:17</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-5-19-to-25-oct-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-5-19-to-25-oct-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>Personally, not much activity happening, which is to say: this was basically a routine sort of week. That's not a bad thing, but I can't think of much that was "of note." </p>

<p>I'm entering the final phase of training, which means I hit another 12 miler last Saturday, and will move into my final two long runs before my taper for the Dino Valley 25K.</p>

<p>I started reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/When-We-Cease-Understand-World/dp/1681375664"><em>When We Cease to Understand the World</em></a> by Benjamin Labatut. I was reading <em>Persepolis Rising</em>, the 7th book in The Expanse saga, but I'm either just not ready for the book or I'm bored with the characters. In theory, a long, sprawling epic story is interesting and consuming. In practice (maybe it's just these authors), this is along time to spend with these characters, and I'm finding the writing style a bit... mediocre?</p>

<p>I did receive some new woodworking tools in this week! I think this completes the "basic collection" that I need to be able to <em>actually</em> start making things. This week's haul included a block plane, a shoulder plane, a coping saw, and some more measuring/marking tools. My first goal is to build <a href="https://www.freeonlinewoodworkingschool.com/bookstand">this book stand</a>, and perhaps a dovetail box after that. We'll see where it takes me! I do think project-based work, even if I'm bad at it, is going to be the best way forward here to gain the skills I'm currently lacking.</p>

<p>Work was work-y. Nothing to see here.</p>

<p>P is doing really great. I'm seeing so much growth in her over the last couple of months. I think Elaine and I are both feeling a little reticent to "look at it straight on" in fear of things returning to how they used to be. We had years of tough, and months of REALLY tough. But there are signs from her that things are genuinely looking up and hopeful.</p>

<p>Lyla and I watched Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows part 1 last night. We finished the entire book series months and months ago, and have slowly eked our way through the movies.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Same as last week.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I learned today about a music genre called "shoegaze," which seems to be described best by listening to "Mayonaise" by Smashing Pumpkins. I've been looking for a genre that encapsulates the feel of that song for a long time, so this'll be  a fun rabbit hole (<a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/37i9dQZF1DX6ujZpAN0v9r?si=2be64f8294614e0b">Spotify playlist to match</a>).</p>

<p>Lots of stuff I'm running into re: avoiding news consumption and online feeds. Wherever this is coming from... I should probably listen. We're less than two weeks out from the election, and the truth is I've been feeling the need to step back from even Reddit/NYT consumption, which are the last vestiges of daily news/daily feeds in my routine. </p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Quotes on News Consumption</title>
            <pubDate>2024-10-23 14:15:57</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/quotes-on-news-consumption.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/quotes-on-news-consumption.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>We are not rational enough to be exposed to the
    news-mongering press. It is a very dangerous
    thing, because the probabilistic mapping we get
    from consuming news is entirely different from
    the actual risks that we face. Watching an airplane
    crash on television is going to change your attitude
    toward that risk regardless of its real probability,
    no matter your intellectual sophistication. If you
    think you can compensate for this bias with the
    strength of your own inner contemplation, you are
    wrong. Bankers and economists – who have
    powerful incentives to compensate for newsborne hazards – have shown that they cannot. The
    only solution: cut yourself off from news
    consumption entirely.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--Rolf Dobelli, <a href="https://gwern.net/doc/culture/2010-dobelli.pdf">"Avoid News: Toward a Healthy News Diet"</a></p>

<p>^ Written in 2010; I'd argue in 2024 this is just as applicable to infinite-feed sites. (Reddit being my personal number one culprit that I'm having trouble kicking.)</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>As I've written before, alarming news is nothing new, but the central place the news has come to occupy in many people's psychological worlds is certainly novel. Because of how digital media works – though also because the news developments themselves are legitimately huge – these global dramas start to feel like life's centre of gravity, with the immediate worlds of family, job and neighborhood relegated to the periphery.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--Oliver Burkeman, <a href="https://ckarchive.com/b/r8u8hoh8eeov">"Becoming News-Resilient"</a></p>

<p>One of the things making me think about this right now is just how much I feel like my actual view of reality has been/is being warped by news &amp; media feeds. I know it's election season and these feelings are especially potent for everyone right now. I just want to approach life both calmly and <em>realistically</em>. One may argue that being informed helps with at least the latter, but I find that doubtful.</p>

<p>Lord grant me strength to avoid the bullshit.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 4 - 5 to 18 Oct 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-10-19 12:01:39</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-4-5-to-18-oct-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-4-5-to-18-oct-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>Even as I start writing this, I'm realizing how difficult it is to reach back two weeks ago to try to remember what was happening. Here's what I can remember:</p>

<p>The big thing was the end of the cross country season! We made our way to Georgetown last Friday (why I didn't write a weeknote last week), and the junior high and high school teams performed really well. We had a high school girl win her whole division in state, and lots of other runners place and medal in the top 8. Proud of the kids... and also happy the season is over :)</p>

<p>We are in the process of refinancing our mortage -- which we seem to have done at just the right time as rates seem to be rising (??) again. Everything looks like it's going to go through, and we're going to save something like $270 per month on our payment, which is really cool.</p>

<p>I finished a woodworking project! Using <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lPiMjv7lkqI">Rex Krueger's guide to making a Roman-style workbench</a>, I was able to complete this over the course of working on it on and off for the last couple weeks. I made a lot of mistakes, it doesn't exactly look pretty, but it works! Which is a pretty good feeling.</p>

<p>Once I get a couple more work holding options for the bench and a few more tools (said every woodworking hobbyist ever), I think I'll actually be able to make some of the projects that have caught my eye over the last year or so.</p>

<p>Work has been... fine. There is nothing inherently <em>bad</em> about it. I still enjoy my team, LOVE the flexibility, etc. But I'm realizing that I have hit a strange plateau point. There aren't things that I could come across, as of now, that I couldn't just handle with relative ease on my own. That has historically been a challenging time for me in any job I've held, so this is probably going to be a recurring theme until I can figure out how to hit that "sweet spot" at work again.</p>

<p>Training for the Dino Valley 25K is in its most intense training block. I hit 12 miles this morning, and have another few weeks of ramped intensity before I can back down into a taper. My legs are feeling it, but I'm feeling pretty good about my chances of placing top 3 overall. But we will see! Goal A is top 3, goal B is sub 2:04, goal C is finish with a smile on my face.</p>

<p>Elaine and I have had the chance to take every Wednesday to spend time together. Every other Wednesday is our "pastorate" (All Saints Dallas's version of small groups), and on the off weeks we are taking a date night. It has been wonderful.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Currently working on the color run at the girls' school. My job is to create the course, procure cones, and just think about the logistics of the run itself.</li>
<li>I <em>think</em> there is still time to plant the fall garden (seems like it may be a warmer-than-average winter), so we should probably get on that this weekend.</li>
<li>I really need to mow, but... lol.</li>
</ul>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<ul>
<li>The new Bon Iver EP: <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/2Cwxsws0uZcu61gliYLOEm?si=-dtr6l14Q2mAS3u3HO4scQ">SABLE,</a></li>
<li>Watching The Penguin. Maybe not <em>excellent</em> but it is fun.</li>
<li>Finished <a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/moonbound/introduction/"><em>Moonbound</em></a> by Robin Sloan, recommended.</li>
<li>This PBS show, <a href="https://www.pbs.org/video/woodwrights-shop-roman-work-bench/"><em>The Woodwright's Shop</em></a> &lt;-- This is a link to a specific episode where Chris Shwarz is demonstrating how to use a Roman workbench, but other episodes are fun too. Boy do I love public television sometimes.</li>
<li>There is a new coffee shop in our little town that is <em>excellent</em>: <a href="https://bloomandpour.com/">Bloom &amp; Pour</a>. We know one of the owners, and I'm so happy Waxahachie has a space like this, finally.</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>