<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Moving Backwards</title>
            <pubDate>2024-08-29 11:13:26</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/moving-backwards.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/moving-backwards.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I did two things this week that might seem counterintuitive:</p>

<p>1) I moved all the music (that I really wanted to keep, anyway) from an old hard drive to my Macbook and my iPhone.
2) I have reverted to using corded headphones.</p>

<p>On 1 -- I kind of did this on a whim. Elaine needed a hard drive, and I rememberd that we had a 1TB lying around that had a backup of my old Macbook on it. When I was looking in there to clean things up for her, I saw all my old music and thought it would be fun to have access to on a regular basis. Over the last few years, I've been collecting CDs every once in a while. Usually when we go to Half Price Books, I spend the first 10 - 15 minutes of the visit perusing the CD area just to see if there's anything I want to add to the collection.</p>

<p>Anyway, I pulled all that music over to the Macbook, added album art to make things a little more colorful and fun, and then transferred everything over to my phone. I still have access to Spotify and won't likely get rid of it. But you know, there's just <em>something</em> about listening to music that you know is yours. Of course this also leads to listening to full albums a little more often as well (I was already trying to do that, but Spotify makes it so easy to get lost in algo-shuffle). Who knows? Maybe one day I'll ditch Spotify and go back to just my owned collection. There's something good in that, I just don't quite know what it is yet.</p>

<p>On 2 -- this is a little more of just a pragmatic move. My AirPods Pro are starting to give up the ghost a little bit. They still work, and the battery's ok. But if you have them in and you move around at all, both headphones are starting to crackle. What's frustrating about that is that this is an indicator that this tech is essentially "disposable." I have corded headphones that have worked for YEARS. Are they somewhat less convenient because I'm physically tied to my device? Sure. But they also never fail to connect to my phone or laptop. And the sound is as good as (or better than) my wireless headphones. We're literally talking about the free headphones that used to come with phones.</p>

<p>Two ways I moved "backwards" this week. But I think there is just a little more joy there than infinite choice and the lack of a tether. Maybe what's shiny isn't always what's best.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>What I'm Up To - August 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-08-24 14:43:38</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/what-i-m-up-to-august-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/what-i-m-up-to-august-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well, August is about two-thirds over, and it's definitely been a bit of a whirlwind. After a long, somewhat leisurely (and not <em>too</em> hot) summer, August came out swinging.</p>

<p>No worries though. I was feeling a little anxious about it in the weeks leading up to August 1, knowing what was coming. As we've gotten into the groove of things, however, it doesn't feel as unsettled as it did at the end of July / beginning of August.</p>

<p>The first week of August brought the beginning of the cross country season, and I'm coaching both the middle and high school teams (four high schoolers, six junior highers). We practice on Mondays, Wednesdays, and some Fridays, and we just had our first meet last week. It was incredibly hot, but the team did well all things considered (two HS girls placed top ten in their races). As always, I love coaching even if it means giving up a little time in the evenings to get to sleep early. Practice starts at 6:30, so Lyla and I wake up around 5:50 AM on those days.</p>

<p>In a similar mode, I also started seriously training for the <a href="https://www.theactivejoe.com/dinosaurvalley">Dinosaur Valley Endurance Run (25K)</a>. Goal time here is just around 2hrs or so, which would be an 8 minute mile. Of course this isn't road running so we'll see how things go. But training is going well. This past week was the fourth week of official training, and I'm feeling pretty strong.</p>

<p>The girls started school about two weeks ago as well, and I'm happy and proud to say the both got back into the swing of things pretty quickly. We had a little bit of anxiety going into the year after some school difficulty last year, but Pais has really grabbed the reins and seems happy to be back. We also really seem to be rounding a corner with her -- she's much quicker to calm back down after heated moments, and we've really worked hard to move into problem solving mode when things are overwhelming or stressful.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago I built a new raised bed for the garden, and it was finally "cool" enough (read, not hellish) today to bring the bed to the back, pull out some of the older spring beds, and fill the container with new soil. The soil looks great, and I'm excited to get the fall garden going. Right now we're planning for carrots, broccoli, garlic, and maybe sweet potatoes? We'll see.</p>

<p>Finally, we've made a switch for our church home. After about two years of just recovering at St. Paul Episcopal in Waxahachie after the stint at LIDE, we felt it was time to find a place where we could feel more at home, and perhaps get more involved. After some debate as a family, we decided to try <a href="https://asd.church/">All Saints Dallas</a>, an Anglican church out of the AMIA. They seem to have an equivalent focus on liturgy, scripture, and matters of the Spirit, which is a refreshing thing to hear, and seems to sort of "check all the boxes" for the different desires in our family. I think we're ready to try this place out long term, and it's exciting (and a little anxiety-inducing, if I'm honest) to try to wade back out into these waters.</p>

<p>Life feels a little tiring, a little challenging, but I think for the first time in a long time, I feel truly good about the direction we're going as a family. We're finding rest where we can, and pushing towards growth and new goals.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>The Weekly Scratchpad is Back, Baby</title>
            <pubDate>2024-07-17 12:10:03</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-weekly-scratchpad-is-back-baby.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-weekly-scratchpad-is-back-baby.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Long ago, in my university career years, I had a running template "scratchpad" that I used to keep track of projects I was running, to-do lists, links I ran into, thoughts, etc. For some reason, when I left that job for the second time (lol) and began working at home, I abandoned that method even though I actually found it quite useful. I have been experimenting with the Arc browser for a while, and it's held some of my website links. I also like the "Spaces" feature, which helps to differentiate what I'm working on. But I have some concerns about Arc (namely, their stupid push for <a href="https://cbaca.blog/further-down-the-road-towards-a-less-human-web.html">"AI search"</a>. Also, Manu <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/some-more-thoughts-on-tbc">posted some thoughts</a> recently about Arc that made me rethink my use of their product... mostly that it's not "reimagining the internet," but just a fancy Chromium wrapper.)</p>

<p>In any case, what I <em>don't</em> want is for my links and things that I find to get sucked into a separate product that I won't have access to if I decide to stop using it or whatever. This actually happened with my former scratchpad notes because I was using Evernote and stopped last year. And I really hate that exporting notes from Evernote is such a hassle.</p>

<p>All that to say, I'm trying out a new scratchpad process using Apple Notes. Obviously that doesn't exactly solve the problem of them being "stuck" in an application, but Apple is a little friendlier to privacy and I'd anticipate I could transfer all those notes if I wanted to.</p>

<p>In theory, the best solution would be my own homegrown notes system built on .txt or .md files, but I'm not really at the point where I want to build that myself so... here we are.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Feeling Alienated</title>
            <pubDate>2024-07-16 14:11:04</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feeling-alienated.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feeling-alienated.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>It's a strange thing, to go away for a weekend and enjoy yourself, but to come back feeling... deflated isn't the right word. It's somewhat akin to the Sunday scaries that plague many of us in our modern work-lives. But it's not necessarily related to work <em>itself</em>. The more I've thought about the feeling I'm coming away with after a long weekend visiting friends in Kansas City is alienation.</p>

<p>And I think what's really happening is that I was already feeling this -- it's just that being with these friends brought that feeling to the surface. We didn't do too much, but these friends of ours are the camping/outdoorsy type of folks, have a pretty fruitful garden, and generally hold values about nature that Elaine and I also hold. The difference is that we have struggled to live out those values in the same way that they do. On Saturday, we spent most of the day at Clinton Lake out in Lawrence, KS. It was a pretty special day but nothing spectacular; we took the boat out, swam, tubed, swam some more. </p>

<p>On Sunday we just hung out and chatted and used some fresh veggies from the garden for lunch and dinner. And on Monday we left. It wasn't like it was some epiphany that I had. But the whole weekend, I felt like some part of my soul that's been buried was becoming uncovered. Some piece of myself that I didn't quite forget about but was becoming forgotten. I just love being outside. I feel better when I am in the sun, among water and plants and there is just a tiny bit of unknown in the experience, some piece that I have no control over.</p>

<p>I think I simply realized that I spend so much of my time in comfort because it's so easy to craft and control what you encounter when you work in front of a screen, live in constant AC, and spend weekends just vegging because you're mentally tired from a week of all of the normal wearing down of life.</p>

<p>This feels a little rambly. And I know I'm not the first person in the world to explore human alienation from nature -- it's been a problem we've been thinking about since at least early modernity.</p>

<p>Mostly I just want to write this down so I can remember, and perhaps remind myself down the road. I want to encounter nature more, to be outside, to grow my own food sometimes, to make trips to the mountains and rivers and woods and remember that I am small.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Largely Shielded</title>
            <pubDate>2024-06-28 08:31:56</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/largely-shielded.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/largely-shielded.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Due to my insistence on avoiding social media (except for you Reddit, which, as a side note, I continue to return to like cigarette addict to his vape pen), I've been largely shielded from <em>~the discourse~</em>.</p>

<p>Instead, I have chosen to focus on other things. In the physical world, that's been my work, my family, my home, my health. Those things have proven far worthier of my attention than whatever bullshit is in the waterfalls of opinion online.</p>

<p>Digitally too, though. RSS and podcasts are the majority of my digital diet (and even then, not much on the podcast side). I listened to Ezra Klein talk on someone else's podcast about the debate last night, which is the extent of what I'll listen to on this topic. I have an opinion (or several) on the election and the candidates and what should happen.</p>

<p>But, you know, at the end of the day, even digitally I have other more important things to focus on. I like my blog and I want to maintain it. I am currently in the middle of part I of Nand2Tetris (This week is part 4 -- the Hack computer language. The last three weeks I've spent building logic gates, an ALU, and RAM... digitally of course), and I am actually really enjoying learning computer science from first principles onward. I think I'll have another post forthcoming on this, but I have been thinking a lot about what computers are, what digital information is, and because of those things, what we <strong>should</strong> use computers for. They are good for some things and not others, and that ultimately comes down to what we want to be and focus on as human beings.</p>

<p>Rabbit trailing a little bit. Suffice it to say, I think this week has shown me that digitally I have taken the right steps, and I want to keep moving in that direction.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>