<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Links 11-17-2022</title>
            <pubDate>Thu, 17 Nov 2022 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/links-11-17-2022.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/links-11-17-2022.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>Links Lurking in My Tabs</h2>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public/">Learn in Public</a></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>Whatever your thing is, make the thing you wish you had found when you were learning. Don’t judge your results by “claps” or retweets or stars or upvotes - just talk to yourself from 3 months ago. I keep an almost-daily dev blog written for no one else but me. Guess what? It’s not about reaching as many people as possible with your content. If you can do that, great, remember me when you’re famous. But chances are that by far the biggest beneficiary of you trying to help past you is future you. If others benefit, that’s icing.</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/series/domestic-cozy/">Domestic Cozy</a></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>Domestic cozy is in an attitude, emerging socioeconomic posture, and aesthetic, that is in many ways the antithesis of premium mediocrity. Unsurprisingly, it takes its cues from the marginal shadow behaviors of premium mediocrity. It finds its best expression in privacy, among friends, rather than in public, among strangers. It prioritizes the needs of the actor rather than the expectations of the spectator. It seeks to predictably control a small, closed environment rather than gamble in a large, open one. It presents a WYSIWYG facade to those granted access rather than performing in a theater of optics.</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/about.html#hardware">(Solar) Low-Tech Magazine</a></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Internet is not an autonomous being. Its growing energy use is the consequence of actual decisions made by software developers, web designers, marketing departments, publishers and internet users. With a lightweight, off-grid solar-powered website, we want to show that other decisions can be made.</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://homebrewserver.club/low-tech-website-howto.html">Homebrew Servers Club</a></li>
<li><a href="https://applerankings.com">Apple Rankings - finally... a definitive ranking of apples.</a></li>
<li><a href="https://linuxize.com/post/how-to-create-bash-aliases/">How to Create Bash Aliases</a></li>
<li><a href="https://vandenbran.de/post/2022-05-10-smol-web-lean-hosting/">My Small Web Setup</a></li>
</ol>

<h2>Books I Came Across This Week</h2>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/New-Dark-Age-Technology-Future-ebook/dp/B076NR24RZ/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=9781786635471&amp;linkCode=qs&amp;qid=1668542579&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-1">New Dark Age: Technology and the End of the Future</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Life-Code-Personal-History-Technology-ebook/dp/B01N4P12XJ/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=9780374711412&amp;linkCode=qs&amp;qid=1668542434&amp;s=books&amp;sr=1-1">Life in Code: A Personal History of Technology</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Everything-All-Time-Everywhere-Postmodern-ebook/dp/B08V5F6V5H/ref=tmm_kin_swatch_0?_encoding=UTF8&amp;qid=&amp;sr=">Everything, All the Time, Everywhere: How We Became Postmodern</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/We-Have-Never-Been-Modern/dp/0674948394/ref=sr_1_1?crid=15OG65TW087AK&amp;keywords=latour+we+have+never+been+modern&amp;qid=1668542794&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=latour+we+have+never+been+moder%2Cstripbooks%2C84&amp;sr=1-1">We Have Never Been Modern</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Bacteria-Bach-Back-Evolution-Minds-ebook/dp/B01HDSU2KY/ref=sr_1_1?crid=PP0G561ISSFL&amp;keywords=dennett+bach&amp;qid=1668542767&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=dennet+bach%2Cstripbooks%2C81&amp;sr=1-1">From Bacteria to Bach and Back: The Evolution of Minds</a> </li>
</ol>

<h2>Videos</h2>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qE77MbDnljA">Rsync - Corey Schafer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vpk_1gldOAE">SSH - Corey Schafer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=toBTPGfurLc">Rich Spirit - Kendrick Lamar</a></li>
</ol>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>TIL: 11-16-22</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/til-11-16-22.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/til-11-16-22.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well, today was a cool day. Since making the <a href="https://github.com/cdbaca/ssg">static site generator</a>, my goal has been to move the actual website content pages (plus styling/scripts) to my own VPS. I really wasn't sure where to start for a long time. But then I came across <a href="landchad.net">LandChad</a>. Now, the owner of this site holds to some views that I find pretty unagreeable. I won't link to his home page, because I went down that rabbit hole and it wasn't the most wholesome content... Nevertheless, he offers a ton of legitimately helpful advice on getting started with a virtual private server (VPS).</p>

<p>I made my way through grabbing a domain name (via NameCheap), purchasing droplet space from DigitalOcean, and away I went. Honestly, it really wasn't that bad. The kicker for most people, I think, is that you need some familiarity with Linux-based systems and working in the terminal rather than a GUI for managing files. But it was cool because I was able to set up nginx, which is the actual web server on the VPS that I'm using. I'd read about nginx before but it seemed like gobbledygook. The other thing I'll need to keep learning is how to use ssh effectively. SSH is a method for remoting into a non-local server or computer and managing files remotely. I found <a href="https://twitter.com/b0rk/status/1087936439470444544/photo/1">Julie Evans' cartoon</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vpk_1gldOAE">Corey Shafer's video on ssh</a> really hepful here.</p>

<p>Next goals will be to use the server for other things: maybe storage or automating tasks when my laptops are put away. I also want to host a full-blown Django or Flask app. This blog is built by hand on my local computer, and the domain you're reading is just plain ol' vanilla HTML/CSS/JS. Django will change that up with doing server-side work. I plan to use <a href="https://mattsegal.dev/simple-django-deployment-1.html">Matt Segal's Django deployment guide</a> for that.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Kierkegaard on Doing the Thing</title>
            <pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/kierkegaard-on-doing-the-thing.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/kierkegaard-on-doing-the-thing.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In what feels like another lifetime (or, as we Texans say, <em>a-whole-nother</em> lifetime), I spent a ton of time delving into Søren Kierkegaard's life and work. What especially interested me was his understanding of knowledge. For Kierkegaard, there was a difference between kinds of knowledge, which I think still bears out today.</p>

<p>Roughly, knowledge was broken into two broad categories that further splintered after that breakdown:</p>

<ol>
<li>Objective</li>
<li>Subjective</li>
</ol>

<p><strong>Objective knowledge</strong> could be either absolutely certain or relatively certain. I.e., mathematical and purely logical truths are knowable with 100% certainty. 2+2 can be nothing other than 4, and that must be true in any universe. Relatively certain objective knowledge was more in the realm of historical or scientific truth. But it's objective because it's a truth about the external world.</p>

<p><strong>Subjective knowledge</strong>, on the other hand, splinters into true subjective and pseudo-subjective knowledge. Pseudo subjective knowledge is a kind of acting knowledge that we don't enact in our daily lives, despite "knowing" that it is true. E.g., I can "know" that I should treat those around me with respect and graciousness but not act on that "knowledge." (And one gets the sense that Kierkegaard would say, "Well... do you <em>really</em> know that then?"). True subjective knowledge is just what it sounds like: it is when we "know" that something is true, and we act on that truth.</p>

<p>I've found myself thinking about this some again w/r/t the whole open web thing going on right now. I cam across a <a href="https://maggieappleton.com/">really beautiful website</a> yesterday: Maggie Applleton is a writer who focuses on anthropology and technology. She has an essay on the <a href="https://maggieappleton.com/garden-history">origins of digital gardening</a>, which is a topic I'm personally interested in, because it's an embodiment of what I <em>want</em> the web to be like for people. Open curiosity, the willingness to explore a subject one knows little about, building a digital space that sprawls.</p>

<p><a href="https://notes.andymatuschak.org/zUMFE66dxeweppDvgbNAb5hukXzXQu8ErVNv">Another note</a> I came across was from Andy Matuschak's site about content creators who make it their job to write about note-taking and productivity:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>But most people who write about note-taking don’t seem particularly accomplished in their own fields, whatever those may be. In fact, most such writers aren’t applying their notes to some exogenous creative problem: their primary creative work is writing about productivity. These writers offer advice on note-taking to help scientists and executives with the challenges of their work, but the advice was developed in a context disconnected from those external realities.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is something that has bothered me about this "sphere" of the internet as I've delved into it. Many indie-web people that I've come across so far aren't self-hosted and writing a blog about, say, running and fitness, or self-sufficiency, or coffee and travel. It's like many of them are stuck in this meta-writing thing where they're stuck writing about writing about the thing.</p>

<p>Kierkegaard tangentially talks about this issue regarding Christendom and the bishops in Denmark in the 19th century. Christianity for them wasn't about the life that ought to be lived. It was self-referential all the way down. The university scholars and influential and wealthy priests and bishops of the Lutheran Church were obsessed with status or producing "new" theological work. They were not interested in living the life the Christianity demanded from them. They pushed what should have been subjective knowledge into the objective sphere. And by doing so, they cheapened what <em>faith</em> was actually supposed to be; they stood on the outside of Christianity, looking in and examining it rather than taking the leap into it and <em>living</em> the faith they professed with such certainty. </p>

<p>Similarly, what I want from (what I hope is) this new moment in the web's development is average, everyday people learning the value of self-hosting and owning your own space. And then I want to see those people using their digital homes to build beautiful things and talk about what they're passionate about.</p>

<p>I'd perhaps encourage the technologically-minded folks (myself included) in this space to jump in and explore topics outside of technology in our digital homes. Are you a developer by day, but roast coffee at night? Write about that, because I want to read it? Are you researching the history of vaccines, or ultramarathons, or knitting? Post about it, make some digital gardens, let's see it!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Social Media and This Moment</title>
            <pubDate>Mon, 14 Nov 2022 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/social-media-and-this-moment.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/social-media-and-this-moment.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>It feels like we're having a moment. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Social networks’ evolution into social media brought both opportunity and calamity. Facebook and all the rest enjoyed a massive rise in engagement and the associated data-driven advertising profits that the attention-driven content economy created. The same phenomenon also created the influencer economy, in which individual social-media users became valuable as channels for distributing marketing messages or product sponsorships by means of their posts’ real or imagined reach. Ordinary folk could now make some money or even a lucrative living “creating content” online. The platforms sold them on that promise, creating official programs and mechanisms to facilitate it. In turn, “influencer” became an aspirational role, especially for young people for whom Instagram fame seemed more achievable than traditional celebrity—or perhaps employment of any kind.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>-- <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2022/11/twitter-facebook-social-media-decline/672074/">"The Age of Social Media is Ending"</a> - Ian Bogost</p>

<p>Journalists and news outlets are publishing articles like this more and more frequently, especially in the last ~two weeks since Elon bought Twitter. It's like an awakening is happening across culture, one that many people I've been listening to have been heralding for the last few years. I won't keep going on and on about the open/indie web. But eveyrone from Neil Postman to Alan Jacobs to Austin Kleon to Cal Newport have been dinging this bell for a while now (Postman saw it <em>decades</em> before anyone else did in <em>Entertaining Ourselves to Death</em>.)</p>

<p>But what's even more interesting to me is the cultural icons that are also dealing with this in music and comedy. Bo Burnham's <em>Inside</em> was never really about the pandemic, even if that helped frame it. It was about an individual person's interaction and obsession with the internet and social media. The feeling of constantly being watched, of having one's whole life online ready to be consumed and spit out by the masses.</p>

<p>Kendrick's <em>Mr. Morale and the Big Steppers</em> didn't get the critical acclaim that his work normally does, but the more I've listened to it, the more prescient it has become. "N95", a song about masks, written as a reference to covid-era protection, was never about either covid or the just-sub-surface level idea that "riches and materialism need to be removed to see the real you." No, deeper than that, it's about how we allow the outside world to determine how we present ourselves. Our (often imagined) worst critics determine the masks we put on, and those masks slowly fuse onto our faces until we can't tell the difference between our false selves and our true selves.</p>

<p>Social media may not have been the cause of all of this. We are humans and suffer from that condition, after all. But it has certainly exacerbated those tendencies. And due to its unique ability to force us to live in the algorithm-feed-moment, many of us have forgotten that the world outside is different than the one we interact with every day.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Lift Calculator in Javascript</title>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 00:00:00 CST</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/lift-calculator-in-javascript.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/lift-calculator-in-javascript.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I'd classify myself as mediocre as a Python developer. I'm more of a scripter, really. Automating tasks in Python has been pretty fun over the last year and half or so.</p>

<p>But as I've gotten more into web stuff, Javascript keeps staring me in the face, and I've avoided it up until now. If my Python is mediocre, my Javascript ability is best classified as <em>complete and utter novice</em>. That's fine... I'm not planning on being a full-blown Javascript developer, and upon reading and listening to a lot about internet bloat, I'll probably mostly stay away from it.</p>

<p>But! A few months ago, out of frustration from calculating the weights I needed on the bar for lifting, I built a weightlifting calculator in Python and hosted it on <a href="http://cdbaca.pythonanywhere.com/weightlifting/">PythonAnywhere</a> (I doubt if this link will stay live forever, but this is it for now.)</p>

<p>The problem is, as far as I'm aware, I can't do server-side scripting on the static site generator I've got going on here. The thought then became, can I move the calculator over to this site and use client-side scripting with Javascript? Turns out you can!</p>

<p>The Python code was simple:</p>

<p>`</p>

<pre><code>def calculator(request):

    user_input = request.POST['user_input']
    user_input = float(user_input)
    weight_no_bar = (user_input-45)/2

    poss_weights = (45, 35, 25, 10, 5, 2.5)
    weights_to_add = {}

    for weights in poss_weights:
        weights_to_add[weights] = 0

    def get_weights(weight_no_bar):
        for num in poss_weights:
            if weight_no_bar &lt; num:
                pass
            else:
                weight_no_bar = weight_no_bar - num
                weights_to_add[num] += 1
                break

        if weight_no_bar &gt; 0:
            get_weights(weight_no_bar)

    if weight_no_bar &gt; 0:
        get_weights(weight_no_bar)
        return render(request, 'result.html', {'results': weights_to_add})
    else:
        return render(request, 'result.html', {'result': f'Use {user_input/2} lb dumbbells!'})
</code></pre>

<p>`</p>

<p>It takes the post request from the form, does some math, and returns a dictionary object to the html page. Then the template form parses the dictionary renders the data.</p>

<p>I've transferred the logic to Javascript (probably poorly, as I barely understand the syntax... all these brackets, ugh!). Here's the same-ish logic in Javascript:</p>

<p>`</p>

<pre><code>function calculator() {
    document.getElementById("result").innerHTML = '';
    let user_input = document.getElementById("lift").value
    user_input = Number.parseFloat(user_input)
    let weight= (user_input - 45)/2
    const poss_weights = [45, 35, 25, 10, 5, 2.5]
    let weights_to_add = {"45":0, "35":0, "25":0, "10":0, "5":0, "2.5":0};

    function get_weights(weight) {
        for (let num of poss_weights) {
            if (weight &lt; num) {
            }
            else {
                weight = weight - num
                weights_to_add[num] += 1
                break
            }
        }
        if (weight &gt; 0) {
            get_weights(weight)
    }
    }
    if (weight &gt; 0) {
        get_weights(weight)
    }

    for (let key of poss_weights) {
        document.getElementById("result").innerHTML += `&lt;li&gt;&lt;h5&gt;${key}: ${weights_to_add[key]}&lt;/h5&gt;&lt;/li&gt;`;
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>`</p>

<p>What's cool about this is that when the JS function runs, it deletes whatever content is in the html "results" tag, then runs the logic as before, then lists the weights and amounts in order for what needs to be put on the bar.</p>

<p><a href="../docs/lift.html">Here's the link</a> to the lift calculator on the SSG.</p>

<p>Not the best thing ever, and it can probably be cleaned up design-wise, but this was one of my goals when redesigning this site. I'm happy with it!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>