<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 5</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-28 15:49:10</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-5.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-5.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h1>Chapter 5: VDOT System of Training</h1>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<p>VDOT is Daniels' shorthand for the VO2max value, specifically the maximal value of oxygen being consumed over 1 minute. This is a performance-based score, so it's slightly different than the real VO2max value. For Daniels, this score can be used in training to determine appropriate paces for training in his various training run types (E, M, T, I, R).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Using a person's race times gives a far better prediction of training intensities and other race performances that do tests in the lab. Race times reflect your max, your economy, your threshold, and your mental approach to racing, all in one measure -- the time it takes you to run a race." (76)</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>As a personal aside, my own current VDOT would seem to be around the level of 48 or so according to his charts. While I think it's fairly accurate, I think it works best for runners who are already in training. My score indicates that my threshold pace should be around 7:02, which is not currently a pace I can hold in training for 20 minutes (I can for about 15 or 16 minutes right now... I imagine I'll be able to hold it soon as my training volume and intensity increases).</em></p>

<p>The majority of this chapter was filled with charts for the ranges of VDOTs, plus some additional charts for comparing VDOTs across age ranges (i.e., a VDOT of 48 at age 55 is much more competitive than a VDOT at say, 18).</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 4</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-19 17:58:05</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-4.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-4.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h1>Chapter 4: Types of Training and Intensities</h1>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<p>Daniels has five buckets of workouts that he uses to training distance athletes:</p>

<ul>
<li>Easy (E)</li>
<li>Marathon (M)</li>
<li>Threshold (T)</li>
<li>Interval (I)</li>
<li>Repetition (R)</li>
</ul>

<p>These workout types increase in intensity (going down the list), and they all serve a different training purpose.</p>

<h3>Easy</h3>

<ul>
<li>E runs are paced at 59-74% of a runner's VO2 max value. Individual runs should be somewhere between 30-150 minutes, and those single runs should be no more than 25-30% of the total weekly mileage for runners who run 40 miles a week or less. 30 minutes should be the minimum of an easy run.</li>
<li>"E running does a good job of strengthening the heart muscle because the maximum force of each stroke of the heart is reached when the heart rate is at about 60 percent of maximum." (50)</li>
<li>"Another benefit of E running is an incrase in vascularization (opening of more tiny blood vessels that feed the exercising muscles)." (51)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Marathon</h3>

<ul>
<li>This is training at your predicted marathon pace, typicall at 75-84% of VO2 max (or 80-89% of max HR). Invidual runs should be limited to the lesser of 110 minutes or 18 miles, whichever comes first. (55 - see chart in book for various runs.</li>
<li>"The physiological benefits are really not different from those gained during E running." (56)</li>
<li>Primary use seems to be for runners actually training for a half or full marathon to bring confidence in the ability to run at this pace for long distances, and also to train for taking in calories/water during that time.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Threshold</h3>

<ul>
<li>T runs should be "comfortably hard." Performed at 80-85% of VO2 max (or 80-86% for lesser trained runners). Roughly equal to 88-92% of max HR. A single session should not total more than 10% of total weekly mileage.</li>
<li>"The purpose of T runs [is to] improve your endurance -- teaching your body how to deal with a slightly more demanding pace for a prolonged period of time, or increasing the duration of time you can hold at a specific pace." (56)</li>
<li>Daniels recommends two different kinds of T runs: 1) tempo runs (longer sustained efforts, around 15-20 minutes) and 2) cruise intervals (a series of runs at T pace with short rests, giving a longer total time at desired threshold intensity).</li>
<li>A tempo run can also be done during what's called a "progression run" -- i.e., a run started at an E pace and then a gradual increase to T for the final miles.</li>
<li>Recommended work/rest (W/R) ratio for T runs is 5:1, so if doing cruise intervals, you could do 5 minutes cruise, 1 minute rest (doesn't have to be full rest, can be 1 minute E jog).</li>
</ul>

<h3>Interval</h3>

<ul>
<li>Intervals should be "hard." Performed at 95-100% of VO2 max. A max single session should be consist of the lesser of 10K or 8% of total weekly miles (so a 30 mile a week runner should run no more than 2.4 miles of intervals in a single session). Daniels also denotes another kind of run called "H" runs (Hard) for determining Intervals by time rather than distance.</li>
<li>"The most logical purpose of I training is to maximize aerobic power (VO2 max)" (60)</li>
<li>"It is good to normally use 3- to 5-minute work bouts durin gan I workout because you are guaranteed some time at max even when it takes a minute or two to reach max." (62)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Repetition</h3>

<ul>
<li>Repetitions should be performed at 105-120% of VO2 max, and should be the lesser of 5 miles or 5% of total weekly miles in a single training session.</li>
<li>"The primary purpose of R (repetition) training is to improve anaerobic power, speed, and economy of running." (66).</li>
<li>Due to the purpose of these runs, the W/R ratio should be 1:2-3, and the max time per repetition should be around 2 minutes.</li>
<li>"Most true R sessions will be made up of repeated 200s, 300s, 400s, 500s, and 600s for most runners." (67)</li>
<li>"It is always best to think in terms of time spentn running at various intensities, rather than distances covered, or else the slower runners on a team end up spending considerably more time doing the workouts than do the faster runners." (67)</li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 3</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-17 12:44:21</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-3.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-3.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h1>Chapter 3: Physiological and Personal Training Profiles</h1>

<h2>Notes</h2>

<p>The big takeaway from this chapter seems to be that there are a variety of baseline metrics that can be used to measure performance potential:</p>

<ul>
<li>VO2 Max (maximum oxygen consumption rate) </li>
<li>vVO2 Max (speed at which the athlete runs when at VO2 Max)</li>
<li>Running economy (the curve on which we determine a runner's oxygen consumption at various intensity levels)</li>
<li>BLa (Blood lactate levels at various intensity levels)</li>
<li>Heart rate (max HR, resting HR, blood hemoglobin levels)</li>
</ul>

<h2>Quotes</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>"It is without question that vVO2 max is a better way to compare potential running performance than is either economoy or VO2 independently." (38)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"The important thing for any runner is to improve as many variables as possible in order to perform better... it is necessary to include training that will ipmrove aerobic power (VO2 max) and running economy, and as either, or both, of these variables ipmroves, there will be an improvement in the important vVO2 max variable." (42)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"If the purpose of a specific workout is to spend time at a specific <em>speed</em> of running, then it might be necessary to not let heart rate be the guide. but if <em>intensity</em> of effort is the most important thing being sought, then heart rate can be very useful."</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Algorithms Aren't Smart</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-17 11:22:19</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/algorithms-aren-t-smart.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/algorithms-aren-t-smart.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>When I was in college (and for some time after when I had my first office job), I helped tutor a class called developmental math for several years. Tom Ferguson was the professor of that class when I first started, and the guy was incredibly smart -- sometimes to the detriment of those poor students trying to get by in the bare bones of college-level mathematics.</p>

<p>Once, when explaining to students about how to reason about some math problem and when calculators were useful and when they weren't, he said simply, "Calculators are stupid. They don't know anything."</p>

<p>This was long before my journey into trying to understand the very basics of programming and computer science, so I didn't really know what he meant at the time. Of course, I do now. Calculators, computers -- anything digital really -- are stupid. They don't / can't know anything, and if you give them even the <em>slightest</em> wrong instruction, they will follow it with no regard for what you meant. (LLMs notwithstanding, though I think the argument can be made they're just stupid in a different way?)</p>

<p>This memory came back to me when reading this blog post (<a href="https://tadaima.bearblog.dev/if-nothing-is-curated-how-do-we-find-things/">"If nothing is curated, how do we find things?"</a>). Quote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"And algorithms can only predict content that you've seen before. It'll never surprise you with something different. It keeps you in a little bubble. Oh, you like shoegaze? Well, that's all the algorithm is going to give you until you intentionally start listening to something else."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is my experience exactly. The algorithms are stupid too. They only repeat, relentlessly. There's no magic in it, no surprise. Most often, it feels the the new, best experiences I've had with media or food or other kinds of consumption happened because I stumbled upon it by accident, through a friend recommendation (and no, not through a "social network"), or through making a connection to a work that I liked (à la Austin Kleon's note about "reading what your favorite authors read").</p>

<p>Algorithms aren't smart, but people sometimes are.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 2</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-16 10:38:48</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-2.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-2.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h1>Chapter 2: Training Principles and Tips</h1>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<p>While the previous chapter was general "laws" of running and training, Daniels gets a little closer to defining the rules of training, and a little more specific about the "whys" in this chapter.</p>

<p>Before giving specific tips/principles, he notes that extreme approaches to training should generally be avoided. Better to have a general training approach that's flexible for most/all runners than it is to train for the extremely talented, which may only lead to one or two runners performing well, leaving the rest behind.</p>

<h3>Principles of Training</h3>

<ul>
<li>The body reacts to stress</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Every time you impose a specific stress, there will be immediate reactions in different parts of your body.... over time there is a different reaciong to a particular repeated stress, and that is the body strengthening itself." (17)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Specificity</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"The tissues being stressed are the ones that react to that stress" (18) (i.e., train for what you're racing)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Overstress</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"If you overstress some body parts, they may not get tougher; in fact, they may get weaker or break down completely." (18)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Whenever you are not sure which of two training sessions to take on at any particular time, select the less stressful of the two." (18)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You should always be able to answer the question, "What is the purpose of this workout?" &lt;-- this is a common, repeated maxim by Daniels.</p>

<ul>
<li>Training response</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>The body responds to "new stress." Usually with a fitness increase. Fitness then plateaus, which requires new, increased stress. There are several ways to increase stress:</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
  <li>Increase workload (run farther)</li>
  <li>Increase intensity (run faster)</li>
  <li>Decrease recovery (rest less between "intervals")</li>
  <li>Increase frequency (run more)</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"It is not a good idea to change more than one of the training variables." (22)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Personal limits</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everyone has limits, whether that's personal maximum limits or seasonal limits due to other responsibilities / commitments.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Diminishing returns</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Basically, it's harder to increase fitness the more fitness increases. (A 30 second mile-time decrease is much easier from 8:00 to 7:30 than it is from 5:30 to 5:00)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Accelerating setbacks</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is essentially an "ideal window" for overall training intensity. As training intensity increases, the possibility and chance of setback increases drastically.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Maintenance</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"It is easier to maintain a level of fitness than it was to achieve that fitness" (26)</p>
</blockquote>

<h3>Other specific principles</h3>

<ul>
<li>Stride rate</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>In general, 180 steps / minute is the average ideal for runners, especially for racing. Running at 180 steps / minutes should also help normalize a runner's form without doing much else (e.g., they will find their natural most comfortable foot strike &amp; breath rate when trying to run at 180).</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Foot strike</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Basically, it varies by athlete.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Breathing while running</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>2-2 (breathe in for 2 steps, then out for 2 steps) is most common and probably most efficient for receiving oxygen at higher intensity levels. You can use this as a baseline to determine how hard an athlete is working</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>