<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>John Scalzi on the Artisan Web</title>
            <pubDate>11/29/2022 15:42:52</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/john-scalzi-on-the-artisan-web.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/john-scalzi-on-the-artisan-web.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Now, why should we bring back that artisan, hand-crafted Web? Oh, I don’t know. Wouldn’t it be nice to have a site that’s not run by an amoral billionaire chaos engine, or algorithmically designed to keep you doomscrolling in a state of fear and anger, or is essentially spyware for governments and/or corporations? Wouldn’t it be nice not to have ads shoved in your face every time you open an app to see what your friends are up to? Wouldn’t it be nice to know that when your friends post something, you’ll actually see it without a social media platform deciding whether to shove it down your feed and pump that feed full of stuff you didn’t ask for?</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://whatever.scalzi.com/2022/11/25/how-to-weave-the-artisan-web/">John Scalzi: "How to Weave the Artisan Web"</a></p>

<p>I know I keep tooting this horn but... dang it, it's true!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Mastodon No More</title>
            <pubDate>11/29/2022 09:23:42</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mastodon-no-more.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mastodon-no-more.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I decided yesterday that Mastodon wasn't a good fit for me and deleted my account at IndieWeb.Social. The premise, I think, was promising. Federated groupings, servers run by real people and not a single corporation, better rules of engagement, etc. But it didn't take long before I was seeing the same sorts of undesirable behavior on my instance that I was seeing on Twitter that made me get off in the first place.</p>

<p>Perhaps it will be a balm for those whose online lives revolve around Twitter. It's just not what I want the internet to be. More and more, I want the internet to be a little more homebrewed, a little less corporate. At least, that's the internet <em>I</em> want to interact with. </p>

<p>I'm still interested in giving micro.blog a go, but there are some technical challenges with building a feed on this website since it's static, and then hooking it up with ActivityPub. I need to do some more reading and digging at the micro.blog forums to see what that will entail. And then the question really is, why do I want the micro-format in the first place? Onen of the other things that bugged me about Twitter a long time ago was that I felt myself "thinking in Tweets" rather than thinking in broader strokes and trying to piece things together. The micro format <em>itself</em> encourages short-form thinking, which is not what I want to find myself doing regularly.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>God is (in) the Details</title>
            <pubDate>11/28/2022 16:19:21</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/god-is-in-the-details.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/god-is-in-the-details.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I don't have much to say, except that I listened to two podcasts this week:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.premierguitar.com/podcast/wong-notes/chris-thile-cory-wong-interview">Wong Notes - "Chris Thile's Exercise in Joy"</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.singforscience.org/episodes/rivers-cuomo-guido-van-rossum">Sing for Science - "Rivers Cuomo and Guido van Rossum"</a></li>
</ol>

<p>In both episodes, the interviewees said the phrase "God is in the details" -- in the former, Thile then corrects himself, and says "God <em>is</em> the details."</p>

<p>I find myself thinking and not thinking about God and religion much these days. "God" permeates my work and the culture that surrounds me, and yet, since leaving LIDE, I find myself wanting very little to do with <em>formal</em> and <em>institutional</em> versions of spirituality. (I recognize this is awfully millennial of me)</p>

<p>On the other hand, I cannot deny the draw of spirituality on some deep level within me. There has always, always been a sense of beauty, of love, of transcendence in life. The very existence of these feelings seem to me to be pointers to a deeper reality that I cannot quite grasp. A reality that fades from my vision when I try to look to closely, like a dream that I try to remember just after waking.</p>

<p>Mostly, it's in the details that I have these feelings. The feel of Elaine's hand on my back, the feel of my daughters' hair when I kiss them goodnight on the top of the head, the cold wind in the morning when I'm out walking, the gratitude I feel when surrounded by close friends and family.</p>

<p>Perhaps God is in the details after all, and that is all that we can say about it.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Changing up the Coffee Routine</title>
            <pubDate>11/22/2022 09:52:53</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/changing-up-the-coffee-routine.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/changing-up-the-coffee-routine.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Probably for the better part of 2+ years, my coffee routine hasn't shifted much. I roast coffee roughly once every six weeks or so, usually about 5 lbs at a time. Once the coffee has had a few days to rest post-roast, I put a little in a jar for the next week's consumption. The rest get sealed with the FoodSaver and frozen.</p>

<p>Nearly every day, I have two cups of coffee -- one in the morning and one around 2pm or so. A while back, James Hoffmann posted <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j6VlT_jUVPc">his preferred Aeropress recipe</a>. I use this every time I make an Aeropress now with slight variation:</p>

<h3>Current Aeropress Recipe</h3>

<ol>
<li>Standard orientation (non-inverted)</li>
<li>13 g coffee, ground relatively fine</li>
<li>Coffee in, then add 200 g water at roughly 205 degrees F</li>
<li>Let steep for 2 minutes, then swirl</li>
<li>At four minutes, plunge</li>
</ol>

<p>That's it. I love the simplicity of it, and honestly it makes a pretty incredible cup.</p>

<p>Sometimes in the afternoon I'll do the same, but I also have a Rancilio Silvia (V3), and if I'm feeling frisky for a few weeks, I will hit the espresso in the afternoon. I also got <em>really</em> into making cortados at work in the afternoon at the beginning of this year. I had a goal of getting better at latte (well... cortado) art, so I was drinking a <em>ton</em> of espresso in January and February. That was fun, but got to be a little too much dairy. I did succeed though! I make a pretty mean cortado if I do so say myself. My latte art went from being awful to mediocre+. That is, I can make a heart if I try hard enough and the stars align.</p>

<p>Years ago, I was Chemex-obsessed. In the same way I've used the Aeropress nearly every day for two years, I did the same with the Chemex. Alas, it broke while cleaning it at some point, and I never bothered to buy a new one. Until recently, that is! I needed to buy another one for Thanksgiving because we're having family over this year.</p>

<p>The new Chemex arrived two days ago, and I made my first Chemex in a couple of years. You know how there is just something about a smell or flavor that really takes you back to a point in your life? I know it's cliché, but that really does happen with the Chemex. It smells slightly different, brings out different aromatics, has a brighter flavor than the Aeropress or French Press. That said, I'm guessing I'll stick with the Chemex for a good long while and enjoy the nostalgia it brings with it.</p>

<h3>Current Chemex Recipe</h3>

<ol>
<li>35 g coffee, ground medium-fine</li>
<li>Use total 595 g water</li>
<li>Start with 70 g water to bloom, wait 45 seconds</li>
<li>Pour remainder of water in spurts of about 100 g or so</li>
<li>Final goal is for the coffee to finish brewing within 4-5 minutes of starting the bloom</li>
</ol>

<p>I used to take measurements and grinding and stuff so seriously and tried not to deviate. Coffee, however, is alive. It changes as the days get further out from the roast date. This usually requires a change in the brewing or grinding method. And because people usually have different coffee flavor preferences, I find that it's fine to change up water/coffee ratios, grind size, or whatever until you find what suits you. The only general rules I follow are: get roasted coffee as fresh as you can, and try to find a relatively inexpensive burr grinder. The rest will work itself out. Oh, and immersion brewing (Aeropress and French Press) covers a multitude of sins.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>TIL: 11-18-22</title>
            <pubDate>11/18/2022 16:03:38</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/til-11-18-22.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/til-11-18-22.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I came across an issue today with the generator I've written. If I write multiple posts in a day, the RSS feed may not pick up the newest post, because all the original post dates were set to today's date, but a time of 00:00:00 CST. So if it doesn't sort it properly, a feed reader may not pick up the newest post of the day because it could get pushed to the bottom of the list of today's posts instead of the top.</p>

<p>To fix that, I introduced datetimes to my "create a post" script, and then had to manipulate that datetime string to do what I needed in the creation of the data structures for the site. E.g., I wanted only the date (not the time) to show up on the index page, but I want them in order of writing in reverse. I also wanted the feed to be in reverse order of writing so that even if I post multiple times a day, feed readers will pick up the newest post.</p>

<p>The problem is, I have multiple functions doing the work of creating posts, manipulating data, creating the index page vs. the RSS feed vs. actual posts. But there is a single reference list of dictionaries I'm passing into these functions. In the script, my "make<em>index" function happens upstream of the "make</em>rss" function. And even though the index function was getting the right order, somehow, after I was passing in and manipulating the data in the function, the <em>original list</em> was getting manipulated even though I assigned it to a new variable.</p>

<p>Apparently, this is a feature/bug in Python (I'm sure someone <em>likes</em> that this happens in Python... I didn't experience that particular joy today). For example, if I have a list of lists called "posts" and then say posts<em>copy = posts, if I manipulate values within the posts</em>copy list, any values I change there <em>will also change</em> the values in the reference list. That's bonkers, but whatever. After a couple of hours of cursing the void, I found my answer <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/68712435/changes-made-in-python-list-showing-up-in-copy-of-original-list">here</a>. Not only do you need to assign the values to a new variable, you have to make a "deepcopy" of the original list and assign it (if the list in question has other data structures inside it). So instead of</p>

<p>`</p>

<pre><code>posts_copy = copy
</code></pre>

<p>`</p>

<p>I needed to do:</p>

<p>`</p>

<pre><code>from copy import deepcopy

posts_copy = deepcopy(posts)
</code></pre>

<p>`</p>

<p>From there, I was able to manipulate values in the function without worrying about overwriting data in the original list.</p>

<p>I like programming, but that was maddening.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>