<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 3 - 28 Sept to 4 Oct 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-10-04 13:59:46</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-3-28-sept-to-4-oct-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-3-28-sept-to-4-oct-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>This is the second to last week of cross country. While I love cross country so much, I'm also ready to be done with early wake up calls and long Saturdays. Now onto the end of my race training!</p>

<p>In trying to decide on a woodworking bench design, I remembered that I had already bought the material a while back for <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lPiMjv7lkqI">Rex Krueger's low Roman-style bench</a>. While it's basic and will not meet all the needs I'll have for woodworking, it's:</p>

<p>a) a start, which is what I really need and,
b) "free" since the materials have already been bought</p>

<p>I'm trying to do this in spare little free moments I have -- 20 minutes here, 30 minutes there. I figure it's the only real way I'll be able to actually pursue a hobby that's a craft and not just wasting my time. Once the bench is built I'm hoping to learn to cut some more precise joints, and maybe make a few of the projects from <a href="https://www.freeonlinewoodworkingschool.com/">Matt Estlea's free woodworking school</a>.</p>

<p>I took Wednesday off and we all went to the Texas State Fair. Besides the heat, it turns out Wednesdays are a great time to go. The crowds were very low, and we had such a great time. We all ate some good fair food (the strawberry pop-tart beignetffle was a winner). Paisley won a fair game and got a giant stuffed boba tea. We saw a horse show, a magic show (meh), and did the petting zoo. The fair isn't really my jam, but the low crowds meant I didn't find it too overwhelming.</p>

<p>Elaine entered a photo competition a few weeks ago and was selected as a top-ten finalist, so we went to the event for that last night. Not a winner, but it was still exciting to be in the top ten. We ate dinner with Shelby at Red Robin after, and it was great to catch up after a long time and after all the sickness over the last couple months that we've been dealing with.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Finish up refinancing on the house. We should be able to save almost $300 on P&amp;I on our home, going from 7.625% to 6.125%. (Unfortunately, our taxes were also GROSSLY miscalculated, so my guess is our monthly payment will roughly stay the same AND we'll have a pretty big tax bill that we'll need to catch up on. Bummer.)</li>
<li>Find a decent budget software and actual start working on it / sticking to it with Elaine.</li>
<li>Clean out the shower (it's due for it's monthly grout cleaning)</li>
- 
</ul>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I found a YouTube Channel that has some episodes of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mnUH-yJPVuw">Britain's Best Woodworker, season 2</a>, which is fun. Sort of like that British baking show, but for woodworking.</p>

<p>When I was watching some guitar maintenance and building videos last week, I came across an old school HTML-style site that seems to have some really great info on guitar care and maintenance (diy): http://www.frets.com/FretsPages/OwnerManual/manssguitar.html</p>

<p>There are a bazillion different lists of "tools you need to buy" when starting woodworking. It's pretty dizzying, but this site really did narrow it down to a somewhat manageable list: https://woodandshop.com/learn-traditional-woodworking-with-hand-tools/getting-started-traditional-handtool-woodworking-step-1/ &lt;-- I've written the list down elsewhere but I do think that this is a helpful place to start.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 2 - 21 to 27 Sept 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-09-27 08:28:44</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-2-21-to-27-sept-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-2-21-to-27-sept-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>The week started "somewhat" normally. While our whole junior high team was out for last week's cross country race, our high school team raced pretty well (it was the "SCS II" Invitational). Lyla was still recovering, and many of the other junior highers were sick, so definitely a weird one.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the sickness saga in our own family hasn't quite completely finished. Last night, L came home from school and was running a fever again, and it seems to have held on through the night so she has a doctor's appointment today to rule out pneumonia or some other secondary infection post-flu.</p>

<p>We had a really, really tough day with P on Monday. Probably a total of 3-4 emotional explosions from her that neither Elaine or I dealt with particularly well. Some days we feel really stuck with her and like we haven't made any improvements at all. And then we feel a little crazy because things get better. Homework and responsibilities are clear triggers for her, so we are trying to continue to work through the <a href="https://livesinthebalance.org/">"Explosive Child" methodology</a>. It seems that when we stick with it, we see more and more success. When we sort of "fall off" that wagon is when we see regression.</p>

<p>I was able to start running this week again after being sick last week. Although, I think I overdid it a little bit by jumping back into lifting on Monday along with adding mileage starting Sunday. My legs were <em>thrashed</em> for a few days, though I was able to push through and got some 1200m intervals in Thursday.</p>

<p>Still reading: <em>Lore of Running</em> (this one is going to take forever, it's like 900+ pages). I finished <em>Piranesi</em> which was a great, fun, relatively quick read. I also started <em>Moonbound</em> by Robin Sloan this week.</p>

<p>We got a lot of rain at the beginning of the week, which has helped to bring somewhat "fall"-ish weather. That's been such a good respite from mid-to-upper 90s.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<ul>
<li>Plant in the fall garden (I added some more homemade Mel's Mix to the raised bed on Thursday)</li>
<li>Mortgage refi (unsure if I should continue to wait to see if rates drop more or not)</li>
<li>Deep clean the Honda</li>
<li>Buy a new dining table / chairs</li>
</ul>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I have the unfortunate personality trait of being interested in, well, <em>everything</em>. Things catch my attention really easy, and it's one of the great regrets of my life that I will not be able to pursue all my interests. One week I want to be a woodworker, the next I want to study health and exercise, the next I want to continue down the path of programming. </p>

<p>It also means that I struggle with <em>choosing</em> what interests to pursue in the first place. This is a classic Kierkegaardian problem -- not choosing <em>is</em> choosing, of course.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, I found myself watching videos on building things this week. Mainly guitars and tiny homes.</p>

<h3>Daisy Tempest's guitar build series:</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=A44AQGv2wY0">Part 1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MQxm8zNFp2I">Part 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QIOvkEPcaVo">Part 3, as yet unwatched</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0lTuBRp_tHE">Full tiny home build</a></p>

<p>I am seriously considering pre-ordering a <a href="https://www.thelightphone.com/blog/introducing-the-light-phone-iii">Light Phone III</a>. It looks great, and seems like it would be a great tool for going further down the digital simplicity rabbit hole.</p>

<p>Alan Jacobs: <a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/pos-not-posse/">"POS, not POSSE"</a>, with a historic quote Louis C.K. quote from <a href="https://tumblr.austinkleon.com/post/144251991476">Austin Kleon's old Tumblr</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You have your number. It’s very dangerous to be liked by more people than should like you. It’s bad for them, and it’s bad for you. There’s gonna be a shock down the road for them, or you’re gonna dilute yourself and take yourself to a place where you can’t live with who you are. I think that you make an honest account of who you are and you live with the results. The results will be appropriate to who you are.</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 1 - 14 to 20 Sept 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-09-20 11:08:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-1-14-to-20-sept-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-1-14-to-20-sept-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I've been doing some more thinking on habits, technology use, and my own priorities. Of course, I've always been the kind of person whose interests vary day to day or week to week. I get excited about new ideas, rediscover old ones, go down rabbit trails -- all things that (I think) are somehow hallmarks to my own personality.</p>

<p>What I find is that I still lack a coherent way of <em>remembering</em> things. I'll take up the journal every once in a while when the mood strikes me, or write a blog post, or snap and post a picture to Flickr. But I don't have a consistent practice that would allow me to look back and find patterns of thought or sentiment. I'd like that, but I think the barrier of entry needs to be pretty low for it to be a normal occurrence. As much as I'd LOVE to be a daily blogger, that's just not going to happen right now.</p>

<p>A weekly update/note though -- that seems relatively doable? Manuel's <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/pb-giles-turnbull">guest on P&amp;B</a> this week was <a href="https://gilest.org/">Giles Turnbull</a>. In doing a little rabbit-trailing (what the internet was made for imho), I found this article on Giles's website: <a href="https://doingweeknotes.com/">Doing Weeknotes</a>. A bit of a long article, but overall I thought it was actually a really good idea -- both for teams/organizations and even for individuals doing what I talked about above -- remembering.</p>

<p>So I thought, what the hell? Maybe I should give this a go. Once a week for a little bit doesn't seem to be a huge ask of myself (I also sent to Landon, my team lead at Green Line to see if it was a good enough idea to implement at work). It could not only help me just on a personal level but also maybe help me make connections at work or at home that I otherwise wouldn't make. </p>

<p>The question is, should there be a format to my own weeknotes? In looking at others, there seems to be a variety. Some are sort of "freehand." Others have a weekday cadence (e.g., headers for each day and what happened in each one); still others answer a standard set of questions ("What brought me joy?", "Where am I stuck?", etc.).</p>

<p>To make it simple on myself, I think it'd be helpful to have more structure for now. As time moves on, of course, perhaps that will open up the possibility of deviation from the structure. But for now, I think three questions/headers will do:</p>

<ol>
<li>What have I been doing?</li>
<li>What do I need to take care of?</li>
<li>What caught my interest?</li>
</ol>

<p>So... well, let's get to it I suppose. One final note -- I'm going to not try to think about this too hard. Just answer the questions. If I miss something, forget about something, etc... I can always come back later and add a new post or add it into next week's note. Or it will just fall out of memory and won't matter anyway -- haha!</p>

<h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>Last Saturday the cross country team had a meet in Ennis. It was hot and flat. Mixed performance on the team due to both the weather and also a mistake by the race officials during the HS girls varsity race. </p>

<p>Elaine had been down with the flu since two days prior, and I began to cough on Saturday. By Sunday morning, I had a fever and was in for a rough ride. By that evening, both L and P also began to run fever. Thus began about 4-5 days of illness for the rest of the family, and some bad days and nights. Monday and Tuesday were basically blurs. My fever and aches were so bad that I couldn't do much except lay in bed and stare at the wall. By Wendesday I could be up and about somewhat, but there was lot of television watching happening by that point as well (started <em>The Sopranos</em>, finished season 1 by Thursday). </p>

<p>I started <em>Piranesi</em> by Susanna Clarke, and am about 80% of the way through as of today. I am enjoying it.</p>

<p>Yesterday after work I needed a break from home (A tough day with P as she was still probably feeling unwell but needing to catch up on homework. She was overwhelmed and that often leads to emotional explosions.). I ate some Mod, then went to the library for a bit. I browsed and picked up a few CDs to add to the collection at home, and also the old <em>Anne of Green Gables</em> mini series on DVD.</p>

<p>This week at work consisted mostly of catching up on tickets that got left while I was sick. Not too big of a deal, mostly GTM work, and some cleanup/troubleshooting of data. Also got some good news that my salary increase was approved! While this was supposed to go through in June, it wasn't possible for a few months due to a hiring and raise freeze. That seems to have been lifted, and my next paycheck will reflect that. So very good news for us.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Goodness gracious it seems like there are a lot of things on my mind in terms of what I'd like to get done. Trying to not overwhelm myself here, but, here's just a list of things I think need to get done:</p>

<ul>
<li>Clean up the backyard</li>
<li>Start the fall garden/planting</li>
<li>Start the process for the mortgage refi</li>
<li>Replace the cabin air filter in the Prius</li>
<li>Check the tires on the Prius at Discount Tire</li>
<li>Deep clean both cars</li>
<li>Purge old clothes of mine</li>
</ul>

<p>There are also so many longer term projects at the house that I know we want to do. Things like adding lighting/electrical to the gazebo, buying a new dining table and chairs, buying other decorative furniture (like a sidetable for the entryway), decorating the walls so they aren't so bare. As I come back to this list, maybe it will help me to talk with Elaine about actual plans for this so it's not just something that swirls around my head and causes anxiety about the fact that there are so many things I'm/we're <em>not doing</em>.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I think this was actually last week, but just posting it here because it's awesome: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zISYJ-bT7DQ">"Watch the Party Die" by Kendrick</a>.</p>

<p>I've been thinking a lot about how I can be more knowledgeable and researched in the area of both running science and first aid + injury prevention (specific to running). Books that I have or want to read on this subject:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Anatomy for Runners</em> by Jay Dicharry</li>
<li><em>Lore of Running</em> by Timothy Noakes</li>
<li><em>Training Essentials for Ultrarunning</em> by Jason Koop</li>
</ul>

<p>Also thinking more about <strong>digital minimalism</strong> and being more intentional about digital ownership. Two links that caught my eye this week on this subject:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://knhash.in/gentle-guide-to-self-hosting/">A Gentle Guide to Self-Hosting Your Software</a> - I already do some of this with the blog, but it could be interesting to go further in depth here on "self"-hosting (a fraught term according to HackerNews comments, lol) other kinds of software.</li>
<li><a href="https://chollinger.com/blog/2024/08/why-i-still-self-host-my-servers-and-what-ive-recently-learned/">Why I still self host my servers (and what I've recently learned)</a> - Haven't read this one as of this writing, but this is definitely the more hacker-esque, nitty-gritty kind of self-hosting. Not sure I want to get this far into it but I always find reading about this fascinating.</li>
</ul>

<p>This has been going for a little while, but I have a somewhat latent interest in sketching (well..... learning to sketch). A while back I borrowed, and then eventually bought, <em>The New Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain</em> by Betty Edwards. Shaky neuroscience aside, so many sources seem to point to this book as a great starting point for <strong>learning how to see</strong> (which is the primary ability gained from sketching, I hear). Other sources I see mentioned a lot are <a href="https://drawabox.com/">Draw a Box</a> and these old <a href="http://www.alexhays.com/loomis/">Andrew Loomis books</a>.</p>

<p>...</p>

<p>Whew! That was a lot more than I thought it would be. I probably should have a set a timer so I didn't spend too much time here.</p>

<p>Oh well, here's to next week!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Moving Backwards</title>
            <pubDate>2024-08-29 11:13:26</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/moving-backwards.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/moving-backwards.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I did two things this week that might seem counterintuitive:</p>

<p>1) I moved all the music (that I really wanted to keep, anyway) from an old hard drive to my Macbook and my iPhone.
2) I have reverted to using corded headphones.</p>

<p>On 1 -- I kind of did this on a whim. Elaine needed a hard drive, and I rememberd that we had a 1TB lying around that had a backup of my old Macbook on it. When I was looking in there to clean things up for her, I saw all my old music and thought it would be fun to have access to on a regular basis. Over the last few years, I've been collecting CDs every once in a while. Usually when we go to Half Price Books, I spend the first 10 - 15 minutes of the visit perusing the CD area just to see if there's anything I want to add to the collection.</p>

<p>Anyway, I pulled all that music over to the Macbook, added album art to make things a little more colorful and fun, and then transferred everything over to my phone. I still have access to Spotify and won't likely get rid of it. But you know, there's just <em>something</em> about listening to music that you know is yours. Of course this also leads to listening to full albums a little more often as well (I was already trying to do that, but Spotify makes it so easy to get lost in algo-shuffle). Who knows? Maybe one day I'll ditch Spotify and go back to just my owned collection. There's something good in that, I just don't quite know what it is yet.</p>

<p>On 2 -- this is a little more of just a pragmatic move. My AirPods Pro are starting to give up the ghost a little bit. They still work, and the battery's ok. But if you have them in and you move around at all, both headphones are starting to crackle. What's frustrating about that is that this is an indicator that this tech is essentially "disposable." I have corded headphones that have worked for YEARS. Are they somewhat less convenient because I'm physically tied to my device? Sure. But they also never fail to connect to my phone or laptop. And the sound is as good as (or better than) my wireless headphones. We're literally talking about the free headphones that used to come with phones.</p>

<p>Two ways I moved "backwards" this week. But I think there is just a little more joy there than infinite choice and the lack of a tether. Maybe what's shiny isn't always what's best.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>What I'm Up To - August 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-08-24 14:43:38</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/what-i-m-up-to-august-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/what-i-m-up-to-august-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well, August is about two-thirds over, and it's definitely been a bit of a whirlwind. After a long, somewhat leisurely (and not <em>too</em> hot) summer, August came out swinging.</p>

<p>No worries though. I was feeling a little anxious about it in the weeks leading up to August 1, knowing what was coming. As we've gotten into the groove of things, however, it doesn't feel as unsettled as it did at the end of July / beginning of August.</p>

<p>The first week of August brought the beginning of the cross country season, and I'm coaching both the middle and high school teams (four high schoolers, six junior highers). We practice on Mondays, Wednesdays, and some Fridays, and we just had our first meet last week. It was incredibly hot, but the team did well all things considered (two HS girls placed top ten in their races). As always, I love coaching even if it means giving up a little time in the evenings to get to sleep early. Practice starts at 6:30, so Lyla and I wake up around 5:50 AM on those days.</p>

<p>In a similar mode, I also started seriously training for the <a href="https://www.theactivejoe.com/dinosaurvalley">Dinosaur Valley Endurance Run (25K)</a>. Goal time here is just around 2hrs or so, which would be an 8 minute mile. Of course this isn't road running so we'll see how things go. But training is going well. This past week was the fourth week of official training, and I'm feeling pretty strong.</p>

<p>The girls started school about two weeks ago as well, and I'm happy and proud to say the both got back into the swing of things pretty quickly. We had a little bit of anxiety going into the year after some school difficulty last year, but Pais has really grabbed the reins and seems happy to be back. We also really seem to be rounding a corner with her -- she's much quicker to calm back down after heated moments, and we've really worked hard to move into problem solving mode when things are overwhelming or stressful.</p>

<p>A few weeks ago I built a new raised bed for the garden, and it was finally "cool" enough (read, not hellish) today to bring the bed to the back, pull out some of the older spring beds, and fill the container with new soil. The soil looks great, and I'm excited to get the fall garden going. Right now we're planning for carrots, broccoli, garlic, and maybe sweet potatoes? We'll see.</p>

<p>Finally, we've made a switch for our church home. After about two years of just recovering at St. Paul Episcopal in Waxahachie after the stint at LIDE, we felt it was time to find a place where we could feel more at home, and perhaps get more involved. After some debate as a family, we decided to try <a href="https://asd.church/">All Saints Dallas</a>, an Anglican church out of the AMIA. They seem to have an equivalent focus on liturgy, scripture, and matters of the Spirit, which is a refreshing thing to hear, and seems to sort of "check all the boxes" for the different desires in our family. I think we're ready to try this place out long term, and it's exciting (and a little anxiety-inducing, if I'm honest) to try to wade back out into these waters.</p>

<p>Life feels a little tiring, a little challenging, but I think for the first time in a long time, I feel truly good about the direction we're going as a family. We're finding rest where we can, and pushing towards growth and new goals.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>