<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 2</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-16 10:38:48</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-2.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-2.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h1>Chapter 2: Training Principles and Tips</h1>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<p>While the previous chapter was general "laws" of running and training, Daniels gets a little closer to defining the rules of training, and a little more specific about the "whys" in this chapter.</p>

<p>Before giving specific tips/principles, he notes that extreme approaches to training should generally be avoided. Better to have a general training approach that's flexible for most/all runners than it is to train for the extremely talented, which may only lead to one or two runners performing well, leaving the rest behind.</p>

<h3>Principles of Training</h3>

<ul>
<li>The body reacts to stress</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Every time you impose a specific stress, there will be immediate reactions in different parts of your body.... over time there is a different reaciong to a particular repeated stress, and that is the body strengthening itself." (17)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Specificity</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"The tissues being stressed are the ones that react to that stress" (18) (i.e., train for what you're racing)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Overstress</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"If you overstress some body parts, they may not get tougher; in fact, they may get weaker or break down completely." (18)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Whenever you are not sure which of two training sessions to take on at any particular time, select the less stressful of the two." (18)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>You should always be able to answer the question, "What is the purpose of this workout?" &lt;-- this is a common, repeated maxim by Daniels.</p>

<ul>
<li>Training response</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>The body responds to "new stress." Usually with a fitness increase. Fitness then plateaus, which requires new, increased stress. There are several ways to increase stress:</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
  <li>Increase workload (run farther)</li>
  <li>Increase intensity (run faster)</li>
  <li>Decrease recovery (rest less between "intervals")</li>
  <li>Increase frequency (run more)</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>"It is not a good idea to change more than one of the training variables." (22)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Personal limits</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everyone has limits, whether that's personal maximum limits or seasonal limits due to other responsibilities / commitments.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Diminishing returns</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Basically, it's harder to increase fitness the more fitness increases. (A 30 second mile-time decrease is much easier from 8:00 to 7:30 than it is from 5:30 to 5:00)</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Accelerating setbacks</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is essentially an "ideal window" for overall training intensity. As training intensity increases, the possibility and chance of setback increases drastically.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Maintenance</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"It is easier to maintain a level of fitness than it was to achieve that fitness" (26)</p>
</blockquote>

<h3>Other specific principles</h3>

<ul>
<li>Stride rate</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>In general, 180 steps / minute is the average ideal for runners, especially for racing. Running at 180 steps / minutes should also help normalize a runner's form without doing much else (e.g., they will find their natural most comfortable foot strike &amp; breath rate when trying to run at 180).</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Foot strike</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>Basically, it varies by athlete.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
<li>Breathing while running</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>2-2 (breathe in for 2 steps, then out for 2 steps) is most common and probably most efficient for receiving oxygen at higher intensity levels. You can use this as a baseline to determine how hard an athlete is working</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Various Discussions and Posts on LLMs</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-16 09:44:40</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/various-discussions-and-posts-on-llms.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/various-discussions-and-posts-on-llms.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Whether it is a flash in the pan or whether we're truly living in a time of great technological acceleration due to the advancement of LLMs, I do not know. What I do know is there are concerns and predictions across the board about the disruption LLMs are bringing -- to the economy, to education, to our very sense of what it means to be human.</p>

<p>This week I just happened to listen to and read quite a lot about "AI", that catch-all term we're currently using for the large language models built by Anthropic, OpenAI, Google, and so on (Another big 3! Go figure.).</p>

<p>A few links to what I came across this week:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/13/opinion/ezra-klein-podcast-rebecca-winthrop.html">Ezra Klein (maybe my favorite podcast interview show) interviewed Rebecca Winthrop</a>, the director of the Center for Universal Education at the Brookings Institution. I don't know anything about her, or didn't before this interview. What I found important in this conversation was the grappling with education and its purpose. Of course, even prior to the rise of LLMs as a "cheating tool," the value of education -- especially higher education -- was in question across the U.S. </p>

<p>And rightfully so! In my opinion, anyway. We got the purpose of higher ed all mixed up with the economy and the job market. When that happened, most people started needing some form of higher ed credential to even "be successful" (a term I'll leave there for now, knowing it is fraught). So then college becomes the game we play to make money and live our life as adults. That was already a problem prior to the rise of LLMs. And now, we have this magic tool that will largely do the work for us. If the purpose is the credential, and the credential is for material success, then OF COURSE. Of course our students will cheat. It makes no sense not to cheat.</p>

<p>But this conversation brings to light the real, foundational questions, which are:</p>

<ul>
<li>What is education?</li>
<li>What is education for?</li>
<li>How should education take place?</li>
</ul>

<p>(For those of you following for a long time, you'll know these are my baseline questions for understanding <em>anything</em>: What is it? What is it for?)</p>

<p>And of course, to really answer those questions, we need to ask even MORE fundamental questions -- what does it mean to be human? what does it mean to live a good life? Yet again, we were already encountering this problem in society, having lost the moorings of common ethical and religious foundations. I'm off on a tangent now, but LLMs, in this way, are apocalyptic in the literal sense. They reveal the truth of the matter, which is that we largely lack a cohesive narrative for orienting our lives.</p>

<p>The episode doesn't quite get into those last questions, but it is a thought-provoking conversation, especially as we are very involved in our kids' education and have thoughts about what it should do for them.</p>

<p>This morning I also listened to R<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wNJJ9QUabkA">oss Douthat interview Daniel Kokotajlo</a>, former OpenAI employee and current executive director of the AI Futures Project. Kokotajlo believes that by 2027, AGI will not only exist but will also fundamentally remake the economy and the world as we know it. There will largely be no jobs because AI superintelligence will far outstrip humans' ability in basically all areas. This will be followed by a time of superabundance and will obviously be highly disruptive worldwide. While this was an interesting conversation, and I do not doubt that LLMs and whatever other versions of AI will continue to rapidly expand in its capabilities, I ultimately find these predictions unconvincing. Human systems are slow. Governments are slow. Corporations are slow. <em>Even if</em> the technology expands the way the interviewee says they will, I think there are pretty hard limits on how these tools are utilized. My primary thought for this entire interview was "Maybe he should have just become a sci-fi writer." His imagination is certainly capable of producing fascinating (if outlandish) scenarios.</p>

<p>H/T Alan Jacobs for <a href="https://nealstephenson.substack.com/p/remarks-on-ai-from-nz">this quote from Neal Stephenson</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Speaking of the effects of technology on individuals and society as a whole, Marshall McLuhan wrote that every augmentation is also an amputation...  Today, quite suddenly, billions of people have access to AI systems that provide augmentations, and inflict amputations, far more substantial than anything McLuhan could have imagined. This is the main thing I worry about currently as far as AI is concerned. I follow conversations among professional educators who all report the same phenomenon, which is that their students use ChatGPT for everything, and in consequence learn nothing.</p>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p>Ultimately, my thoughts on LLMs are varied. They are technical miracles, and can produce "better than the best available human" in so many cases. I've used it multiple times for code questions, for gardening questions, and asked about illnesses. It is only getting "better." So perhaps the question we ought to ask ourselves is, what is it that this tool can never do that humans can? What do humans possess that this tool does not?</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 1</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-15 15:40:20</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-1.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-1.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In prepping for a new upcoming cross country season (with what will hopefully also be a good ramp up with summer training sessions for the team), I'm reading Daniels' Running Formula, and also would like to restart <em>Lore of Running</em> by Tim Noakes. <em>Lore</em> is a much larger and more technical book. In the meantime though, I feel like the best way to absorb this information is not only to read and mark up the book but also jot down notes from the chapter in summary to help it stick in my brain and refer back to when I need some guidance during the season.</p>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<h3>The Basic Ingredients</h3>

<p>There are four basic ingredients of success for runners: inherent ability, intrinsic motivation, opportunity, and direction.</p>

<p>Inherent ability is a "no-brainer" kind of factor. One that is likely the most important and cannot be changed. But when paired with motivation, opportunity, and direction, lower inherent ability can be trumped.</p>

<p>For runners who have a lot of inherent ability but low intrinsic motivation, one way to increase motivation is "asking... runners to feel the workouts and to feel the same workout getting easier before increasing training stress." (7)</p>

<p>For the opposite runner -- lower ability, higher motivation -- it can be important to emphasize that success and growth can happen in different time frames for different runners for a variety of reasons. Therefore "Every runniner should have short-term and long-term goals to shoot for." (7)</p>

<p>Opportunity, fortunately, is there for nearly all people. Running is neither expensive nor does it require specific weather or situations.</p>

<p>Direction largely has to do with coaching:</p>

<ul>
<li>"A good coach can always answer the questions 'What is the purpose of this workout?' and 'Why are we doing this workout today?'" (11)</li>
<li>"What coaches tend to overlook is the importance of giving positive individual attention to each athlete on the team. Nthing can replace encouraging comments or understanding words from a coach." (11)</li>
</ul>

<h3>Daniels' Basic Laws of Running:</h3>

<ul>
<li>Every runner has specific individual abilities. </li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "the main emphasis should be taking advantage of known strengths" (12)</p>

<ul>
<li>A runner's focus must stay positive.</li>
<li>Expect ups and cowns; some days are better than others</li>
<li>Be flexible in training to allow for the unexpected.</li>
<li>Set intermediate goals. (nb: try "smaller goals" that might lead to failure but provide a learning experience)</li>
<li>Concentrate on the task at hand.</li>
<li>Most mistakes in races are made early in the race.</li>
<li>Training should be rewarding</li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "It's not always fun, but it should always be rewarding." (13)</p>

<ul>
<li>Eat and sleep well.</li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "If you regularly eat and sleep well, one bad meal or poor night's sleep will ot have a negative effect on you." (13)</p>

<ul>
<li>Don't train when sick or injured.</li>
<li>Chronic health issues should be checked by a professional.</li>
<li>A good race or run is never a fluke.</li>
</ul>

<p>Key quote: "Sometimes a bad run is a fluke, but if you do run a great race, it is because you are capable of doing it." (14)</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>"Consistency in training is the single most important thing that leads to success." (14)</p>

<hr />

<p>I'm happy to say after reading through the first chapter, much of the training philosophy here is what has guided my own approach to coaching. That's not to say I haven't had my failures, but I think that's more because of a lack of a formula or guiding principle &amp; scientific research to undergird how I'm training athletes. I'm hoping the next chapters will help me build on that foundation of what I already know and am doing. And perhaps help correct me where I have been wrong.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Various Running Links and Quotes</title>
            <pubDate>2025-04-14 10:37:01</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/various-running-links-and-quotes.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/various-running-links-and-quotes.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Well it's definitely been a while since my last post. As per usual in my own life, I go through different seasons where my focal length (to borrow a technical metaphor from photography) narrows and I can only do so much.</p>

<p>Cue track and field since February... and, you know, all of Elaine's vestibular migraine ups and downs. More on that later, I supposed.</p>

<p>Anyway, because I'm a learner at heart, I've consistently got a backlog of links and quotes I've gathered. I want to be better about tracking that and storing it, but it can sometimes get away from me. The purpose of this post is just to track a few of the links, quotes, and resources I've come across in the last month or so when trying to learn some better coaching methods or thinking about what a summer cross country training program should look like.</p>

<p><a href="https://run.wxm.be/summer-of-malmo/">Summer of Malmo</a></p>

<p>There seems to be a longer resource somewhere out there ("Malmo's Manifesto") that I can't access without paying for a subscription to Scribd. Malmo has a summer program of sorts for runners prepping for the fall. The gist:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Aimed at people with enough time in their summer (e.g., students on summer break)
    Run more
    Double 4+ days a week
    Meet up with others twice a week at the track
    Once for ~threshold (6.5 - 10 km total)
    Once for longer intervals, either
    4-6x1200-2000, one lap jog
    16-24x150-300m with 300m full recovery
    Slower people can just take a break more often and hop back in, because track</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Also in the manifesto:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Run twice a day, as many days as you can. Hopefully five, six or seven days a week.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Run more. How much? I dunno. You figure it out, but find out for yourself.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Run it faster.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Love running and LOVE racing.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Stay focused.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Set goals and don't be afraid to fail.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Listen to your body and don't be afraid to rest.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Compete WITH your comrades in sweat - never AGAINST them.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <ol>
    <li>Smile a lot.</li>
    </ol>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<hr />

<p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/running/comments/wi43kw/comment/ij9pfvp/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button">A user on Reddit about what should count as "tempo pace."</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Threshold pace usually refers to the (upper) lactate threshold. As a rule of thumb, it is the pace you can hold for about one hour at race conditions, e.g., well rested and tapered, on a fast course. In training, you can hold that pace for 15-40 minutes at a rather hard effort. At 6:20/mile for your recent 1:23 half, threshold pace is a just a tiny little bit faster than that, but still closer to your HM race pace that to your 10k race pace.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Some people then use this backwards: they refer to the pace you can hold for a one hour race as threshold pace, and use that as an indication for where your lactate threshold is.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>In reality, your average training loop likely will be slower than that HM race course where some nice flat roads have been blocked off for the runners, and that needs to be taken into account. When I was much younger and able to run such paces, my threshold runs actually ended up slightly slower than HM race pace, simply because of terrain and cumulative fatigue.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>In any case, threshold runs are longer runs at approximately (upper) lactate threshold pace, perhaps with very short breaks. For example, Daniels might have you do 4x6 minutes at T-pace with 1 minute rest.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Tempo run is a poorly defined term. It will have different meanings for different people. It will depend very heavily on what your training goals are. Say, are you preparing for an 800m race, or for an ultra in the mountains? Some people simply use "tempo run" as a synonym for a threshold run. After all, both words begin with a T.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Finally, any such workouts are effective half marathon training, but quite demanding. Don't do too many of those, there is a relevant injury risk.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>^I thought that was a pretty good descriptor, though perhaps I should do some more reading of the literature. The often frustrating thing about running and training is that there are elements of what we understand about training that are evidence-based, and then there is the "feel" of it. Sometimes you just gotta let it rip and see what happens.</p>

<hr />

<p>I discovered a runner/coach named John Lydiard who seems to have been a pioneer from the 60s of the ways we think about training now for distance racing (e.g., building an aerobic base, then building speed and strength, then "sharpening").</p>

<p>See this Reddit comment <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/AdvancedRunning/comments/nglu42/comment/gyv8r6x/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button">here</a>, this article on Runner's World(<a href="https://www.runnersworld.com/advanced/a20825109/training-the-lydiard-way-28-weeks-to-a-pr/">"Training the Lydiard Way"</a>), and the John Kellogg article on page 14 of this USATF publication (<a href="https://trackandfieldnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/TC216-1.pdf">"Revving the Cardiovascular Engine"</a>).</p>

<hr />

<p>Teaching hurdles is a new thing for me this year. The best resource by far that I found is ACE Method Coaching (run by Mike Caton)</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1P3jB2YRfJySaeiXy56TYgNzFhHHbxEt6kEIZRHeqwzM/edit?gid=0#gid=0">Hurdle Technique &amp; Drill Guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLKwbFInCAQIckoJorQmY_vXUiew5bypIL">An excellent playlist for general coaching</a></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>From Outside Online, <a href="https://www.outsideonline.com/health/running/training/training-plans/blueprint-master-the-mile/?scope=anon">how to train for a 1600m race</a> (for an older runner like me!)</p>

<hr />

<p>Books or certifications I'm looking at to read or complete:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.fixingyourfeet.com/fixing-your-feet/">Fixing Your Feet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.coachjayjohnson.com/">Coach Jay Johnson</a> - for his XC and Track Training Systems</li>
<li><a href="https://www.usatf.org/programs/coaches/usatf-campus-online">USATF's online campus</a></li>
<li><a href="https://nfhslearn.com/courses/first-aid-health-and-safety">NFHS First Aid Health and Safety</a></li>
<li><a href="https://acemethodcoaching.com/product/bronze-bundle/">ACE Method's Hurdle Mastery series</a></li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Best of 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-12-27 13:15:29</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Another year, another review. I'll be 100% honest, I both want and don't want to do this right now. Elaine just got back from the hospital yesterday after an extreme migraine that presented with stroke-like symptoms. I want to remember this year though, and don't want this to get lost in the static. Maybe another post will be forthcoming, but I don't know how much I want to relive a somewhat traumatic Christmas Day.</p>

<h1>Music</h1>

<p>2024 was Kendrick's year, no question.</p>

<h3>Favorite Songs</h3>

<p>Yet again, I don't feel like Spotify Wrapped captured the musical year for me. It may have even been worse than <a href="https://cbaca.blog/best-of-2023.html">last year</a>. But! Regardless of what they said I mostly listened to, I feel like we had a pretty great musical year. Here's another Spotify playlist of my favorites:</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/0NF9z5n8gXskwcb1w26HD7?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="352" frameBorder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3>Favorite Albums (and a word about big "moments")</h3>

<p>The beginning of the year was filled with boygenius's <em>the record</em>, and Tyler Childers's <em>Live on Red Barn Radio I &amp; II</em>. </p>

<p>After that, I think it was primarily a hip-hop year, with some incredible releases:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Ultra 85</em> - Logic</li>
<li><em>Chromakopia</em> - Tyler, the Creator</li>
<li><em>Bando Stone and the New World</em> - Childish Gambino</li>
<li><em>Samurai</em> - Lupe Fiasco</li>
</ul>

<p>and OF COURSE:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>GNX</em> - Kendrick Lamar</li>
</ul>

<p>The Kendrick and Drake beef was the highlight of the year. It's been talked about a bajillion times online and I do not need to repeat the story. But waking up every day or every other day for over a week to new diss tracks, and watching Kendrick just completely dominate from "eupohoria" forward was thrilling.</p>

<p>Three other albums worth mentioning:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Weezer (blue)</em> - Weezer (there was a 30 year deluxe release and it was fun to rediscover the album)</li>
<li><em>No Name</em> - Jack White (this album just absolutely rips)</li>
<li><em>Beethoven Blues</em> - Jon Batiste</li>
</ul>

<h1>Movies</h1>

<p>The standout movies this year for me were:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Dune, part II</em> - movie of the year for me. The sandworm scene, the end fight scene, and of course Paul's speech when he fully embraces his role as the Lisan al-Gaib (that scene gives me goosebumps every time I watch it)</li>
<li><em>Wicked</em> - I'm starting to realize just how much I like musicals</li>
<li><em>Midsommar</em> - Not released this year, but we watched it for the first time. Insane movie. Not a "favorite" but it really stuck in my head.</li>
<li><em>Deadpool and Wolverine</em> - just super fun</li>
<li><em>Wild Robot</em> - also fun, and quite touching</li>
<li><em>Wonka</em> - continuing the Timothée love</li>
<li><em>Poor Things</em> - So strange. Another "not a favorite" but it stuck in my head movie.</li>
<li><em>Interstellar</em> - IMAX re-release. It was amazing and overwhelming. Standout scene was the moment when Cooper had to re-align the two spaceships. It was <em>almost</em> too much to watch.</li>
</ul>

<h1>TV</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>The Penguin</em></li>
<li><em>No Good Deed</em></li>
<li><em>Nobody Wants This</em></li>
<li><em>Sopranos (season 1)</em> - I watched this when I had the flu in September, great TV.</li>
<li><em>The Joy of Painting with Bob Ross</em> - Silly, but we turn this on for Cooper every time we leave the house, and then we inadvertently watch it for one or two episodes at some point during the day.</li>
<li><em>Seinfeld</em></li>
<li><em>Six Feet Under</em> - we're still in the middle of watching season 1, but it's good
-<em>Love is Blind, seasons 6 and 7</em> - trash, but great trash?</li>
<li><em>3 Body Problem</em> - not as good as the book, of course, but fun anyway</li>
</ul>

<h1>Books</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>Shift</em> - Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Dust</em> - Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Four Thousand Weeks</em> - Oliver Burkeman</li>
<li><em>On the Edge of the Dark Sea of Darkness</em> - Andrew Peterson</li>
<li><em>Station Eleven</em> - Emily St. John Mandel</li>
<li><em>Cibola Burn</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Nemesis Games</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Babylon's Ashes</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Moonbound</em> - Robin Sloan</li>
<li><em>Fellowship of the Ring</em> - J.R.R. Tolkien</li>
<li><em>When We Cease to Understand the World</em> - Benjamin Labatut</li>
<li><em>Demon Copperhead</em> - Barbara Kingsolver</li>
<li><em>Piranesi</em> - Susanna Clarke</li>
<li><em>The Silent Patient</em> - Alex Michaelides</li>
</ul>

<h1>Everything Else</h1>

<p>Notable events and things from the year:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>We started attending <a href="asd.church">All Saints Dallas</a> around July of this year, and this is the first time is a family in a few years that we have all <em>wanted</em> to be attending somewhere regularly.</p></li>
<li><p>This was my first year coaching cross country in a long time. There were so many cool moments, and it was great to be able to coach a team again. Despite some of its difficulties, coaching brings me joy in a way that many things do not.</p></li>
<li><p>I spent such a large portion of the year training for the Dinosaur Valley Endurance Run (25K). Lots and lots of weeks with lots and lots of miles. But I felt so strong and good overall. To make a long story short, I was going to run on the Saturday of the race, but nerves got the better of me, and I was up until about 2:30 AM. I was so lucky that the race organizers allowed shorter distances to run on either Saturday or Sunday without pre-notification, so I punted, moved to Sunday, and ran a great race (4th overall, 1st in my age group).</p></li>
<li><p>We took a little weekend trip to Kansas City in July to visit some good friends up there. It was filled with good food, lake relaxing, and just space to be friends. (Also, I'll probably always remember this was the weekend of the attempted assassination. Wild.)</p></li>
<li><p>We have a 13 year old 😵‍💫</p></li>
<li><p>I shot my first ducks this year! Hoping to become (albeit intermittently) something of a small game hunter in the coming years.</p></li>
</ul>

<hr />

<p>There was, of course, so much more. I'll address a couple of those things in the looking forward to 2025 post. But also, you just can't capture a year in words. These are the things that stand out now. As always, I'm grateful for another year with my beautiful family, another year of joy, sadness, grief, excitement, and all the things in between.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>