<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Best of 2023</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-11 19:23:35</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2023.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2023.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Starting this post early this year because I want to make sure that I get everything down that I want to get down. 2023 was... wild? Not sure if that is quite the right word for it. It certainly held so much for me and for our family. I'll get to that at the bottom of the post. But for now, let's go over my favorite things of the year:</p>

<h1>Music</h1>

<h3>Favorite Songs</h3>

<p>I seem to have mostly kept with the 2000s indie | 90s/00s hip-hop | pop | progressive bluegrass trend. My favorite songs of the year are compiled here in this Spotify playlist:</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/2ysmC07e9WEr7iYE8hmG00?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameBorder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<p>I love Spotify Wrapped, but I never feel like it <em>quite</em> captures the overall feel of my music for the year. Usually when I come across a new song that I listen to a ton, it gets thrown in this playlist. I also don't feel like I came across as much truly new music this year as I have in previous years.</p>

<h3>Favorite Albums</h3>

<ul>
<li><em>GUTS</em> - Olivia Rodrigo</li>
<li><em>Celebrants</em> - Nickel Creek</li>
<li><em>Beneath the Medicine Tree</em> - Copeland (old but rediscovered this year)</li>
<li><em>College Park</em> - Logic</li>
<li><em>the record</em> - boygenius (new to me in December but enjoying it a lot)</li>
<li><em>Transatlanticism</em> - Death Cab for Cutie</li>
</ul>

<h3>Concerts</h3>

<ul>
<li>June 2023 - Nickel Creek | <em>Celebrants</em> tour</li>
<li>September 2023 - Switchfoot | 20 year <em>Beautiful Letdown</em> tour</li>
<li>October 2023 - Deathcab for Cutie | 20 year <em>Transatlanticism</em> tour + Postal Service | 20 year <em>Give Up</em> tour</li>
</ul>

<h1>Movies</h1>

<p>(these were all I could remember but I'm sure there are more)</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Barbarian</em></li>
<li><em>Spider-Man: Across the Spider-Verse</em></li>
<li><em>TMNT: Mutant Mayhem</em></li>
<li><em>The Marvels</em></li>
<li><em>Everything Everywhere All at Once</em></li>
<li><em>Parasite</em></li>
<li><em>Ant-Man: Quantumania</em></li>
<li><em>Elemental</em> (saw this on our epic midwest roadtrip, half of us were sick lol)</li>
<li><em>Guardians of the Galaxy, Vol. 3</em> (great first use of "fuck" in the MCU)</li>
<li><em>Oppenheimer</em></li>
<li><em>Barbie</em></li>
<li><em>Knock at the Cabin</em></li>
<li><em>The Rental</em></li>
<li><em>Bodies Bodies Bodies</em></li>
<li><em>No Hard Feelings</em></li>
<li><em>A Haunting in Venice</em></li>
<li><em>Mission Impossible: Dead Reckoning</em></li>
<li><em>The Unbearable Weight of Massive Talent</em></li>
<li><em>The Killer</em></li>
<li><em>Leave the World Behind</em></li>
</ul>

<h1>TV</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>The Bear</em> (S2, kept the momentum going for sure)</li>
<li><em>You</em> (S4)</li>
<li><em>Ted Lasso</em> (S3)</li>
<li><em>The Crowded Room</em></li>
<li><em>Black Mirror</em> (S6)</li>
<li><em>Beef</em> (up there with Loki and The Bear for top 2023 contenders)</li>
<li><em>Dave</em> (season 3, good, but not as great as S2. "Hearsay" was a banger though.)</li>
<li><em>Silo</em></li>
<li><em>The Last of Us</em></li>
<li><em>Succession</em> (started, I think we're in S2 now)</li>
<li><em>Loki</em> (S2, best Marvel has done in a long time)</li>
<li><em>Doctor Who</em> 60th anniversary specials (David Tennant is back!)</li>
<li><em>Lessons in Chemistry</em></li>
</ul>

<h1>Books</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>Gilead</em> - Marilynne Robinson</li>
<li><em>Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince</em> - J.K. Rowling (to Lyla)</li>
<li><em>Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban</em> - J.K. Rowling (to Paisley)</li>
<li><em>Strange Rites</em> - Tara Isabella Burton</li>
<li><em>Jonathan Strange and Mr. Norrell</em> - Susanna Clarke | <strong>The favorite this year</strong></li>
<li><em>Shop Class as Soul Craft</em> - Matthew B. Crawford</li>
<li><em>The Three Body Problem</em> - Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>The Dark Forest</em> - Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>Death's End</em> - Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>The Postmortal</em> - Drew Magary</li>
<li><em>Wool</em> - Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Shift</em> - Hugh Howey (anticipating finishing this before the end of 2023)</li>
</ul>

<h1>Everything Else</h1>

<p>This truly was a big year for our family. I talked about some of this in my <a href="https://cbaca.blog/status-update-10-17-23.html">October 2023 update</a>, but the biggest obvious things are that I started a new job at <a href="https://greenline.nyc">Green Line Digital</a> in January, and we finished up our house selling/purchasing process in October/November. We now live in a much newer home with just a little more space for our family. It has been a dream so far.</p>

<p>The girls started 4th and 7th grade, and things are definitely changing for Lyla. It's so strange to see someone genuinely grow up right before your eyes, but that's what she is doing 12/13 is a big year for her.</p>

<p>One of my main goals for the year was my desire to pursue <a href="https://cbaca.blog/looking-to-2023-presence-and-ease.html">presence + ease</a>. I think that I sometimes got this right, but mostly I failed. Starting a new job was a big change for us as a family. While I really do love remote work and wouldn't trade it, there was a big learning curve for all of us, and I often struggled to not be frustrated when we were all home together and I felt the pressure of doing well at a new job. I do think that the end of the year is better than the beginning, especially in terms of being more present. One quote from <em>Gilead</em> that I put in that post was:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Irritation is a form of anger, I recognize that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And it still haunts me somewhat. I am more easily irritated than I want to be, especially at my kiddos, and I want to continue to work on this. Another post will come, I think, where I look at how I want to look forward to the 2024.</p>

<h3>Another couple of highlights:</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>We bought two farm-fresh turkeys for Thanksgiving. Due to weird timing, Elaine's brother and I had to take the turkeys (Snowflake and Thunder) to get slaughtered and processed. I really didn't know how this would go, and thought I wouldn't want to eat them. But honestly, it was quite an enlightening experience, and those birds had "one bad day" as my sister-in-law likes to say.</p></li>
<li><p>Not long after that, my best friend from high school and I went duck hunting, which was also a new experience for me. We didn't shoot anything that day, but it was a blast being out there, and honestly made me want to give it a shot again. I'd love to go hunting a few times a year just to be a little more connected to my food and nature.</p></li>
<li><p>As a celebration of a new job and Elaine's parents moving from GA to TX, we all went to Disney World in February. This was my second trip and a total blast. Lyla's first real roller coaster was Guardians of the Galaxy, and she was TERRIFIED the first time all the way through, but we got to ride it two more times while we were there. 100% the best roller coaster experience I've ever had. It was wild to get up very early and work so I could meet the family at the parks in the afernoon though.</p></li>
<li><p>We had a long midwest road trip as a family in June. We drove through Kansas City (saw some other old high school friends, and saw Nickel Creek live, which was the girls' first concert ever!), St. Louis, on up to Chicago. Chicago was such a fun time, and it was a place none of us had ever visited. Saw the Cubs play, had deep dish (meh), went to the Museum of Science and Industry, walked Navy Pier, saw the Bean, had Intelligentsia, went to Indiana Dunes National Park. On the way back we stayed in Branson, MO which is WAYYYY prettier than I would have ever thought. In the kindness of an old friend from college, we got to stay in a cabin in the woods and it was beautiful. Branson wasn't much, but Lambert's was maybe the best country food I've ever eaten.</p></li>
<li><p>Watching the division and world series of the MLB and experiencing the Rangers FINALLY winning a title with Elaine and her family (who are huge fans).</p></li>
<li><p>My first blood nephew was born, and we got to meet him on his second day on the planet.</p></li>
<li><p>Went to Louisiana, had a Darrell's special (not as good as my dad said it would be) and saw baby alligators at a roadside attraction place that I passed a million times when I was a kid.</p></li>
<li><p>Lyla had three theater performances (Cinderella, Jungle Book, Game of Tiaras, The Audition) and Paisley had one (Cinderella, Jungle Book)</p></li>
<li><p>I took about six months to beat <em>The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em> -- a fantastic game, but man it's hard to find enough time to beat massive games like this</p></li>
<li><p>Buzzed my head for the first time ever, that was cool for about a week, and then I hated it.</p></li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>People and Blogs Series -  Manuel Moreale</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-08 08:11:35</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/people-and-blogs-series-manuel-moreale.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/people-and-blogs-series-manuel-moreale.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I keep ringing the bell a million times over, but I'm such a huge fan of the indie web and blogs in particular. I think it's the best way to resist the pull of large-scale corporations running the internet, and the barrier for entry (despite the technical knowledge sometimes required) is so low, that I think this is the way forward for keeping part of the internet sane.</p>

<p>A series I'm really enjoying from an indie blogger is a weekly series that <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/">Manuel Moreale</a> is running over at his blog. The series is "People &amp; Blogs" and he's just interviewing other folks on the internet running blogs and who are keeping up their own little corners of the web. The <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/pb-eli-mellen">most recent one</a> dropped today, and all of them are worth perusing.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>The Blog is Already Back</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-04 16:14:14</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-blog-is-already-back.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-blog-is-already-back.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Now that the white-hot fire of Twitter is burning itself out, and its various alternatives (Threads, Bluesky, Mastodon) are generating merely gentle (or sputtering) flames, and TikTok (which is not a social-media site in any meaningful sense but rather a media-consumption platform) is still going nova, this is the time for people to rediscover the pleasures of blogging – of writing at whatever length you want, and posting photos, and embedding videos, and linking to music playlists, all on your little corner of the internet.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Let’s bring back the blog. And leave all the bad things spawned by the blogosphere to social media, where they belong. </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/bring-back-the-blog/">"Bring Back the Blog"</a>, Alan Jacobs</p>

<p>See, the thing is, I think the blog is already back. Just because social media giants (and <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">the small guys too</a>) are taking up most of the discourse w/r/t web interaction doesn't mean the blog is not back. Thankfully, most of the interesting stuff I find now isn't through social media anymore. It's still through RSS, and still through indie blogs run by regular ol' people like you and me.</p>

<p>I think the only thing I'd really like to see is an easier way / lower barrier for entry into indie blogging. I can figure out how to put together <a href="https://github.com/cdbaca/ssg">a little static site generator of my own</a>, and blog through my terminal and text files. I doubt most regular folks can do that. And my sense is that Wordpress and other tools like it are too heavy for most folks' use.</p>

<p>I did find <a href="https://blot.im/">this little tool</a> the other day (via my RSS feed, via an indie blog!) which is pretty cool and simple. Looks as easy as having a couple folders on your computer, linking to something like Dropbox, and syncing up the folders once you've written a post or shared an image.</p>

<p>Anyway, to the original point of this post -- blogging might have done a little hibernating while we all experimented with a few sites that functioned as somewhat-global town squares. But my sense is that it is reawakening and ready to give us a warm, cozy hug when we are ready for it again.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Algorithms and Gen Alpha</title>
            <pubDate>2023-11-30 09:31:07</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/algorithms-and-gen-alpha.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/algorithms-and-gen-alpha.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Parents of Gen Alpha must take this seriously. I speak to many parents about social media; they worry that their kids will talk to predators or be exposed to explicit self-harm and suicidal content — which are, of course, real risks. But there is also something more pernicious, and more destabilizing happening. Something we have to get ahead of. Because maybe it seems like your child is simply watching some makeup tutorials, following some mental health influencers, or experimenting with their identity. But let me tell you: they are on a conveyor belt to someplace bad. Whatever insecurity or vulnerability they are struggling with, they will be pushed further and further into it. </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>What I would say to the parents of Gen Alpha is: don’t let your children open accounts on social media platforms when they are still in early puberty. Delay their entry until at least 16. Prioritize their in-person interactions, and encourage them to discover who they are from real-world experiences, not manipulative algorithms.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/algorithms-hijacked-my-generation">"Algorithms Hijacked My Generation. I Fear For Gen Alpha."</a>, Freya India</p>

<p>I'm a little wary of fear mongering w/r/t social media and technology, but the truth is my escape from nearly all social media (damn you, YouTube) has been monumental for my own day to day mental health. Not even in a clinical sense. I just feel happier, more connected, less anxious.</p>

<p>And the above is why we still have not allowed our kiddos to have phones. They occasionally use devices for school or a few minutes of searching for something, but we have tried to be very intentional about the internet being a tool, not something to just scroll through and be fed by. Here's to hoping we can stick it out, because I have the same concerns as Freya.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Computer Science Ed - Applicative vs. Normal Order Evaluation</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-26 13:19:12</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/computer-science-ed-applicative-vs-normal-order-evaluation.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/computer-science-ed-applicative-vs-normal-order-evaluation.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I recently started reading <a href="https://sarabander.github.io/sicp/html/index.xhtml#SEC_Contents"><em>Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</em></a> (the first recommended book in the <a href="www.teachyourselfcs.com">Teach Yourself CS</a> curriculum). I'm not even past the first section of the first chapter, and there are already concepts I'm coming across that never crossed my mind before, despite working with Python and Javascript for the last few years.</p>

<p>One concept I found interesting and yet difficult to grasp at first is the idea of the order in which computeres evaluate procedures. In SICP, they write of Scheme (a subset of the Lisp programming language) that it is an applicative-order language. That is,</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>All the arguments to Scheme procedures are evaluated when the procedure is applied. In contrast, normal-order languages dalay evaluation of procedure arguments until the actual argument values are needed.
    --1.1.5, <a href="https://sarabander.github.io/sicp/html/1_002e1.xhtml#g_t1_002e1_002e5:~:text=Applicative%20order%20versus%20normal%20order">"Applicative order versus normal order"</a></p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>The example problem used to confirm that Scheme is an applicative-order language is the definition of two procedures and a calling of the test procedure:</p>

<p><code>
    (define (p) (p))
    (define (test x y)
        (if (= x 0)
        0
        y))
    (test 0 (p))
</code></p>

<p>Because Scheme is an applicative-order language, the interpreter attempts to evaluate all the arguments within the test procedure <em>first</em> before the full procedure is applied. When it tries to do this, (p) is called infinitely because (p) calls itself. The interpreter can never finish calling the actual procedure we're attempting to call because it's trying to determine a true value for (p) before determining whether x = 0 or not.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>