<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Site Design Inspiration - Carl Barenbrug</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-31 14:29:20</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/site-design-inspiration-carl-barenbrug.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/site-design-inspiration-carl-barenbrug.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Love the site design <a href="https://carlbarenbrug.com/">here</a>. May consider a change in the new year for this blog. Yet another great find from Manu's <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/people-and-blogs">P&amp;B series</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Looking to 2024: Creation, Fun, and Thoughtfulness</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-31 14:27:27</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/looking-to-2024-creation-fun-and-thoughtfulness.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/looking-to-2024-creation-fun-and-thoughtfulness.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Before I look to 2024, it would probably be best to do a quick look back on how I fared in <a href="https://cbaca.blog/looking-to-2023-presence-and-ease.html">my personal goals for 2023</a>. My goals for last year were centered around two words: "presence" and "ease."</p>

<p><strong>Presence</strong> was all about being in the moment, about trying to maintain presence of mind in my actual real life rather than being distracted in the mind or in my digital habits. I'd say that there was a good portion of the year where I did okay with that, but certainly towards the end of the year my habits (especially my digital habits) tended towards distraction and doomscrolling. One of my more practical goals at the beginning of 2024 will be to decrease my reliance on my phone for boredom and awkwardness and tend towards the analog/physical.</p>

<p><strong>Ease</strong> was to try to pursue an approach to life that was less irritable when new or frustrating things happened. The goal was "ease" in life, not by avoiding hard things, but by changing my perspective. Again, I do think that I somewhat improved in this area, but as I'll mention below, I think there is more I can do here to make this a reality in my daily life.</p>

<hr />

<p>For this year, the three words I want to focus on are 
<strong>creation</strong>, 
<strong>fun</strong>, and 
<strong>thoughtfulness</strong>.</p>

<p>I have chosen these words intentionally, as I believe they either relate to new practices I want to pursue or because they are extensions of last year's goals. </p>

<h3>On Creation</h3>

<p>By <strong>creation</strong> I mean the act of being creative. A large portion of my life (a minimum of ~40+ hours!) is spent in the digital world. I work as a data analyst in digital marketing, and my day is filled with code and data ephemera. While I pretty much like what I do, and the way that it provides for our family, the truth is that it's a job filled with tasks that are digitally slippery. In other words, it's often difficult to point back to my work and see how it is physically affecting the world. Again, I don't <em>necessarily</em> mind that, but I do think that humans are built to find productivity satisfaction from having a physical effect on the real world.</p>

<ol>
<li>The main way I'd like to practice creation is by <strong>woodworking</strong>. I'm hoping this is a year that I can spend building real things with my hands. A small list of things I'd like to build:
<ul>
<li><em>Workbench</em></li>
<li><em>Learn to make dovetail joints and mortise and tenon joints</em></li>
<li><em>pencil boxes</em> (maybe for gifts)</li>
<li><em>whiskey cabinet</em> (that's the "big one" that I think would be a reach)</li>
</ul></li>
<li>The act of creation doesn't have to be out of the digital world though -- I would also like to build a basic web app for our family. The basic idea is that I want this to be a "family wishlist" app. One where there is a family group that you join, each person's address and birthday is stored. Each person has an associated wishlist of items they want for an upcoming birthday or holiday. The main page of the app will show the birthdays upcoming in the next thirty days (or if it's within 30 days of Christmas, it will show a list for everyone). I'm confident that I'm capable of this, especially on the backend of things, but I have never built something with interconnected data tables so there will be some fun challenge there.</li>
</ol>

<h3>On Fun</h3>

<p><strong>Fun</strong> is an interesting one for me to write. It feels strange to say out loud, because I think the truth is I haven't considered fun to be an important part of my own life. And to be quite honest it feels quite silly to even say "I want to have more fun." But the truth is I think it's the best word for what I'm trying to pursue. Having fun this year is the most direct extension of last year's ease goal. <strong>Fun</strong> was borne of my realization that nearly everyone in our family has some struggle with anxiety. While we express it in different ways, at the core of this is some level of fear of new experiences, a nearly overwhelming desire for constant routine, and a general lack of trust that everything that needs to get done will get done.</p>

<p>I don't know that I have tangible goals related to this overarching theme or something that I can specifically point back and stay accountable to. The only thing that comes to mind related to fun is not looking at new things like they are a chore, and being willing to say "yes" more often, especially when it is a new experience or when it's my kids asking me to do something. I'll keep thinking about this one, but I'm hoping for a slow-burn attitude change for myself here.</p>

<h3>On Thoughtfulness</h3>

<p><strong>Thoughtfulness</strong> is probably a general extension of the presence goal. Although I do think I had some personal, general improvements in this area, there are some parts of my life where I feel I am "just floating along." A good example of this is my faith. Again, this is another thing I'm writing about that gives me a general feeling of discomfort due to my long and checkered history with faith. 2023 was a good chance for me to step back from sort of brute forcing my faith after a couple of years of difficulty at <a href="https://www.lifeindeepellum.com">LIDE</a>, and another couple of years with some extended family estrangement revolving around matters of faith. Nevertheless, Christianity has left an indelible mark on my life -- one that is not easily ignored. And the truth is I find that I'm not interested in ignoring it. Jesus is compelling, and perhaps more than just that. Liturgies are beautiful and strange to our modern ears. Continuing to attend church at this time and place is, I think, still a subversive act.</p>

<p>But that's just one example of the things I think I'm not being thoughtful enough about. And I do think there are practical ways that I can be a more thoughtful person in 2024.</p>

<ol>
<li>About a month ago, Elaine, the girls, and I all started a Wednesday night family Bible study. We're currently doing a nine-week series on <a href="https://www.bible.com/reading-plans/28162">the basics of Chrsitianity</a> from The Bible Project. I'd like to truly make sure this continues so we can have engaging faith conversations as a family.</li>
<li>Reduce phone use by at least 1/2. My screen time on my phone has crept up to about 3 hours per day at the end of the year. Some of this is just being on vacation so it's understandable. But I would like this to be greatly reduced, especially as nearly all my working time is spent on a computer. Easiest and simplest way to do this (ugh) is to remove Chrome and other web browsers from my phone so I cannot scroll, then set a password so no apps can be easily downloaded without a serious amount of friction. I will need to find a new way to play Wordle and Connections though.</li>
<li>Conversely, I need to responsibly use the time and attention that I'm attempting to save. And in the spirit of trying to reduce my digital usage and increase my attention towards things that I care about, I think I want to move to a general two notebook system:
<ul>
<li>In the first notebook, I think I'd like to use some version of the bullet journal, which I had good success with a few years ago. Bullet journaling (not the fancy-schmancy kind) is generally used for time management and productivity tracking. I don't want to get too sentimental with this, and really would like to use it as a true tracking tool, nothing more than that.</li>
<li>In the second, I'd like to have something like a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commonplace_book">commonplace book</a>. This is just a way of keeping a notebook for quotes/thoughts/ideas that I care about, whether they come from me or somewhere else. This is, again, something that I think ought not to be sentimental, but just another tool in the repertoire for increasing contemplation, thoughtfulness, and my capacity for attention.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Digitally, since I cannot really escape that world and I do not think is beneficial to completely leave it, I'd like to increase the amount of blog posts I write this year. Most simply, I'd like to write one blog post per week. For the sake of making this more than just a "post a link" situation, it should only count as a blog post if I write a full paragraph.</li>
</ol>

<hr />

<p>So, this year's words: creation, fun, and thoughtfulness. This year's practical goals:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Woodworking</p></li>
<li><p>Create the "family wishlist" web app</p></li>
<li><p>Continue with family Bible study</p></li>
<li><p>Remove Chrome and any other app that allows me to infinitely scroll from my phone for at least an extended period of time (preferably a month, but maybe even the first half of the year)</p></li>
<li><p>Start using two notebooks: a bullet journal and a commonplace book</p></li>
<li><p>Blog at least 1x per week</p></li>
<li><p>(less tangibly) Start saying "yes" more often to my kids, and start to view diversions from the plan as a good thing, not a problem</p></li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Restoring an Old Hand Plane - Video</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-29 11:59:49</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/restoring-an-old-hand-plane-video.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/restoring-an-old-hand-plane-video.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Just got an old Bailey #5, and I'll be restoring it soon. Paul Sellers has some no-nonsense videos, and this seems like a very doable way to restore the one I just got.</p>

<iframe src=https://www.youtube.com/embed/RYyV6IUpsYk></iframe>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Links and Readings on Plain Text</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-20 10:26:56</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/links-and-readings-on-plain-text.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/links-and-readings-on-plain-text.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Via Manuel Morreale's People &amp; Blogs series, I came across some interesting writing, thoughts, and links on focusing on and using plain text for our digital lives. This is interesting to me because I like the thought that plain text is (at minimum) the most durable text format that we have right now (as opposed to .doc or some other file type).</p>

<h1>Here are some links / quotes on this topic:</h1>

<p><a href="https://www.gozgeek.com/posts/2021/my-journey-into-the-plain-text-life-intro/">"My Journey into the Plain Text Life - Intro"</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everything Buckets are selling you a filesystem, and removing the step of creating and saving a new file within that filesystem. That’s their primary value. Whatever organization scheme they may claim to offer, you can replicate on the filesystem. I promise. Even tags (symlinks, aliases - look ’em up).
  <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211227173721/https://www.al3x.net/blog/2009/01/31/the-case-against-everything-buckets">"The Case Against Everything Buckets"</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://plaintextproject.online/">Plain Text Project</a></p>

<p><a href="https://muckhacker.com/elements-of-the-web-text-519c1028ffce">Simple and Universal: A History of Plain Text, and Why It Matters</a></p>

<p><a href="https://tinybrain.fans/low-no-tech-productivity.html">Tiny Brains - Low/No-Tech Productivity</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Every few years a new company says you should use their special format. You have to pay them a monthly fee to use it — or keep all of your documents in their care. They offer some convenience or features, but at the cost of flexibility, portability, and independence.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you store your writing in one company’s unique format, then you need that program to access it. Then the economy takes a turn, they go out of business, and your work is trapped in an unusable format.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>You will outlive these companies. Your writing should outlive you. Depending on companies is not an option.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Plain text is un-commercial. It removes you from the world of subscriptions and hype. There will always be plenty of free, non-commercial software in the public domain for reading and editing text files.
  <a href="https://sive.rs/plaintext">"Write Plain Text Files"</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>My website build is pretty basic, and is essentially built around plain text files (in Markdown) and a couple of templates and Python scripts. But all of it is essentially plain text. At the time, I was building the site to learn about the very basics of personal web framework building (if you could even call it that). But I also stumbled into a world of more digital simplicity, and hopefully by virtue of that, more resilience.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Best of 2023</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-11 19:23:35</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2023.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2023.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Starting this post early this year because I want to make sure that I get everything down that I want to get down. 2023 was... wild? Not sure if that is quite the right word for it. It certainly held so much for me and for our family. I'll get to that at the bottom of the post. But for now, let's go over my favorite things of the year:</p>

<h1>Music</h1>

<h3>Favorite Songs</h3>

<p>I seem to have mostly kept with the 2000s indie | 90s/00s hip-hop | pop | progressive bluegrass trend. My favorite songs of the year are compiled here in this Spotify playlist:</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/playlist/2ysmC07e9WEr7iYE8hmG00?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameBorder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<p>I love Spotify Wrapped, but I never feel like it <em>quite</em> captures the overall feel of my music for the year. Usually when I come across a new song that I listen to a ton, it gets thrown in this playlist. I also don't feel like I came across as much truly new music this year as I have in previous years.</p>

<h3>Favorite Albums</h3>

<ul>
<li><em>GUTS</em> - Olivia Rodrigo</li>
<li><em>Celebrants</em> - Nickel Creek</li>
<li><em>Beneath the Medicine Tree</em> - Copeland (old but rediscovered this year)</li>
<li><em>College Park</em> - Logic</li>
<li><em>the record</em> - boygenius (new to me in December but enjoying it a lot)</li>
<li><em>Transatlanticism</em> - Death Cab for Cutie</li>
</ul>

<h3>Concerts</h3>

<ul>
<li>June 2023 - Nickel Creek | <em>Celebrants</em> tour</li>
<li>September 2023 - Switchfoot | 20 year <em>Beautiful Letdown</em> tour</li>
<li>October 2023 - Deathcab for Cutie | 20 year <em>Transatlanticism</em> tour + Postal Service | 20 year <em>Give Up</em> tour</li>
</ul>

<h1>Movies</h1>

<p>(these were all I could remember but I'm sure there are more)</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Barbarian</em></li>
<li><em>Spider-Man: Across the Spider-Verse</em></li>
<li><em>TMNT: Mutant Mayhem</em></li>
<li><em>The Marvels</em></li>
<li><em>Everything Everywhere All at Once</em></li>
<li><em>Parasite</em></li>
<li><em>Ant-Man: Quantumania</em></li>
<li><em>Elemental</em> (saw this on our epic midwest roadtrip, half of us were sick lol)</li>
<li><em>Guardians of the Galaxy, Vol. 3</em> (great first use of "fuck" in the MCU)</li>
<li><em>Oppenheimer</em></li>
<li><em>Barbie</em></li>
<li><em>Knock at the Cabin</em></li>
<li><em>The Rental</em></li>
<li><em>Bodies Bodies Bodies</em></li>
<li><em>No Hard Feelings</em></li>
<li><em>A Haunting in Venice</em></li>
<li><em>Mission Impossible: Dead Reckoning</em></li>
<li><em>The Unbearable Weight of Massive Talent</em></li>
<li><em>The Killer</em></li>
<li><em>Leave the World Behind</em></li>
</ul>

<h1>TV</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>The Bear</em> (S2, kept the momentum going for sure)</li>
<li><em>You</em> (S4)</li>
<li><em>Ted Lasso</em> (S3)</li>
<li><em>The Crowded Room</em></li>
<li><em>Black Mirror</em> (S6)</li>
<li><em>Beef</em> (up there with Loki and The Bear for top 2023 contenders)</li>
<li><em>Dave</em> (season 3, good, but not as great as S2. "Hearsay" was a banger though.)</li>
<li><em>Silo</em></li>
<li><em>The Last of Us</em></li>
<li><em>Succession</em> (started, I think we're in S2 now)</li>
<li><em>Loki</em> (S2, best Marvel has done in a long time)</li>
<li><em>Doctor Who</em> 60th anniversary specials (David Tennant is back!)</li>
<li><em>Lessons in Chemistry</em></li>
</ul>

<h1>Books</h1>

<ul>
<li><em>Gilead</em> - Marilynne Robinson</li>
<li><em>Harry Potter and the Half-Blood Prince</em> - J.K. Rowling (to Lyla)</li>
<li><em>Harry Potter and the Prisoner of Azkaban</em> - J.K. Rowling (to Paisley)</li>
<li><em>Strange Rites</em> - Tara Isabella Burton</li>
<li><em>Jonathan Strange and Mr. Norrell</em> - Susanna Clarke | <strong>The favorite this year</strong></li>
<li><em>Shop Class as Soul Craft</em> - Matthew B. Crawford</li>
<li><em>The Three Body Problem</em> - Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>The Dark Forest</em> - Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>Death's End</em> - Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>The Postmortal</em> - Drew Magary</li>
<li><em>Wool</em> - Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Shift</em> - Hugh Howey (anticipating finishing this before the end of 2023)</li>
</ul>

<h1>Everything Else</h1>

<p>This truly was a big year for our family. I talked about some of this in my <a href="https://cbaca.blog/status-update-10-17-23.html">October 2023 update</a>, but the biggest obvious things are that I started a new job at <a href="https://greenline.nyc">Green Line Digital</a> in January, and we finished up our house selling/purchasing process in October/November. We now live in a much newer home with just a little more space for our family. It has been a dream so far.</p>

<p>The girls started 4th and 7th grade, and things are definitely changing for Lyla. It's so strange to see someone genuinely grow up right before your eyes, but that's what she is doing 12/13 is a big year for her.</p>

<p>One of my main goals for the year was my desire to pursue <a href="https://cbaca.blog/looking-to-2023-presence-and-ease.html">presence + ease</a>. I think that I sometimes got this right, but mostly I failed. Starting a new job was a big change for us as a family. While I really do love remote work and wouldn't trade it, there was a big learning curve for all of us, and I often struggled to not be frustrated when we were all home together and I felt the pressure of doing well at a new job. I do think that the end of the year is better than the beginning, especially in terms of being more present. One quote from <em>Gilead</em> that I put in that post was:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Irritation is a form of anger, I recognize that.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And it still haunts me somewhat. I am more easily irritated than I want to be, especially at my kiddos, and I want to continue to work on this. Another post will come, I think, where I look at how I want to look forward to the 2024.</p>

<h3>Another couple of highlights:</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>We bought two farm-fresh turkeys for Thanksgiving. Due to weird timing, Elaine's brother and I had to take the turkeys (Snowflake and Thunder) to get slaughtered and processed. I really didn't know how this would go, and thought I wouldn't want to eat them. But honestly, it was quite an enlightening experience, and those birds had "one bad day" as my sister-in-law likes to say.</p></li>
<li><p>Not long after that, my best friend from high school and I went duck hunting, which was also a new experience for me. We didn't shoot anything that day, but it was a blast being out there, and honestly made me want to give it a shot again. I'd love to go hunting a few times a year just to be a little more connected to my food and nature.</p></li>
<li><p>As a celebration of a new job and Elaine's parents moving from GA to TX, we all went to Disney World in February. This was my second trip and a total blast. Lyla's first real roller coaster was Guardians of the Galaxy, and she was TERRIFIED the first time all the way through, but we got to ride it two more times while we were there. 100% the best roller coaster experience I've ever had. It was wild to get up very early and work so I could meet the family at the parks in the afernoon though.</p></li>
<li><p>We had a long midwest road trip as a family in June. We drove through Kansas City (saw some other old high school friends, and saw Nickel Creek live, which was the girls' first concert ever!), St. Louis, on up to Chicago. Chicago was such a fun time, and it was a place none of us had ever visited. Saw the Cubs play, had deep dish (meh), went to the Museum of Science and Industry, walked Navy Pier, saw the Bean, had Intelligentsia, went to Indiana Dunes National Park. On the way back we stayed in Branson, MO which is WAYYYY prettier than I would have ever thought. In the kindness of an old friend from college, we got to stay in a cabin in the woods and it was beautiful. Branson wasn't much, but Lambert's was maybe the best country food I've ever eaten.</p></li>
<li><p>Watching the division and world series of the MLB and experiencing the Rangers FINALLY winning a title with Elaine and her family (who are huge fans).</p></li>
<li><p>My first blood nephew was born, and we got to meet him on his second day on the planet.</p></li>
<li><p>Went to Louisiana, had a Darrell's special (not as good as my dad said it would be) and saw baby alligators at a roadside attraction place that I passed a million times when I was a kid.</p></li>
<li><p>Lyla had three theater performances (Cinderella, Jungle Book, Game of Tiaras, The Audition) and Paisley had one (Cinderella, Jungle Book)</p></li>
<li><p>I took about six months to beat <em>The Legend of Zelda: Tears of the Kingdom</em> -- a fantastic game, but man it's hard to find enough time to beat massive games like this</p></li>
<li><p>Buzzed my head for the first time ever, that was cool for about a week, and then I hated it.</p></li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>