<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>The Dark Forest of the Web</title>
            <pubDate>2023-01-04 10:57:04</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-dark-forest-of-the-web.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-dark-forest-of-the-web.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>The dark forest theory of the web points to the increasingly life-like but life-less state of being online. Most open and publicly available spaces on the web are overrun with bots, advertisers, trolls, data scrapers, clickbait, keyword-stuffing “content creators,” and algorithmically manipulated junk.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>It's like a dark forest that seems eerily devoid of human life – all the living creatures are hidden beneath the ground or up in trees. If they reveal themselves, they risk being attacked by automated predators.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Humans who want to engage in informal, unoptimised, personal interactions have to hide in closed spaces like invite-only Slack channels, Discord groups, email newsletters, small-scale blogs, and digital gardens. Or make themselves illegible and algorithmically incoherent in public venues.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://maggieappleton.com/ai-dark-forest">Maggie Appleton, "The Expanding Dark Forest and Generative AI"</a></p>

<p>Love the reference to The Dark Forest theory w/r/t space and why we haven't found life yet. I'm wondering a lot recently whether the internet as we know it is about to make a major, major shift. Or, maybe there'll be a small band of indie web believers, and the rest of web-connected humanity will get sucked into the neverending vortex of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7K1KIsHp-P4">content</a>.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Ezra Klein on Attention</title>
            <pubDate>2022-12-23 11:46:14</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/ezra-klein-on-attention.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/ezra-klein-on-attention.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>The cost of so much connection and information has been the deterioration of our capacity for attention and reflection. And it is the quality of our attention and reflection that matters most.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://archive.ph/m3Gkc">"The Great Delusion Behind Twitter"</a></p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Looking to 2023: Presence and Ease</title>
            <pubDate>2022-12-23 09:45:43</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/looking-to-2023-presence-and-ease.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/looking-to-2023-presence-and-ease.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>As I'm looking to 2023 and what I want the next year to be like, two words keep coming to mind: <strong>presence</strong> and <strong>ease</strong>. These two words come into focus, I think, because of how much I struggled with these in my own experience of life over the course of the last year.</p>

<h3>What do I mean by presence?</h3>

<p>When I say I want 2023 to be defined by presence, I mean that I want to be aware of my surroundings. When I am in a moment, I want to be <em>in</em> the moment. I find that my brain is often not with my present experience; it might be dwelling on a past event or anxious about something in the future (which, to be sure, may or may not even happen). When my girls want my attention, I want to really give it to them, and not pretend to give it to them while I think about other things.</p>

<p>Some of this is inspired by Alan Jacobs's post <a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/and-then/">"and then?"</a>. Writing about the recent discussions surrounding LLMs and ChatGPT, in response to writers who are excited to (ahem) <em>not need to write</em>, he says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>My question about all this is: And then? You rush through the writing, the researching, the watching, the listening, you’re done with it, you get it behind you — and what is in front of you? Well, death, for one thing. For the main thing. </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>But in the more immediate future: you’re zipping through all these experiences in order to do what, exactly? Listen to another song at double-speed? Produce a bullet-point outline of another post that AI can finish for you? </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>The whole attitude seems to be: Let me get through this thing I don’t especially enjoy so I can do another thing just like it, which I won’t enjoy either.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>I was going to say "we all seem to be doing this." I write that way a lot, where I label the collective "we" with an ill that only <em>I</em> know that I suffer from. That's not fair. Maybe "we" do suffer from this ill, but that's not for me to say.</p>

<p>I struggle with what Alan Jacobs writes about above -- consistently. I get to work and rush through my work so I don't have to do my work anymore. When I get done with that, I get to lunch and rush through lunch because I want to eat so I can rush back to work. I repeat that cycle till the evening, when I go home, rush through making dinner so I can rush through eating dinner so I can rush through washing dishes and cleaning the house and rush to... sit down on the couch? Perhaps I find some singular moments of pause here and there. But I'm rarely present in (pulling a number out of my ass here) 80-90% of my day. Is that much of my day really not worth being present for? If so, what the hell am I doing?</p>

<p>I can either <em>be here</em> or not be here. I can either be present to my moments or I can rush through my work and my chores and the things I supposedly don't want to do. The truth is, <em>life is all of those things</em>. When I rush through those things, I have a feeling I'll find that I'm going to be old and regret that I didn't enjoy what was happening. Maybe this sounds cliché but it certainly feels like an epiphany, even as I write this.</p>

<p>So. Presence.</p>

<h3>What do I mean by ease?</h3>

<p>Perhaps these words are connected in some way. I think that's probably the case.</p>

<p>When I say I want to live a life of ease, I don't mean with a lack of discomfort, or without doing hard things. I think it's probably true that I want <em>more</em> discomfort and want to make <em>more</em> hard decisions as I grow older. Every time I've had to live with some amount of discomfort and decide to do the hard thing, I have appreciated the ethic it creates in me -- perhaps the character growth I can see in myself over the last decade.</p>

<p>What I mean, I think, is my mindset surrounding my days. We used to do a lot of yoga (though that has taken a bit of a backseat to weightlifting recently) using the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@yogawithadriene">Yoga with Adriene</a> channel on YouTube. "Ease" was an ongoing theme in many, many of her videos. I never paid this much attention, thinking that she was just using certain poses (sukhasana - the easy pose, the pose of ease) and phrases to help her yoga practitioners get into the right mindset for the yoga practice.</p>

<p>But as I come into a new year seeking ease, I think I'm seeing something of what she was trying to do -- that it was deeper than just the practice itself. The goal was to build a practice of ease that rippled into the rest of life. In one of Adriene's videos that focuses on "ease," she says, "The word sukha, although it can translate to 'ease' and can translate to being comfortable, and soft, and happy, the actual root word 'su' and 'kha' to 'good space.'" This is similar to what I'm looking for here when I say "ease."</p>

<p>To my mind, ease is connected to other words, themes, ideas, and experiences. These might be breath, focus, relaxed, calm.</p>

<p>I don't think all moments can be like this, not naturally, anyway. Ease, in this capacity, seems to be a discipline of the mind, one that is built over time. If one struggles with anxiety regularly or even from time to time, ease probably needs to be practiced daily in still, calm moments.</p>

<p>But what I would want from that practice is that it becomes a centering discipline -- one that can be called to mind when my experience pushes me towards anxiety, fear, or anger.</p>

<p>(As a side note/quote: I'm reading <em>Gilead</em> by Marilynne Robinson right now. So far, it's a beautiful novel. She writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>A little too much anger, too often or at the wrong time, can destroy more than you would ever imagine. Above all, mind what you say. 'Behold how much wood is kindled by how small a fire, and the tongue is a fire' -- that's the truth...</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>And later:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Irritation is a form of anger, I recognize that.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>Beautiful thoughts, and haunting too.)</p>

<p>There's a lot to this "ease" business, I realize, as I'm writing this blog post. I put in the quote above from <em>Gilead</em> because I find that I am quite often irritated. Mostly inwardly, although I probably fail to hide it as often as I mean to. And this <em>is</em> connected to the idea of presence, because I find that my irritation sometimes/often comes from the feeling that I am being inconvenienced, that I would rather be doing something else, that I would rather not be where I am right now.</p>

<p>So, in some ways, a lack of presence leads to a lack of ease. </p>

<p>But it comes from other things too: it can come from the occasional feeling that something unexpected came up that I must now deal with. It can come from the feeling that the future is uncertain and I feel trapped or lost in how to handle what might come.</p>

<p>Rather than handle these things with irritation or fear or resentment, I want to take them with ease. To recognize that 1) I have very little control over very few things, and the rest I have no control over at all and 2) life looks and feels more beautiful when I look at <em>the thing</em> head on with acceptance.</p>

<p>So, for 2023, I'm seeking presence and ease. This was a good bit more abstract than I meant it to be. Practically, I anticipate that there will be some practices and disciplines that will need to bolster these themes for me to actually try to pursue them as ideals for my life. But right now, just writing them down is enough.</p>

<p>Presence. Ease.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Best of 2022</title>
            <pubDate>2022-12-22 09:10:28</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2022.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/best-of-2022.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I usually try to wait until very close to the end of the year before I make a "best of" post. I do this because it's quite often that I come across something really good in December (this is my only real issue with Spotify's Wrapped, which I love: it happens at the beginning of December, so it misses a whole month of listening). Anyway, here are my favorite things I watched/listened to/read/did this year. None of the lists are in any particular order</p>

<h2>Music</h2>

<ul>
<li><em>Hell on Church Street</em> - Punch Brothers</li>
<li><em>Illmatic</em> - Nas</li>
<li><em>People's Instinctive Travels and the Paths of Rhythm</em> - A Tribe Called Quest</li>
<li><em>The Low End Theory</em> - A Tribe Called Quest</li>
<li><em>Midnight Marauders</em> - A Tribe Called Quest</li>
<li>"Earfquake" - Tyler, the Creator</li>
<li><em>Mr. Morale and the Big Steppers</em> - Kendrick Lamar</li>
<li>"Lavender Haze" - Taylor Swift (a nice little nod to <em>Mad Men</em> here in the title)</li>
<li><em>All The Truth That I Can Tell</em> - Dashboard Confessional</li>
<li><em>The Score</em> - The Fugees</li>
<li>"Cath.." - Death Cab for Cutie</li>
<li>"Electric Feel" - MGMT</li>
<li>"GET A LIL BAG" - Tobe Nwigwe</li>
<li>Three main genres I got really into this year: 90s/early 00s alt rock, 2000s indie, and 90s hip hop</li>
</ul>

<h2>Movies</h2>

<ul>
<li>Vengeance </li>
<li>The Batman</li>
<li>Nope</li>
</ul>

<h2>TV</h2>

<ul>
<li>Severance</li>
<li>The Bear</li>
<li>White Lotus</li>
<li>Stranger Things</li>
<li>Dave</li>
<li>Better Call Saul Season 5</li>
</ul>

<h2>Books</h2>

<ul>
<li><em>Dune</em> - Frank Herbert</li>
<li><em>Dune Messiah</em> - Frank Herbert</li>
<li>The first three books in <em>The Expanse</em> - James S.A. Corey</li>
<li><em>Go ahead in the Rain</em> - Hanif Abdurraqib</li>
<li><em>Adult Children of Emotionally Immature Parents</em> - Lindsay C. Gibson</li>
<li>As always, I'm reading to the kids every night. Currently about to finish <em>Order of the Phoenix</em> with Lyla.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Podcasts</h2>

<ul>
<li>Ezra Klein's interview with Maryanne Wolf</li>
<li>Dissect's season on <em>Inside</em> by Bo Burnham</li>
<li>Serial's season on <em>The Trojan Horse Affair</em>. Felt a little whodunnit-ish, and was a fun listen.</li>
</ul>

<h2>Everything Else</h2>

<ul>
<li><em>Inside</em> on Switch</li>
<li><em>Axiom Verge</em> on Switch</li>
<li>I've been weightlifting three days a week since August. Started with StrongLifts and recently switched to GZCLP. I feel stronger, healthier, and better than I have in a long time, even with the running I was doing before. I took a break from running because of some hip issues, but I'm excited to see how running and lifting can complement each other when I get to the new year.</li>
<li>I really took the plunge this year on no social meda / self-hosting and getting into indie-web spaces. I'm still trying to figure out what this can look like for me. I really hate being on Twitter, Facebook, and Instagram. I think TikTok is a really awful service that hijacks our brains. I love RSS, the idea of federation, the ideal of an open web.</li>
<li>We visited Schlitterbahn a couple of times. On one of those visits, Paisley and I got to go and hang, just the two of us. That was a blast.</li>
<li>Went to see Mae perform <em>The Everglow</em> in February, and saw Dashboard Confessional in August. Both shows were amazing.</li>
<li><em>We got a dog.</em> Really.</li>
<li>We finally removed all the carpet from our whole house. Long overdue.</li>
<li>I got a pretty bomb ass tattoo. Not quite a half sleeve, but it covers most of my upper right arm. Very pleased, and it's beautiful.</li>
<li>We got to spend a week in South Padre with Elaine's brother and his family. I love the beach more than most things. Also, boogie boarding, good drinks, good food, and a large amount of relaxation.</li>
<li>I'll forever look at 2022 as the year that Elaine (re)discovered her obsession with scratch-off tickets.</li>
<li>My best friend since high school moved to TX in the summer. We have gotten to reconnect a ton, and that's been really amazing.</li>
</ul>

<p>Personally, there were also some really difficult points in the year. I'm still struggling internally with some family issues. To be honest, I think this will require therapy, and that's been a really hard step for me to take.</p>

<p>On top of that, whatever was left of my faith after leaving Life in Deep Ellum in 2021 feels (at worst) completely gone or (at best) entirely dormant. I have a hard time even remembering what it was <em>like</em> to be a person of faith. Prayer feels largely unnatural. I do not have any kind of feel or sense of "God's presence" as I (think) I used to feel it. Largely, my experience of the world feels unaffected by whether I believe that God exists or not, or whether I am a follower of Jesus or not. I don't want to get too deep into this, as I think it warrants another blog post or set of blog posts. It is sufficient to simply say that my faith is not what it once was, and that's not something I feel I can force. I also don't know if I even <em>want</em> to find a way back to that. Maybe someday. Not right now.</p>

<p>A final note: last week, I accepted a job offer at Green Line Digital as a data analyst to go work on a friend's team there. My final day at SAGU will be January 6th. And while one should never say never, I don't anticipate I'll be coming back this time. Fully remote work, a healthy pay bump, better benefits... it's gonna be a good thing for us overall even if the transition takes some getting used to.</p>

<p>Overall, I'm thankful for the year, hard parts included.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Luddite Teens</title>
            <pubDate>2022-12-16 16:23:40</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/luddite-teens.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/luddite-teens.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Eventually, too burned out to scroll past yet one more picture-perfect Instagram selfie, she deleted the app.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>“But that wasn’t enough,” she said. “So I put my phone in a box.”</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>For the first time, she experienced life in the city as a teenager without an iPhone. She borrowed novels from the library and read them alone in the park. She started admiring graffiti when she rode the subway, then fell in with some teens who taught her how to spray-paint in a freight train yard in Queens. And she began waking up without an alarm clock at 7 a.m., no longer falling asleep to the glow of her phone at midnight. Once, as she later wrote in a text titled the “Luddite Manifesto,” she fantasized about tossing her iPhone into the Gowanus Canal.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://archive.ph/WeNjj">"‘Luddite’ Teens Don’t Want Your Likes"</a></p>

<p>Maybe we'll make it out of this thing ok. But it will take time.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>