<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>EST - A new tag for a new personal focus</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-19 10:30:50</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/est-a-new-tag-for-a-new-personal-focus.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/est-a-new-tag-for-a-new-personal-focus.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I am creating a new tag as of today -- <a href="https://cbaca.blog/tags/EST.html">EST</a>. This will stand for exiistentialism, secularism, and technology. All three of these subjects have interested me at different times in the last, I don't know, 8 years or so? But I have generally been interested in them as somewhat separate subjects. <strong>Existentialism</strong> was a big focus for me in the latter portion of my graduate degree, especially Kierkegaard's existential, theological epistemology during my thesis. During that time, I also discovered Charles Taylor via James K.A. Smith, and his work <em>A Secular Age</em>, which I have only partially read but find useful a way to think about modernity, <strong>secularism</strong>, and what has brought about the current shape of religious thought. Also around this same time, I discovered Neil Postman as a cultural <strong>technology</strong> critic, and found his model for thinking about our cultural uses of technology (and the ways in which those technologies <em>use us</em>) as insightful.</p>

<p>The more I think about this, the more I believe these are, or can be, interconnected modules of thought. They overlap in interesting ways. Technology affects our mode of being and acting in the world more than ever before, Secularism (Taylor's version, anyway) can be seen partially as deeply intertwined with the technological progress of the last 200 years. And I think it somewhat goes without saying how secularism and existentialism are affected by one another.</p>

<p>I imagine that I will want to think of EST as more of a long-term personal idea project, and less as a year long personal project that I will somehow summit by the end of 2024. Alan Jacobs mentioned recently (somewhere on his blog) that technopoly (a Neil Postman term to describe our cultural habits w/r/t technology) was a decade-long research interest of his.</p>

<p>But, what better place to store thoughts, links, ideas, books, and whatever else I find related to this subject than my blog? I thought about placing them in Evernote or Notion or some other tool, but I don't think those will be as resilient as my site, since this already has a structure in place, and whether or not it stays online, I will always have the Markdown and HTML files to refer back to in a structured form.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Richard Beck on Existential Theology and Its Current Benefits</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-18 10:32:48</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/richard-beck-on-existential-theology-and-its-current-benefits.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/richard-beck-on-existential-theology-and-its-current-benefits.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>...existential theology has done a good job of mapping the existential and experiential terrain of human experience as it relates to God. Again, existentialism points to our Augustinian restlessness. You can't live without God and not have that impact you in some existential way. We have a natural desire for a supernatural end, and that desire will always be left existentially unfulfilled until it finds rest in God. Existential theology does a great job at describing and evoking both this desire and its lack of fulfillment. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>--Richard Beck, <a href="https://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2024/01/reclaiming-existential-theology-part-5.html">"Reclaiming Existential Theology: Part 5, More Than Swallowing Horse Pills"</a></p>

<p>This is something I think I've not fully been able to articulte in the past, especially w/r/t my ongoing facscination with existentialism and in particularl Kierkegaard.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Kierkegaard's epistemological work enthralled me (and continues to) because I think he maps out a condition that <em>still</em> matters, even in 21st century modernity. Kierkegaard, I think, is a theologian first and foremost (earlier works notwithstanding). His main life's work was later in his writing, and being faithful under modern epistemological conditions was a constant source of tension for him, IMO. The "ache" or something similar to Charles Taylor's term regarding "fullness" in a secular age brings about the <em>need</em> for existential theology -- otherwise, we're perhaps speaking a disingenuous language.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Adding Webmentions Walkthrough (link)</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-16 13:39:51</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/adding-webmentions-walkthrough-link.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/adding-webmentions-walkthrough-link.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>For future me:</p>

<p><a href="https://janmonschke.com/adding-webmentions-to-your-static-blog/">"Adding webmentions to your static blog"</a></p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Mary Harrington on 'Cringemaxxing'</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-13 09:56:31</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mary-harrington-on-cringemaxxing.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mary-harrington-on-cringemaxxing.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>But the absolute opposite of “cool” is not “uncool” but “cringe”: the wincing, jaw-clenching feeling you get when you do, or witness, something that you know the cool people would regard not just as uncool, but actively anti-cool: embarrassing, awkward, social Kryptonite. And while babies merely uncool, probably the most cringe thing you can do is going to church. There, you show up regularly to join a group of others you didn’t choose, and some of whom are probably old, or weird, or awkward, or otherwise uncool. The purpose of showing up is prayer: again, the opposite of cool, because to pray is to declare, openly, that you are not completely self-contained.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://reactionaryfeminist.substack.com/p/you-need-to-be-cringemaxxing">"You Need to be Cringemaxxing"</a></p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Blogs and Websites, Gaining Traction</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-11 09:32:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/blogs-and-websites-gaining-traction.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/blogs-and-websites-gaining-traction.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Some links on the state of personal websites and blogging:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many people are now desperately waiting for their Twitter archives, hoping that they’ll arrive before all their content is lost for good. For those who were using Twitter primarily for ephemeral chatter, all this isn’t that tragic. But for others, all their posts, conversations, and connections on the social network were a significant part of their online identity. They are about to lose a place on the Web into which they put a huge amount of time, attention, and energy...</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>So how about we make 2023 the year of the personal website? The year in which we launch our first site or redesign our old one, publish a little more often, and add RSS and Webmentions to our websites so that we can write posts back and forth. The year we make our sites more fussy, more quirky, and more personal. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://matthiasott.com/notes/the-year-of-the-personal-website">"The Year of the Personal Website"</a></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In those days, it was really simple. You could sign up for a free site on GeoCities, Yahoo, Blogger, Diaryland, or any of a number of free hosting sites that allowed you to set up your blog, get going with a WYSIWYG editor, and send your thoughts out into the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>For those who were a little more adventurous, you could purchase an actual domain name, pay for website hosting, and go for it that way...</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Bring back personal blogging in 2023. We, as a web community, will be all that much better for it. </p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://www.theverge.com/23513418/bring-back-personal-blogging">"Bring back personal blogging"</a></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The real web is built on links. Hyper ones, in fact. Links you can share on your website. Links you can send to your mates. Links to pages that can be indexed by search engines so you can find things again (in theory)...</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>The real web, the small web, the indie web is amazing. Don't give Facebook and the rest of these clowns your content. Don't give them the time or your attention. Get a blog, a website, a Mastodon account, something you control, and share links to cool things you find.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>--<a href="https://rknight.me/blog/the-web-is-fantastic/">The Web is Fantastic</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>My only quibble (and I believe I've noted this before) is that personal blogging / having a personal website needs to be <em>easy</em> for regular people. If we're going to really push this personal web thing again, blogging shouldn't be inaccessible to people that aren't bent towards wanting to mess around with markup and code. I happen to like that stuff, so building this was fine for me. But there are other people with other thoughts that should find it ultra-easy, even frictionless, to build a site and a blog. To that end, here is a list of resources for doing so from Robb Knight:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://micro.blog/">Micro.blog</a> - $5 a month, has cross-posting to a whole load of places
  <a href="https://www.wordpress.com">Wordpress.com</a> - Free
  <a href="https://home.omg.lol/referred-by/robb">weblog.lol via omg.lol</a> - $20 a year also includes a &gt;Mastodon server, pastebin, profile page, now page, and some other cool things
  <a href="https://bearblog.dev/">Bear</a> - free
  <a href="https://neocities.org/">Neocities</a> - free
  <a href="https://pika.page/">Pika</a> - free
  <a href="https://www.11ty.dev/">Eleventy</a> if you want to dig into code and run your own thing.</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>