<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Feeling Alienated</title>
            <pubDate>2024-07-16 14:11:04</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feeling-alienated.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feeling-alienated.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>It's a strange thing, to go away for a weekend and enjoy yourself, but to come back feeling... deflated isn't the right word. It's somewhat akin to the Sunday scaries that plague many of us in our modern work-lives. But it's not necessarily related to work <em>itself</em>. The more I've thought about the feeling I'm coming away with after a long weekend visiting friends in Kansas City is alienation.</p>

<p>And I think what's really happening is that I was already feeling this -- it's just that being with these friends brought that feeling to the surface. We didn't do too much, but these friends of ours are the camping/outdoorsy type of folks, have a pretty fruitful garden, and generally hold values about nature that Elaine and I also hold. The difference is that we have struggled to live out those values in the same way that they do. On Saturday, we spent most of the day at Clinton Lake out in Lawrence, KS. It was a pretty special day but nothing spectacular; we took the boat out, swam, tubed, swam some more. </p>

<p>On Sunday we just hung out and chatted and used some fresh veggies from the garden for lunch and dinner. And on Monday we left. It wasn't like it was some epiphany that I had. But the whole weekend, I felt like some part of my soul that's been buried was becoming uncovered. Some piece of myself that I didn't quite forget about but was becoming forgotten. I just love being outside. I feel better when I am in the sun, among water and plants and there is just a tiny bit of unknown in the experience, some piece that I have no control over.</p>

<p>I think I simply realized that I spend so much of my time in comfort because it's so easy to craft and control what you encounter when you work in front of a screen, live in constant AC, and spend weekends just vegging because you're mentally tired from a week of all of the normal wearing down of life.</p>

<p>This feels a little rambly. And I know I'm not the first person in the world to explore human alienation from nature -- it's been a problem we've been thinking about since at least early modernity.</p>

<p>Mostly I just want to write this down so I can remember, and perhaps remind myself down the road. I want to encounter nature more, to be outside, to grow my own food sometimes, to make trips to the mountains and rivers and woods and remember that I am small.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Largely Shielded</title>
            <pubDate>2024-06-28 08:31:56</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/largely-shielded.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/largely-shielded.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Due to my insistence on avoiding social media (except for you Reddit, which, as a side note, I continue to return to like cigarette addict to his vape pen), I've been largely shielded from <em>~the discourse~</em>.</p>

<p>Instead, I have chosen to focus on other things. In the physical world, that's been my work, my family, my home, my health. Those things have proven far worthier of my attention than whatever bullshit is in the waterfalls of opinion online.</p>

<p>Digitally too, though. RSS and podcasts are the majority of my digital diet (and even then, not much on the podcast side). I listened to Ezra Klein talk on someone else's podcast about the debate last night, which is the extent of what I'll listen to on this topic. I have an opinion (or several) on the election and the candidates and what should happen.</p>

<p>But, you know, at the end of the day, even digitally I have other more important things to focus on. I like my blog and I want to maintain it. I am currently in the middle of part I of Nand2Tetris (This week is part 4 -- the Hack computer language. The last three weeks I've spent building logic gates, an ALU, and RAM... digitally of course), and I am actually really enjoying learning computer science from first principles onward. I think I'll have another post forthcoming on this, but I have been thinking a lot about what computers are, what digital information is, and because of those things, what we <strong>should</strong> use computers for. They are good for some things and not others, and that ultimately comes down to what we want to be and focus on as human beings.</p>

<p>Rabbit trailing a little bit. Suffice it to say, I think this week has shown me that digitally I have taken the right steps, and I want to keep moving in that direction.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Maybe There Are Two Internets</title>
            <pubDate>2024-05-03 12:47:56</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/maybe-there-are-two-internets.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/maybe-there-are-two-internets.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I don't write about it much here, but I work in digital marketing in my day job. Because of this, I consistently experience a bit of cognitive dissonance. On the one hand, I love the idea of the web as an open, democratic place. One where privacy reigns supreme, where you can stumble upon some really amazing stuff on any given day, where you can find people you never would have found before that share your same interests, and chiefly, where corporations decidedly <em>do not</em> have control over your digital assets.</p>

<p>It's the reason I even have a self-hosted blog in the first place. It's why I'm not (really) on social media.</p>

<p>But -- and maybe, probably this is a little bit of self-justification -- maybe it's best to think about the internet as somewhat multifaceted. Maybe it doesn't only need to be the social, open web (though I want more and more of that). The truth is, the fact that portions of the internet are commodified, open to advertising, and that people give away a little bit of their privacy so they can find the products and services they want is not the worst thing. Partially because it provides my own livelihood, of course. But also because the digital economy has lifted a ton of folks up -- people who perhaps otherwise would never have had a voice or been able to build their own business. (Elaine's photography is a good example of this).</p>

<p>I'm starting to think that it may be helpful to think of the internet as somewhat split. There's the commodified side. Which, sure, can be a little icky sometimes. You have to give away a bit of yourself to participate. But there are also ways around this if you really care about privacy.</p>

<p>Then there's the open, non-analytics side. There are anonymous and non-anonymous blogs and sites where you can still stumble across things without worrying about your feeds and how much you linger on something being tracked. Two different spaces, two different purposes.</p>

<p>Maybe it's just a little more complex than the idealism of a one-size-fits-all approach.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Further Down the Road towards a Less Human Web</title>
            <pubDate>2024-02-05 10:46:29</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/further-down-the-road-towards-a-less-human-web.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/further-down-the-road-towards-a-less-human-web.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>I guess what I’m saying is: thanks, I hate it. Give me context; give me nuance; give me the ability to think for myself. We built the world’s most incredible communication and knowledge-sharing medium, rich with diverse perspectives and alternative ideas; let’s not sanitize it through a banal filter that is designed to strip it of its humanity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>--Ben Werdmuller, <a href="https://werd.io/2024/stripping-the-web-of-its-humanity">"Stripping the web of its humanity"</a></p>

<p>Not long ago at work, I made a passing comment to my teammates that the internet was humanity's best idea, but that we have been actively mucking it up for the last two decades or so. That was a bit of an overstatement on my part (after all, humanity did just fine without the web for thousands of years). But I do think the web, at its core, is still a great <em>idea</em>. As a tool, it enables knowledge sharing, especially for those who would historically have been less privileged; it bolsters the global economy and has helped us to grow in ways we could only dream of a century ago; it allows for an openness to the experience of others outside our immediate communities.</p>

<p>So, humanity's <em>best</em> idea? Probably not, but I still think it's up there in terms of <em>potential</em>.</p>

<p>My concern, however, is that we genuinely are mucking it up, and two new forms of technology -- one software, one hardware -- were released last week that only serve to confirm my feelings. </p>

<p><strong>The first is <a href="https://arc.net/blog/arc-search">Arc Search</a>.</strong> Arc is a new-ish internet browser company that really is doing new and interesting things for browsing the web. I haven't incorporated the Arc browser into my life much because my work life revolves so much around Chrome. But when I use Arc I find it pretty interesting and fun.</p>

<p>The idea behind Arc Search, however, is disappointing. Arc says of Arc Search:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Browses for you.</strong> For any search, tapping Browse for Me will scour the web, read multiple pages, and build you the perfect tab - already a fan favorite.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I can't even read those words without feeling bummed. In my mind, that's not what the web or search on the web is <em>for</em>. This is inevitable given the incorporation of LLMs in other search engines. But I don't <em>want</em> a search for something to result in a machine browsing for me and creating a bespoke web page for me that reduces the possible pages I might come across into a single, condensed page. The fun of surfing in the early aughts was stumbling upon things that you weren't necessarily looking for. And this whole concept of AI search not only relegates the fun part of search to a machine, you also don't get to <em>choose</em> where that condensed information is even coming from. It's chosen for you, and it's not even curated by a human being!</p>

<p><strong>The second is the new Apple Vision Pro.</strong> I'm not a reviewer of this product. I haven't touched one in person. I have seen several videos, watched the keynote, seen the product's capabilities, etc. Listen, it looks like a very interesting technological leap forward. Or as Marques Brownlee puts it in his video, it's tomorrow's technology with today's hardware. And honestly, this is the technology that Marvel (Tony Stark) and Minority report somewhat predicted in the last two decades.</p>

<p>But watching and reading reviews, where the people using the Vision Pro are immersed in a digital world is also, well, a bummer. Many folks are predicting that the headset will continue to get smaller and smaller over the next decade so as to be more discrete. The fact that this model is a "Pro" implies a non-pro, less expensive option is in the works. So it will be more widely available in the near future.</p>

<p>But practically, what does this mean? Well, we know what it means, because we already have a model from smartphones on how we progress in our use of it. First it will be sparse, then more and more folks will use it until it's ubiquitous -- a "necessity" for work, then we won't be able to imagine entertainment without it either. </p>

<p>But at the end of this, we'll see that our interactions with this technology remove or degrade social bonds, because the underlying premise is that I am immersing <em>myself</em> in this digital world, separate from my family and friends and the people around me. I am in some sense escaping (or at least augmenting) actual, objective reality because actual, objective reality is no longer enough.</p>

<p>I don't want to be a doomer about all this. My career currently requires a lively internet, and probably will flourish under this new technological landscape if I stick to digital marketing.</p>

<p>But damn if it isn't sad. These were the two top stories last week. AI has been on our societal brain for the last couple of years. We knew Apple was working on this for a while, and it came out and there is tons of hype.</p>

<p>And all I can see is a bleaker, less human web.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Emergence from Modularity - Quote</title>
            <pubDate>2024-01-19 11:07:11</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/emergence-from-modularity-quote.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/emergence-from-modularity-quote.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <p>The prevalence of modularity in computer design, and of "emergent" strategies and techniques in software design, makes my dreams of Morlockian power seem absurdly far-fetched. If the people who design and build the microchips, construct the hardware, and write the software codes don't understand how exactly the whole thing manages to work—or, as is often the case, why it doesn't—then shouldn't I just become the most skillful computer user I can (a "power user," as the lingo has it) and forget about tinkering under the hood? After all, Johnson argues that, as self-organizing systems become more technologically dominant—a development he thinks is inevitable, especially in computer software—the ability to "accommodate uncertainty" (as Baldwin and Clark put it), to accept one's lack of control over the outcome of a given process, will become a cardinal virtue.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>--Alan Jacobs, <a href="https://www.booksandculture.com/articles/2002/mayjun/10.16.html">"Computer Control (Who's In Charge?)"</a></p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>