<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Robin Sloan on New Ideas</title>
            <pubDate>12/07/2022 11:02:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/robin-sloan-on-new-ideas.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/robin-sloan-on-new-ideas.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>All along, from the frothy 1990s to the percolating 2000s to the frozen 2010s to today, the web has been the sure thing. All along, it’s been growing and maturing, sprouting new capabilities. From my vantage point, that growth has seemed to accelerate in the past five years...</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>For people who care about creating worlds together, rather than getting rich, the web is the past and the web is the future. What luck, that this decentralized, permissionless system claimed a position at the heart of the internet, and stuck there. It’s limited, of course; frustrating; sometimes maddening. But that’s every creative medium. That’s life.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://www.robinsloan.com/lab/new-avenues/">"A Year of New Avenues"</a> - Robin Sloan</p>

<p>And also:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Back in the 2000s, a lot of blogs were about blogs, about blogging. If that sounds exhaustingly meta, well, yes — but it was also SUPER generative. When the thing can describe itself, when it provides the best place to talk about itself, I am telling you, some internal flywheel gets spinning, and powerful things start to happen.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>I expressed frustration about this a couple of weeks ago (i.e., wanting to see more blogs that weren't <em>about blogs</em> but blogs about other things... homesteading or anthropology or design or whatever). But maybe Robin has a point here... the meta-ness of blogging about blogging is generative.</p>

<p>As a side note, this is sending me down another hole. Three things I've been rolling around in my head:</p>

<ol>
<li>I like e-ink, but damn do the companies that produce these products not make it easy to develop for their readers. Especially Kindle. I'm an avid Paperwhite user, but I have essentially <em>zero</em> ability to make anything for the Kindle. (I had an idea this morning for building an RSS service that automatically sends to Kindle... worth exploring).</li>
<li>This site is served on a VPS with a Digital Ocean droplet. But of course, that sent me down the rabbit hole of <a href="https://homebrewserver.club/">homebrewed servers</a>. So I'm thinking about getting a Raspberry Pi or something, hooking it up to a small portable hard drive and setting up my own little server at home. </li>
<li>Found this via RSS this morning: Ryan Cordell is a professor that teaches about digital humanities. <a href="https://ryancordell.org/teaching/">His teaching page is here</a>. Somewhere along the way, I guess he mentioned that he's moving all of his course stuff to Canvas (his school's LMS), but before that, he was building personal sites that contained his course material... which I LOVE. I get why you wouldn't do this (school policy, requiring students to use another platform, etc.), but the <em>feel</em> of independence and playfulness here is really fun. That's not even the point I'm trying to make though. I have also been thinking about what it means to teach digital literacy to middle and high schoolers. Everything from learning very basic coding, owning your own domain, how the web works, and how to identify and interact with good and bad information. Almost a "philosophy of the web" course/s informed by indie web stuff and Neil Postman.</li>
</ol>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Currently Listening/Reading: A Tribe Called Quest</title>
            <pubDate>12/07/2022 09:41:14</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/currently-listening-reading-a-tribe-called-quest.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/currently-listening-reading-a-tribe-called-quest.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h3>Currently listening: <em>Low End Theory</em> - A Tribe Called Quest</h3>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/1p12OAWwudgMqfMzjMvl2a?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="380" frameBorder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3>Currently reading: <em>Go Ahead in the Rain: Notes to A Tribe Called Quest</em> - Hanif Abdurraqib</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Go-Ahead-Rain-Called-American/dp/1477316485/ref=sr_1_1?keywords=go+ahead+in+the+rain&amp;qid=1670427939&amp;sr=8-1"><img src="https://m.media-amazon.com/images/I/51EhJ5WCYdL._AC_SY780_.jpg"></img></a></p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>John Scalzi on the Artisan Web</title>
            <pubDate>11/29/2022 15:42:52</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/john-scalzi-on-the-artisan-web.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/john-scalzi-on-the-artisan-web.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Now, why should we bring back that artisan, hand-crafted Web? Oh, I don’t know. Wouldn’t it be nice to have a site that’s not run by an amoral billionaire chaos engine, or algorithmically designed to keep you doomscrolling in a state of fear and anger, or is essentially spyware for governments and/or corporations? Wouldn’t it be nice not to have ads shoved in your face every time you open an app to see what your friends are up to? Wouldn’t it be nice to know that when your friends post something, you’ll actually see it without a social media platform deciding whether to shove it down your feed and pump that feed full of stuff you didn’t ask for?</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://whatever.scalzi.com/2022/11/25/how-to-weave-the-artisan-web/">John Scalzi: "How to Weave the Artisan Web"</a></p>

<p>I know I keep tooting this horn but... dang it, it's true!</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Mastodon No More</title>
            <pubDate>11/29/2022 09:23:42</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mastodon-no-more.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/mastodon-no-more.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I decided yesterday that Mastodon wasn't a good fit for me and deleted my account at IndieWeb.Social. The premise, I think, was promising. Federated groupings, servers run by real people and not a single corporation, better rules of engagement, etc. But it didn't take long before I was seeing the same sorts of undesirable behavior on my instance that I was seeing on Twitter that made me get off in the first place.</p>

<p>Perhaps it will be a balm for those whose online lives revolve around Twitter. It's just not what I want the internet to be. More and more, I want the internet to be a little more homebrewed, a little less corporate. At least, that's the internet <em>I</em> want to interact with. </p>

<p>I'm still interested in giving micro.blog a go, but there are some technical challenges with building a feed on this website since it's static, and then hooking it up with ActivityPub. I need to do some more reading and digging at the micro.blog forums to see what that will entail. And then the question really is, why do I want the micro-format in the first place? Onen of the other things that bugged me about Twitter a long time ago was that I felt myself "thinking in Tweets" rather than thinking in broader strokes and trying to piece things together. The micro format <em>itself</em> encourages short-form thinking, which is not what I want to find myself doing regularly.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>God is (in) the Details</title>
            <pubDate>11/28/2022 16:19:21</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/god-is-in-the-details.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/god-is-in-the-details.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I don't have much to say, except that I listened to two podcasts this week:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.premierguitar.com/podcast/wong-notes/chris-thile-cory-wong-interview">Wong Notes - "Chris Thile's Exercise in Joy"</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.singforscience.org/episodes/rivers-cuomo-guido-van-rossum">Sing for Science - "Rivers Cuomo and Guido van Rossum"</a></li>
</ol>

<p>In both episodes, the interviewees said the phrase "God is in the details" -- in the former, Thile then corrects himself, and says "God <em>is</em> the details."</p>

<p>I find myself thinking and not thinking about God and religion much these days. "God" permeates my work and the culture that surrounds me, and yet, since leaving LIDE, I find myself wanting very little to do with <em>formal</em> and <em>institutional</em> versions of spirituality. (I recognize this is awfully millennial of me)</p>

<p>On the other hand, I cannot deny the draw of spirituality on some deep level within me. There has always, always been a sense of beauty, of love, of transcendence in life. The very existence of these feelings seem to me to be pointers to a deeper reality that I cannot quite grasp. A reality that fades from my vision when I try to look to closely, like a dream that I try to remember just after waking.</p>

<p>Mostly, it's in the details that I have these feelings. The feel of Elaine's hand on my back, the feel of my daughters' hair when I kiss them goodnight on the top of the head, the cold wind in the morning when I'm out walking, the gratitude I feel when surrounded by close friends and family.</p>

<p>Perhaps God is in the details after all, and that is all that we can say about it.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>