<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>A Quote On 'Seeing'</title>
            <pubDate>2024-12-12 11:41:29</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/a-quote-on-seeing.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/a-quote-on-seeing.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>A long quote incoming:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>And where do the symbols come from? From the years of childhood drawing during which every person develops a system of symbols. The symbol system becomes embedded in the memory, and the symbols are ready to be called out, just as you called them out to draw your childhood landscape.</p>
    
    <p>...</p>
    
    <p>To sum up, adult students beginning in art generally do not really see what is in front of their eyes -- That is, they do not perceive in the special way required for drawing. They take note of what's there, and quickly translate the perception into words and symbols mainly based on the symbol system developed throughout childhood and on what they know about the perceived object.</p>
    
    <p>What is the solution to this dilemma? Psychologist Robert Ornstein suggests that in order to draw, the artist must 'mirror' things or perceive them exactly as they are. Thus, you must set aside your usual verbal categorizing and turn your full visual attention to what you are perceiving -- to all of its details and how each detail fits into the whole configuration. In short, you must see the way an artist sees.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--Betty Edwards, <em>The New Drawing on the Right Side of the Brain</em>, p. 82</p>

<p>Edwards is obviously talking about pragmatic "how" of drawing here, but I found this quote remarkably in line with philosophical inquiry regarding seeing the world "as it is" and how our pre-built categories affect what it is we perceive when we look at the world.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 7 - 2 to 15 Nov 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-11-18 10:02:41</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-7-2-to-15-nov-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-7-2-to-15-nov-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>Duck hunting was such a blast! It's been about a week now since I went, but man I had such a good time. We did an evening hunt that was really just more of a practice run for the morning (no ducks were killed, only shot at). But it was a good chance to get a feel for the rhythm of things, what to expect, and so on. In the morning, we arrived at the hunting location at about 5 AM, walked in with our layout blinds, got all set up and brushed in, and waited for shooting light. The stars were truly magnificent -- light pollution is pretty bad where I am so it was wonderful to see (and remember) what the stars really look like. I walked away with three birds from the hunt, and I was the first to kill one that day, so it was a special experience for sure. Now I'm trying to figure out how to get back out where I'm at. The closest location is Lake Bardwell, which is not difficult to get to.</p>

<p>Other than that, things have just seemed to be transitioning with the season, I think. My training cycle is nearly complete (the Dino Valley 25K is this Saturday), so I moved into my training taper period last week. I'm excited and nervous, but mostly excited I think!</p>

<p>The days blur together somewhat from the last two weeks -- there has just been a lot of that "everyday busy-ness" thing going on. Cassandra was here for about 5 days, which was great. </p>

<p>P's 11th birthday is TODAY! 11 years with that kiddo, and it has been a ride, let me tell you. I find myself thankful for her, though, more and more. We went rock climbing yesterday to celebrate and she did a lot of fear-conquering, which was really neat to see.</p>

<p>I'm currently reading Barbara Kingsolver's <em>Demon Copperhead</em>, which is sad and a bit tragic but with which I feel a strange familiarity. I did not grow up an orphan, but the setting of southern poverty gives it a sense of reality to me.</p>

<p>Personally, I'm trying and trying to stay away from general media, news, and feeds as much as possible. A habit this sticky is hard to break, though. Chrome is often deleted from my phone but I re-download it for practical reasons, and then that often leads to checking out Reddit or something else for a few minutes, so I haven't been fully disconnected. The goal is to continue to figure this out, however, because the moments when I'm not actively engaged with media and feeds are much calmer. My blog and the RSS reader are a much different story -- this continues to be a place where I want to be. It's the kind of web I want.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Unforunately, I think the Prius's power brakes are going out. A strange noise occurs when pushing down the brakes at a full stop, and the Prius forums indicate that this is a known issue on my Prius version. It usually results in a hefty repair bill, which will likely cost more than the car is worth. The long story short is, we need to take it into the dealer.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I don't want to say "nothing" here but... nothing I can think of, at least.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>On Losing an Election</title>
            <pubDate>2024-11-06 08:05:21</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/on-losing-an-election.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/on-losing-an-election.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Talking with Elaine this morning after seeing the results, I had a (re-)realization that my daily life and my internet media consumption are in such strong contrast. I live in MAGA country (always have, basically, at least here in Texas). I'm surrounded by committed Republican voters who generally assume that everyone around them votes the same as they do.</p>

<p>But my internet consumption is clearly, <em>clearly</em> left of that. By a wide margin. Despite the fact that I live in MAGA-world, I really thought there was a good shot at a Democrat win across the board. (That is clearly <em>not</em> what happened.)</p>

<p>Two things are on my mind this morning in response to this. Of course I have some political opinions and have some generalized anxiety about how the next four year presidential term will play out. But even more than that:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>It's become increasingly clear (and stark after this morning) that my current media consumption habits are simply not serving me. Scrolling through Reddit feeds a few times a day, checking NYT and NPR, etc. are simply not giving me an accurate view of reality. They are also not helping my mental state... probably at all. I'm going to make it a goal over the coming weeks to devise a plan to change these habits for myself. I want to be a kind person, a good citizen, a loving husband and father, and a thoughtful, <em>well-informed</em> human being.</p></li>
<li><p>Richard Beck has been in my RSS feed for years. While I don't read everything he writes, there are occasions where he writes something that genuinely hits home and makes me feel sane. <a href="https://experimentaltheology.blogspot.com/2024/11/planting-gardens-in-babylon-on-how-to.html">This, from a sermon he wrote years ago</a>, titled "How to Lose an Election," is a gentle reminder that human history is peppered with situations where they lack political power (long quote incoming):</p></li>
</ol>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>In my Bushnell talk, one of the points I made comes from Jeremiah 29. Some of the Israelites have returned home from their Babylonian exile. But many remain behind in Babylon. These write to the prophet Jeremiah asking if they should come home. But Jeremiah writes back to say, no, you should stay in Babylon. And not just stay, to multiply and thrive:</p>
    
    <p>Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, to all the exiles whom I have sent into exile from Jerusalem to Babylon: Build houses and live in them; plant gardens and eat what they produce. Take wives and have sons and daughters; take wives for your sons, and give your daughters in marriage, that they may bear sons and daughters; multiply there, and do not decrease. But seek the welfare of the city where I have sent you into exile, and pray to the Lord on its behalf, for in its welfare you will find your welfare. </p>
    
    <p>Seek the welfare of the city, for it its welfare you will find your welfare. Crucially, the Israelites remain in Babylon as a marginalized, disenfranchised, exilic people. They do not control Babylon, nor will they ever control Babylon. Political power is not in their hands. And yet, there is work to do! Seek the welfare of the city.</p>
    
    <p>And let's be clear on this point, this is Babylon we are talking about. Babylon, the epitome of wickedness, oppression, injustice, violence, and evil in Biblical history and imagination. The point here is that the People of God thrive in places of political marginalization. The People of God thrive in Babylon. So there's no excuse for us not to thrive, even if we lost the election. No matter the outcome today, there is good, creative, generative, and beautiful work to do.</p>
    
    <p>How do you lose an election? It's simple.</p>
    
    <p>You plant gardens in Babylon.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>So how am I planting a garden? Well,  I'll probably literally plant a garden, but I'm raising my kiddos a certain way, I'm disengaging from the shit show that is national politics, and I'm looking to the community around me to build a life together.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 6 - 26 Oct to 1 Nov 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-11-01 15:50:34</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-6-26-oct-to-1-nov-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-6-26-oct-to-1-nov-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>The big thing this week has been prepping for my first duck hunt (🦆)! I went last year with Zack right after Thanksgiving, but didn't have a license so I was just a bystander. We didn't bag anything last year either, so I'm hoping this is a good little trip for me. I'm SO excited, this is an experience out of my norm. I finished up my hunter's education, got my license, and set up my shotgun/accessories situation.</p>

<p>Halloween was also a fun time! I dressed as Miguel from Coco, and the girls were traditional skeletons from Dia de los Muertos. Lots of folks from the girls' school came over and we ate, passed out candy, and the girls were able to go trick or treating with their friends.</p>

<p>I'm getting reallllll close to the race (I think I'm right at 3 weeks out). My legs are a bit tired and I'm definitely feeling worn down some from training. But overall I think I am ready for the race -- my goal is still to place in the top 3 overall, but I'll be happy with a good race no matter what.</p>

<p>I took the step of deleting internet browser access from my phone, just to mitigate access to stupid feeds and news or whatever. It hasn't fully removed my proclivity for doomscrolling, but it's definitely better than it was, and my mood is anecdotally better as well.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Got the grass mowed last weekend, and that should be the last big mow for the season, thank goodness.</p>

<p>Just wanting to get through this next week mostly -- should be quick as I'm taking Thursday and Friday off, and we're hunting next Monday.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>Just bingeing <a href="https://www.themeateater.com/shows/duck-camp-dinners">Duck Camp Dinners</a>, Jean-Paul Bourgeois is the man, and it's just hyping me up for hunting season.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Weeknote 5 - 19 to 25 Oct 2024</title>
            <pubDate>2024-10-25 12:57:17</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-5-19-to-25-oct-2024.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/weeknote-5-19-to-25-oct-2024.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>What have I been doing?</h2>

<p>Personally, not much activity happening, which is to say: this was basically a routine sort of week. That's not a bad thing, but I can't think of much that was "of note." </p>

<p>I'm entering the final phase of training, which means I hit another 12 miler last Saturday, and will move into my final two long runs before my taper for the Dino Valley 25K.</p>

<p>I started reading <a href="https://www.amazon.com/When-We-Cease-Understand-World/dp/1681375664"><em>When We Cease to Understand the World</em></a> by Benjamin Labatut. I was reading <em>Persepolis Rising</em>, the 7th book in The Expanse saga, but I'm either just not ready for the book or I'm bored with the characters. In theory, a long, sprawling epic story is interesting and consuming. In practice (maybe it's just these authors), this is along time to spend with these characters, and I'm finding the writing style a bit... mediocre?</p>

<p>I did receive some new woodworking tools in this week! I think this completes the "basic collection" that I need to be able to <em>actually</em> start making things. This week's haul included a block plane, a shoulder plane, a coping saw, and some more measuring/marking tools. My first goal is to build <a href="https://www.freeonlinewoodworkingschool.com/bookstand">this book stand</a>, and perhaps a dovetail box after that. We'll see where it takes me! I do think project-based work, even if I'm bad at it, is going to be the best way forward here to gain the skills I'm currently lacking.</p>

<p>Work was work-y. Nothing to see here.</p>

<p>P is doing really great. I'm seeing so much growth in her over the last couple of months. I think Elaine and I are both feeling a little reticent to "look at it straight on" in fear of things returning to how they used to be. We had years of tough, and months of REALLY tough. But there are signs from her that things are genuinely looking up and hopeful.</p>

<p>Lyla and I watched Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows part 1 last night. We finished the entire book series months and months ago, and have slowly eked our way through the movies.</p>

<h2>What do I need to take care of?</h2>

<p>Same as last week.</p>

<h2>What caught my interest?</h2>

<p>I learned today about a music genre called "shoegaze," which seems to be described best by listening to "Mayonaise" by Smashing Pumpkins. I've been looking for a genre that encapsulates the feel of that song for a long time, so this'll be  a fun rabbit hole (<a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/37i9dQZF1DX6ujZpAN0v9r?si=2be64f8294614e0b">Spotify playlist to match</a>).</p>

<p>Lots of stuff I'm running into re: avoiding news consumption and online feeds. Wherever this is coming from... I should probably listen. We're less than two weeks out from the election, and the truth is I've been feeling the need to step back from even Reddit/NYT consumption, which are the last vestiges of daily news/daily feeds in my routine. </p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>