<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Luddite Teens</title>
            <pubDate>12/16/2022 16:40:23</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/luddite-teens.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/luddite-teens.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Eventually, too burned out to scroll past yet one more picture-perfect Instagram selfie, she deleted the app.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>“But that wasn’t enough,” she said. “So I put my phone in a box.”</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>For the first time, she experienced life in the city as a teenager without an iPhone. She borrowed novels from the library and read them alone in the park. She started admiring graffiti when she rode the subway, then fell in with some teens who taught her how to spray-paint in a freight train yard in Queens. And she began waking up without an alarm clock at 7 a.m., no longer falling asleep to the glow of her phone at midnight. Once, as she later wrote in a text titled the “Luddite Manifesto,” she fantasized about tossing her iPhone into the Gowanus Canal.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://archive.ph/WeNjj">"‘Luddite’ Teens Don’t Want Your Likes"</a></p>

<p>Maybe we'll make it out of this thing ok. But it will take time.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Workout Program Change - GZCLP</title>
            <pubDate>12/16/2022 10:21:52</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/workout-program-change-gzclp.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/workout-program-change-gzclp.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I lasted about 12 weeks on the StrongLifts program. That is, until I got some kind of hip flexor injury. I suspect it was from a massive amount of squatting, along with not-great form for my anatomy. After I took about a week or two off of heavy squatting, the problem resolved itself, but it did make me question whether StrongLifts was a smart program for me. Some people swear by it, but I did find it unbalanced for progress and the focus on one area (squats) above all others.</p>

<p>After doing some more research, I decided to switch over to the GZCLP Program, named for <a href="http://swoleateveryheight.blogspot.com/">Cody LeFever</a>'s Reddit username. It's a linear progression, so you're still <em>basically</em> adding weight each time. But everything is much slower, and takes a more logical approach to progressive overload for the different lifts.</p>

<h3>The basic program is built like a pyramid with tiers:</h3>

<ul>
<li>T1 - Main barbell lift for the day. Heavy, low rep sets to build continuous strength.</li>
<li>T2 - Main assistance for the day, usually an assistance of the <em>previous workout's</em> primary lift. Mid-weight, mid-range rep sets.</li>
<li>T3 - Secondary assistance for the day. 1-3 workouts that are assistance for the T1 and T2 workouts. Low weight, high rep sets.</li>
</ul>

<p>The primary idea here is that the T1 workouts are the "peak" of the pyramid. It's the height of your strength, but it needs support from lower-level bases. T2 helps provide mid-range strength, and T3 provides a solid base to work from. Build out the whole pyramid, and you have a balanced, stable way of maintaining overall strength.</p>

<h3>Two things I'm finding helpful with this program:</h3>

<ol>
<li>On StrongLifts, you are always pushing for 5x5. If you can't get it, you try twice more, then deload and try again. Honestly, that's kinda dumb the more I got into it. I plateaued very quickly on a few lifts, and couldn't get past those humps even after "following the program." On GZCLP, T1 and T2 have a plan for when you fail. For example, on T1 workouts, when you can't hit 5x3, you move to 6x2, then continue the weight progression. When you can't hit that, you move to 10x1. When you fail again, you reduce by 15%, then go back to 5x3. Makes a lot more sense, and there's a sensible method for deloading and continuing growth.</li>
<li>The assistance work is varied, and I think will help with strength gains for the primary lifts. I had no method of doing that before, it was just trying the same lifts again and again, which ignores the possibility that some assitance muscles are too weak for me to grow in the main lifts.</li>
</ol>

<p>For a good overview of the program, see this <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Fitness/comments/6pjiwd/heres_a_quick_summary_of_the_gzclp_linear/">Reddit post</a>. There's an infographic, and the user also has a free Google Sheet that I'm using to track my workouts for now. I'm gonna give this a go for 12 weeks and see if I can make some better gains in strength. I already feel stronger than I did at the end of StrongLifts.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Old Philosophy Is Still Good Philosophy</title>
            <pubDate>12/16/2022 08:22:49</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/old-philosophy-is-still-good-philosophy.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/old-philosophy-is-still-good-philosophy.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>In response to a <em>Wired</em> article about preserving our digital selves for an "afterlife," Alan Jacobs writes:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Notice also — this is universal in such discourse — the unexamined “we”: “2023 will be the year we broaden our definition of what it means to live forever.” Depends on who “we” are, I think. I for one am not interested in broadening my definition of what means to live forever in such a way that it isn’t living and doesn’t last forever.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/defining-immortality-down/">defining immortality down</a></p>

<p>Connected to this, I'm thinking about the recent spate of excitement around AI and large language models (specifically ChatGPT). Tyler Cowen wrote some about the winners and losers as AI becomes a functional part of how we interact with one another, especially online. One thing he mentions is the idea that perhaps the unreplicable will become more valuable in our society: athletics, gardening, etc.:</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Alternatively, many humans will run away from such competitive struggles altogether.  Currently the bots are much better at writing than say becoming a master gardener, which also requires skills of physical execution and moving in open space. We might thus see a great blossoming of talent in the area of gardening, and other hard to copy inputs, if only to protect one’s reputation and IP from the bots.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Athletes, in the broad sense of that term, may thus rise in status. Sculpture and dance might gain on writing in cultural import and creativity. Counterintuitively, if you wanted our culture to become more real and visceral in terms of what commands audience attention and inspiration, perhaps the bots are exactly what you’ve been looking for.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://marginalrevolution.com/marginalrevolution/2022/12/who-gains-and-loses-from-the-new-ai.html?utm_source=feedly&amp;utm_medium=rss&amp;utm_campaign=who-gains-and-loses-from-the-new-ai">Who gains and loses from the new AI?</a></p>

<p>The first thing I thought when I read Alan Jacobs's response to that article was this: perhaps the Cartesian "I think, therefore I am" is not so old-fashioned as 21st century philosophy has made it out to be. Cogito ergo sum could, in the day and age of AI and the preservation of our "digital selves," give us a way <em>out</em> of the frenetic online hive-mind thing we have going on right now. Cogito ergo sum allows me to reassert my individualism. I am more than a small bit of data that gets fed into a large language model so it can reproduce generic text about any given subject. I am more than a few terabytes of data at the end of my life so that "I" can be preserved for someone else to interact with.</p>

<p>(And I agree, who really wants to keep a lifelong record of everything we say digitally?? Have we not all watched those <em>Black Mirror</em> episodes?)</p>

<p>It seems to me that perhaps the early-to-late modern philosophers may still have something to say to us. Descartes can still teach us a thing or two about our humanity in the midst of AI.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Currently Listening - Midnight Marauders by A Tribe Called Quest</title>
            <pubDate>12/15/2022 17:22:10</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/currently-listening-midnight-marauders-by-a-tribe-called-quest.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/currently-listening-midnight-marauders-by-a-tribe-called-quest.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h3>Currently listening: <em>Midnight Marauders</em> - A Tribe Called Quest</h3>

<p>I gotta say, it's weird to listen to a group's discography, and for each album to be incredible, <em>and</em> for each album to be better than the last. Also fun to listen to these as I read the corresponding chapters in <em>Go Ahead in the Rain: Notes to A Tribe Called Quest</em>.</p>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/album/4v5x3Oo3UjQ9YmF3hRAip5?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="380" frameBorder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Filling up Time</title>
            <pubDate>12/15/2022 16:15:00</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/filling-up-time.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/filling-up-time.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>A couple of weeks ago, I was able to take the plunge on removing all of the "big name" social media. This has been a cool step for me, and mostly kind of a nothingburger if I'm being honest. I already wasn't really using Facebook, my Twitter use was minimal (because, of all of the platforms, Twitter is the one with the most potential for "addiction"), and Instagram was an on-again, off-again thing for me. Mostly I am a lurker on these platforms anyway.</p>

<p>In any case, my Facebook account is no more, and the same is true for Twitter. My Instagram account <em>technically</em> exists but only because I don't want someone using my standard handle (@cdbaca), and I kept up my final story about leaving IG "for good" (one can only hope).</p>

<p>The frustrating part of this experience for me is that I've noticed how easy it is to fill up time with other useless junk. Inasmuch as I am a Twitter junkie, I'm similarly a Reddit junkie. There's new content everyday! I can follow the subs I want to follow! There are new topics to discover all the time!</p>

<p>The problem with this, of course, is the potential for infinite (doom)scrolling, just like anywhere else. It's a mind-waste/time-fill, and I'm just using it more now that I can't scroll Instagram on my phone. That and once I get bored with Reddit, I'll do that weird mindless thing where I check all the websites I normally check: NPR, Gmail, Lifehacker/Gizmodo, etc., and then do the circle again.</p>

<p>That's frustrating. What am I filling up my time for? Is it just because my brain is looking for something to consume and trying to avoid boredom (I expect that's the case)? I want to find some balance here: I recognize I can't <em>simply</em> think and be serious all the time. Sometimes it's probably alright to go mindless for a few minutes. I just don't want it to be for two-ish hours a day -- that is, if my screentime to report from Apple is to be believed.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>