<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>People and Blogs Series -  Manuel Moreale</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-08 08:11:35</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/people-and-blogs-series-manuel-moreale.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/people-and-blogs-series-manuel-moreale.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I keep ringing the bell a million times over, but I'm such a huge fan of the indie web and blogs in particular. I think it's the best way to resist the pull of large-scale corporations running the internet, and the barrier for entry (despite the technical knowledge sometimes required) is so low, that I think this is the way forward for keeping part of the internet sane.</p>

<p>A series I'm really enjoying from an indie blogger is a weekly series that <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/">Manuel Moreale</a> is running over at his blog. The series is "People &amp; Blogs" and he's just interviewing other folks on the internet running blogs and who are keeping up their own little corners of the web. The <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/pb-eli-mellen">most recent one</a> dropped today, and all of them are worth perusing.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>The Blog is Already Back</title>
            <pubDate>2023-12-04 16:14:14</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-blog-is-already-back.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/the-blog-is-already-back.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Now that the white-hot fire of Twitter is burning itself out, and its various alternatives (Threads, Bluesky, Mastodon) are generating merely gentle (or sputtering) flames, and TikTok (which is not a social-media site in any meaningful sense but rather a media-consumption platform) is still going nova, this is the time for people to rediscover the pleasures of blogging – of writing at whatever length you want, and posting photos, and embedding videos, and linking to music playlists, all on your little corner of the internet.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Let’s bring back the blog. And leave all the bad things spawned by the blogosphere to social media, where they belong. </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://blog.ayjay.org/bring-back-the-blog/">"Bring Back the Blog"</a>, Alan Jacobs</p>

<p>See, the thing is, I think the blog is already back. Just because social media giants (and <a href="https://joinmastodon.org/">the small guys too</a>) are taking up most of the discourse w/r/t web interaction doesn't mean the blog is not back. Thankfully, most of the interesting stuff I find now isn't through social media anymore. It's still through RSS, and still through indie blogs run by regular ol' people like you and me.</p>

<p>I think the only thing I'd really like to see is an easier way / lower barrier for entry into indie blogging. I can figure out how to put together <a href="https://github.com/cdbaca/ssg">a little static site generator of my own</a>, and blog through my terminal and text files. I doubt most regular folks can do that. And my sense is that Wordpress and other tools like it are too heavy for most folks' use.</p>

<p>I did find <a href="https://blot.im/">this little tool</a> the other day (via my RSS feed, via an indie blog!) which is pretty cool and simple. Looks as easy as having a couple folders on your computer, linking to something like Dropbox, and syncing up the folders once you've written a post or shared an image.</p>

<p>Anyway, to the original point of this post -- blogging might have done a little hibernating while we all experimented with a few sites that functioned as somewhat-global town squares. But my sense is that it is reawakening and ready to give us a warm, cozy hug when we are ready for it again.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Algorithms and Gen Alpha</title>
            <pubDate>2023-11-30 09:31:07</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/algorithms-and-gen-alpha.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/algorithms-and-gen-alpha.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Parents of Gen Alpha must take this seriously. I speak to many parents about social media; they worry that their kids will talk to predators or be exposed to explicit self-harm and suicidal content — which are, of course, real risks. But there is also something more pernicious, and more destabilizing happening. Something we have to get ahead of. Because maybe it seems like your child is simply watching some makeup tutorials, following some mental health influencers, or experimenting with their identity. But let me tell you: they are on a conveyor belt to someplace bad. Whatever insecurity or vulnerability they are struggling with, they will be pushed further and further into it. </p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>What I would say to the parents of Gen Alpha is: don’t let your children open accounts on social media platforms when they are still in early puberty. Delay their entry until at least 16. Prioritize their in-person interactions, and encourage them to discover who they are from real-world experiences, not manipulative algorithms.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>--<a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/algorithms-hijacked-my-generation">"Algorithms Hijacked My Generation. I Fear For Gen Alpha."</a>, Freya India</p>

<p>I'm a little wary of fear mongering w/r/t social media and technology, but the truth is my escape from nearly all social media (damn you, YouTube) has been monumental for my own day to day mental health. Not even in a clinical sense. I just feel happier, more connected, less anxious.</p>

<p>And the above is why we still have not allowed our kiddos to have phones. They occasionally use devices for school or a few minutes of searching for something, but we have tried to be very intentional about the internet being a tool, not something to just scroll through and be fed by. Here's to hoping we can stick it out, because I have the same concerns as Freya.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Computer Science Ed - Applicative vs. Normal Order Evaluation</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-26 13:19:12</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/computer-science-ed-applicative-vs-normal-order-evaluation.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/computer-science-ed-applicative-vs-normal-order-evaluation.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I recently started reading <a href="https://sarabander.github.io/sicp/html/index.xhtml#SEC_Contents"><em>Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</em></a> (the first recommended book in the <a href="www.teachyourselfcs.com">Teach Yourself CS</a> curriculum). I'm not even past the first section of the first chapter, and there are already concepts I'm coming across that never crossed my mind before, despite working with Python and Javascript for the last few years.</p>

<p>One concept I found interesting and yet difficult to grasp at first is the idea of the order in which computeres evaluate procedures. In SICP, they write of Scheme (a subset of the Lisp programming language) that it is an applicative-order language. That is,</p>

<blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>All the arguments to Scheme procedures are evaluated when the procedure is applied. In contrast, normal-order languages dalay evaluation of procedure arguments until the actual argument values are needed.
    --1.1.5, <a href="https://sarabander.github.io/sicp/html/1_002e1.xhtml#g_t1_002e1_002e5:~:text=Applicative%20order%20versus%20normal%20order">"Applicative order versus normal order"</a></p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>The example problem used to confirm that Scheme is an applicative-order language is the definition of two procedures and a calling of the test procedure:</p>

<p><code>
    (define (p) (p))
    (define (test x y)
        (if (= x 0)
        0
        y))
    (test 0 (p))
</code></p>

<p>Because Scheme is an applicative-order language, the interpreter attempts to evaluate all the arguments within the test procedure <em>first</em> before the full procedure is applied. When it tries to do this, (p) is called infinitely because (p) calls itself. The interpreter can never finish calling the actual procedure we're attempting to call because it's trying to determine a true value for (p) before determining whether x = 0 or not.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Odyssey - Home</title>
            <pubDate>2023-10-25 09:00:16</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/odyssey-home.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/odyssey-home.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I think anyone who listens to synth-y, tech-y, 80s-vibe music on YouTube has come across "Resonance" by Home.</p>

<iframe src=https://www.youtube.com/embed/8GW6sLrK40k?si=5ctc6uCcsEU6yg-G></iframe>

<p>This is such a strange, weird, nostalgia-inducing piece of music. Every time I listen to it, I experience unexplainable feelings of longing and melancholy. It's very strange for a piece of music to do that, but there you have it.</p>

<p>Anyway, I'm still taking a trip in my <a href="https://cbaca.blog/spotify-the-time-machine.html">Spotify time machine</a> and came across the album <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/2Nz9gdj35Unk1AbfL8Igmx?si=azvxpfevQoumuccsolhM_A"><em>Odyssey</em> by Home</a>, which I discovered after the YouTube algorithm so graciously gifted my with "Resonance." It's pretty great -- many of the songs also have that retro feel and its instrumental nature lends itself to being able to continute to focus at work while I listen.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>