<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>God is (in) the Details</title>
            <pubDate>11/28/2022 16:19:21</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/god-is-in-the-details.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/god-is-in-the-details.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I don't have much to say, except that I listened to two podcasts this week:</p>

<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.premierguitar.com/podcast/wong-notes/chris-thile-cory-wong-interview">Wong Notes - "Chris Thile's Exercise in Joy"</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.singforscience.org/episodes/rivers-cuomo-guido-van-rossum">Sing for Science - "Rivers Cuomo and Guido van Rossum"</a></li>
</ol>

<p>In both episodes, the interviewees said the phrase "God is in the details" -- in the former, Thile then corrects himself, and says "God <em>is</em> the details."</p>

<p>I find myself thinking and not thinking about God and religion much these days. "God" permeates my work and the culture that surrounds me, and yet, since leaving LIDE, I find myself wanting very little to do with <em>formal</em> and <em>institutional</em> versions of spirituality. (I recognize this is awfully millennial of me)</p>

<p>On the other hand, I cannot deny the draw of spirituality on some deep level within me. There has always, always been a sense of beauty, of love, of transcendence in life. The very existence of these feelings seem to me to be pointers to a deeper reality that I cannot quite grasp. A reality that fades from my vision when I try to look to closely, like a dream that I try to remember just after waking.</p>

<p>Mostly, it's in the details that I have these feelings. The feel of Elaine's hand on my back, the feel of my daughters' hair when I kiss them goodnight on the top of the head, the cold wind in the morning when I'm out walking, the gratitude I feel when surrounded by close friends and family.</p>

<p>Perhaps God is in the details after all, and that is all that we can say about it.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Changing up the Coffee Routine</title>
            <pubDate>11/22/2022 09:52:53</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/changing-up-the-coffee-routine.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/changing-up-the-coffee-routine.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Probably for the better part of 2+ years, my coffee routine hasn't shifted much. I roast coffee roughly once every six weeks or so, usually about 5 lbs at a time. Once the coffee has had a few days to rest post-roast, I put a little in a jar for the next week's consumption. The rest get sealed with the FoodSaver and frozen.</p>

<p>Nearly every day, I have two cups of coffee -- one in the morning and one around 2pm or so. A while back, James Hoffmann posted <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j6VlT_jUVPc">his preferred Aeropress recipe</a>. I use this every time I make an Aeropress now with slight variation:</p>

<h3>Current Aeropress Recipe</h3>

<ol>
<li>Standard orientation (non-inverted)</li>
<li>13 g coffee, ground relatively fine</li>
<li>Coffee in, then add 200 g water at roughly 205 degrees F</li>
<li>Let steep for 2 minutes, then swirl</li>
<li>At four minutes, plunge</li>
</ol>

<p>That's it. I love the simplicity of it, and honestly it makes a pretty incredible cup.</p>

<p>Sometimes in the afternoon I'll do the same, but I also have a Rancilio Silvia (V3), and if I'm feeling frisky for a few weeks, I will hit the espresso in the afternoon. I also got <em>really</em> into making cortados at work in the afternoon at the beginning of this year. I had a goal of getting better at latte (well... cortado) art, so I was drinking a <em>ton</em> of espresso in January and February. That was fun, but got to be a little too much dairy. I did succeed though! I make a pretty mean cortado if I do so say myself. My latte art went from being awful to mediocre+. That is, I can make a heart if I try hard enough and the stars align.</p>

<p>Years ago, I was Chemex-obsessed. In the same way I've used the Aeropress nearly every day for two years, I did the same with the Chemex. Alas, it broke while cleaning it at some point, and I never bothered to buy a new one. Until recently, that is! I needed to buy another one for Thanksgiving because we're having family over this year.</p>

<p>The new Chemex arrived two days ago, and I made my first Chemex in a couple of years. You know how there is just something about a smell or flavor that really takes you back to a point in your life? I know it's cliché, but that really does happen with the Chemex. It smells slightly different, brings out different aromatics, has a brighter flavor than the Aeropress or French Press. That said, I'm guessing I'll stick with the Chemex for a good long while and enjoy the nostalgia it brings with it.</p>

<h3>Current Chemex Recipe</h3>

<ol>
<li>35 g coffee, ground medium-fine</li>
<li>Use total 595 g water</li>
<li>Start with 70 g water to bloom, wait 45 seconds</li>
<li>Pour remainder of water in spurts of about 100 g or so</li>
<li>Final goal is for the coffee to finish brewing within 4-5 minutes of starting the bloom</li>
</ol>

<p>I used to take measurements and grinding and stuff so seriously and tried not to deviate. Coffee, however, is alive. It changes as the days get further out from the roast date. This usually requires a change in the brewing or grinding method. And because people usually have different coffee flavor preferences, I find that it's fine to change up water/coffee ratios, grind size, or whatever until you find what suits you. The only general rules I follow are: get roasted coffee as fresh as you can, and try to find a relatively inexpensive burr grinder. The rest will work itself out. Oh, and immersion brewing (Aeropress and French Press) covers a multitude of sins.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>TIL: 11-18-22</title>
            <pubDate>11/18/2022 16:03:38</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/til-11-18-22.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/til-11-18-22.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I came across an issue today with the generator I've written. If I write multiple posts in a day, the RSS feed may not pick up the newest post, because all the original post dates were set to today's date, but a time of 00:00:00 CST. So if it doesn't sort it properly, a feed reader may not pick up the newest post of the day because it could get pushed to the bottom of the list of today's posts instead of the top.</p>

<p>To fix that, I introduced datetimes to my "create a post" script, and then had to manipulate that datetime string to do what I needed in the creation of the data structures for the site. E.g., I wanted only the date (not the time) to show up on the index page, but I want them in order of writing in reverse. I also wanted the feed to be in reverse order of writing so that even if I post multiple times a day, feed readers will pick up the newest post.</p>

<p>The problem is, I have multiple functions doing the work of creating posts, manipulating data, creating the index page vs. the RSS feed vs. actual posts. But there is a single reference list of dictionaries I'm passing into these functions. In the script, my "make<em>index" function happens upstream of the "make</em>rss" function. And even though the index function was getting the right order, somehow, after I was passing in and manipulating the data in the function, the <em>original list</em> was getting manipulated even though I assigned it to a new variable.</p>

<p>Apparently, this is a feature/bug in Python (I'm sure someone <em>likes</em> that this happens in Python... I didn't experience that particular joy today). For example, if I have a list of lists called "posts" and then say posts<em>copy = posts, if I manipulate values within the posts</em>copy list, any values I change there <em>will also change</em> the values in the reference list. That's bonkers, but whatever. After a couple of hours of cursing the void, I found my answer <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/68712435/changes-made-in-python-list-showing-up-in-copy-of-original-list">here</a>. Not only do you need to assign the values to a new variable, you have to make a "deepcopy" of the original list and assign it (if the list in question has other data structures inside it). So instead of</p>

<p>`</p>

<pre><code>posts_copy = copy
</code></pre>

<p>`</p>

<p>I needed to do:</p>

<p>`</p>

<pre><code>from copy import deepcopy

posts_copy = deepcopy(posts)
</code></pre>

<p>`</p>

<p>From there, I was able to manipulate values in the function without worrying about overwriting data in the original list.</p>

<p>I like programming, but that was maddening.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Twitter v. Mastodon v. Micro.blog</title>
            <pubDate>11/18/2022</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/twitter-v-mastodon-v-micro-blog.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/twitter-v-mastodon-v-micro-blog.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <blockquote>
  <blockquote>
    <p>Twitter right now is mainly about Twitter but also a little about Mastodon. And Mastodon is mainly about Mastodon but also a lot about Twitter. Both places seem to be pretty chaotic, but here at micro.blog @manton &amp; co. are keeping things smooth and steady. It helps that there don’t seem to be many drama-addicted folks around here.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>-- <a href="https://social.ayjay.org/2022/11/18/twitter-right-now.html">Alan Jacobs</a></p>

<p>Yeah, agreed. I hadn't been on Twitter in while, but jumped to Mastodon just to check things out and see if it could operate differently than Twitter. My observations:</p>

<ol>
<li><em>Mastodon is better than Twitter in many ways.</em> Built in RSS feeds for accounts, ActivityPub compatible so it's genuinely federated, no quote tweeting, better moderation (similar to the better Reddit communities).</li>
<li><em>Mastodon doesn't quite live up to what I want it to be.</em> What I wanted was, perhaps, a way for people to be self-hosted but have a local space where that stuff got sent and you could just check in and see what others are thinking or up to.</li>
<li><em>Lots of people at Mastodon are just talking about Twitter.</em> I actually had to filter out posts that mention the word, but then there are people that call it the "bird site" or talk about Elon or whatever. I want Mastodon to be more than that but maybe that will take some time.</li>
</ol>

<p>I'm also not convinced Mastodon won't become a sort of Twitter 2.0. Maybe not quite as hateful or outrageous, but still chaotic. I've been considering trying micro.blog instead to see if that would function closer to what I want out of the web. It seesm like it's possible that service is closer than Mastodon.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Fitness Update</title>
            <pubDate>11/18/2022</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/fitness-update.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/fitness-update.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>A general fitness update:</p>

<p>I've been working out consistently 8/22/22, which is right at 13 weeks. The first few weeks, I was using the <a href="https://thefitness.wiki/routines/r-fitness-basic-beginner-routine/">r/Fitness Basic Routine</a>. This was helpful just for getting into weightlifting again (I haven't lifted weights since high school!). It helped lower the barrier and increase my confidence since I was just relearning a few basic barbell moves.</p>

<p>After a few weeks, my confidence was high enough that I was able to switch over to a routine that I felt better suited my needs. r/Fitness doesn't recommend it, but I decided to go with <a href="stronglifts.com">StrongLifts 5x5</a>, since it seemed like a logical step up. Roughly the same basic barbell lifts:</p>

<h3>A Day</h3>

<ol>
<li>Squat</li>
<li>Bench Press</li>
<li>Barbell Rows</li>
</ol>

<h3>B Day</h3>

<ol>
<li>Squat</li>
<li>Overhead Press</li>
<li>Deadlift</li>
</ol>

<p>You can go to his site for more details. But the basic idea is, start with really low weight on all lifts (the bar if you can, or a little bit of weight if it needs to be off the floor). Every move is 5 sets of 5 reps with the same weight. The next time you do that move, you increase the weight by 5lbs (2.5 weights on each side). Pure linear progression until your form breaks down or you can't lift the weight. Within a few weeks, I felt good enough to also add in extra arm work (A day: dips and skullcrushers, B day: chin ups and barbell or dumbbell curls). </p>

<h3>Postives / Wins</h3>

<ul>
<li>My chin ups have increased drastically. Before I started lifting, I could only do 1-2 chin ups. I can now do roughly 3 sets of 5 or 6 with no assistance, and that's after I do heavy lifting.</li>
<li>Deadlift is currently sitting at around 165 lbs.</li>
<li>I'm seeing body changes which are really cool. I haven't seen real upper body tone on me in a loooooooong time. It's nice to feel like I have muscles and to feel strong.</li>
</ul>

<h3>Negatives / Struggles</h3>

<ul>
<li>Currently dealing with ann anterior hip flexor issue. It seems like it might have been caused by bad squat form. I've fixed that (I think), but it's gonna take a while to heal, so I'm sticking around the 115-130 range for my squats.</li>
<li>Overhead press has been stalled for weeks now. I made it to about 65-70 lbs but just can't get 5x5. </li>
</ul>

<p>I can see why r/Fitness overall doesn't recommened StrongLifts. Honestly, I think it's a great program for someone starting out. It's simple, effective for building quick strength, and it's a quick workout (mine are usually 45-55 minutes). But I think the deload program doesn't really work. This is obvious by the OHP struggles I'm having. I also think it's possible that for many people who lack strength, growing your squat weight that quickly and squatting so often has the potential for injuring you if you aren't careful or don't listen to your body.</p>

<p>At the end of the day, my goal is really to support other activities I want to do (mainly, running and climbing). I'll continue doing StrongLifts for at least another 2 weeks to finish out 12 full weeks on the program, but I may end up switching to <a href="https://thefitness.wiki/routines/5-3-1-for-beginners/">Jim Wendler's 5/3/1</a> or the <a href="https://thefitness.wiki/routines/gzclp/">GZCL program</a>. My only concern with those are the time commitment. I just don't have more than an hour or so in the mornings, and that's when I'm working out. But either way, I'm trying to play the long game here. I want to be strong and healthy, not necessarily make my life revolve around being "a weightlifter."</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>