<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <atom:link href="https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <title>Roots to Branches</title>
    <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg</link>
    <description>Looking at the roots of things to see where they lead</description>
    <language>en-us</language>    
    
        <item>
            <title>Brush Your Teeth</title>
            <pubDate>2025-10-24 10:47:28</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/brush-your-teeth.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/brush-your-teeth.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>Last week I read <em>Your Money or Your Life</em> by Vicki Robin and Joe Dominguez. This was mostly driven by the desire to be as clear as possible about the current financial trajectory we are on. This past ten months or so has been a doozy with Elaine's chronic migraines and her inability to work (much). We are grateful to have savings and family that have helped to keep us afloat during this time, but the savings account and overall ability to save has definitely taken a bit of a hit. I may not say we're struggling, but it's about time for us to start pulling back even further on spending, seeing where we can be more frugal and live more simply so that we can be responsible with what we have.</p>

<p>Step 2 of the book details a simple (but not easy!) step on the path to financial health/independence. Robin says the only way to be up front and honest about your spending is track every cent in and out. It's been a LONG time since we've done this — the last time was back when we first got married and literally had our income converted to cash and put in envelopes so we could only spend what we made and not a penny more.</p>

<p>So, since the beginning of October, I've started doing just that. Every cent in and out is now tracked in a spreadsheet, with a few extra fields for things like account/category/subcategory, etc. Prior to this, I had a "general" idea about how much we spent on average, but it has been a good practice so far, and my goal is to continue to do this every day.</p>

<p>The overall point, though, I think is deeper than simply this budgeting/financial piece in our lives. Money is necessarily a big part of how we orient our lives, so it's a good place to start. But since I started doing this earlier in October, I've tried to view it like I'm "brushing my teeth" every day. I never, ever miss brushing my teeth. I have one set of them, I'd like to keep them healthy as long as possible, and I like having fresh breath. Not to mention, brushing my teeth isn't even something I <em>think</em> about doing. I just do it because I do it.</p>

<p>I've been thinking a lot about how there are plenty of other areas in our lives that probably ought to be the same way. Tracking all our transactions? Probably needs to be a brush your teeth thing. I have a set amount of money coming in every month. I would like to retire someday, and I would like to be prepared for major expenses. The best way to start to get a real sense of this is by tracking transactions daily.</p>

<p>Cleaning the common areas of the house? Brush your teeth.</p>

<p>Basic car maintenance (something I'm falling into an obsessive YouTube rabbit hole about)? Brush your teeth.</p>

<p>Exercise / fitness? Brush your teeth.</p>

<p>Perhaps one can get a little overly obsessive about this, but on some level this is like... the task of life, right? Later in the book, Robin gives other steps for her financial life plan to set you on a new path. One of those things is to go back through your daily transactions and note whether something positively, negatively, or neutrally affected your life. Did it bring you closer to the kind of person you want to be?</p>

<p>In the same way, perhaps "brushing your teeth" in all of these areas (or the areas that are important to you) eventually gives you some impetus to evaluate what actually matters to you. Since you're checking in on this thing daily or weekly or whatever, you start to get a sense of which things are just taking up your time and space when you actually don't want that in your life. Vice versa, even if you "don't like" brushing your teeth in some area or another, you may continue to do so because you know the outcome is worth the value it brings to your life.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Lore of Running - Chapter 1</title>
            <pubDate>2025-09-18 15:40:27</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-lore-of-running-chapter-1.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-lore-of-running-chapter-1.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I'm currently trying to delve a little deeper into the science of running, not just taking training programs or "common thought" for granted. To that end, I'm now reading <em>Lore of Running</em> by Tim Noakes. A massive 900-pager with a whole intro section steeped in anatomy and physiological models for how running and exercise truly work, this is a bigger project than the <em>Daniels Running Formula</em> read.</p>

<p>I'm attempting to grapple with this book though, so I'm tackling it like I would tackle a textbook in a class. My science background is woefully inadequate, so I'm also trying to supplement with LLMs and trusted sources like Khan Academy. Very possible I get things wrong here, but the hope is that I come out on the other side a better and more informed coach and athlete!</p>

<h1>Chapter 1 - Muscle Structure and Function</h1>

<h2>Notes and Quotes</h2>

<h3>Structural Components of Skeletal Muscles</h3>

<ul>
<li>There are three major types of muscle in the body:</li>
</ul>

<ol>
<li>Cardiac</li>
<li>Skeletal
<ul>
<li>broken into Type I and Type II fibers, discussed later</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Smooth</li>
</ol>

<p>The primary focus of this chapter is on skeletal muscle, as this type of muscle is the biggest contributor (cardiac to a lesser extent) to athletic/running performance.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Muscles are made up of bundles of muscle fibers. Muscle fibers in turn are made up of bundles of rods called myofibrils. Myofibrils in turn are made up of sarcomeres (stacked on top of each other). Sarcomeres are made up of myofilaments which lie parallel to one another. These myofilaments are made up of a "center" thick filament made of myosin molecules and thinner "outer" filaments made of actin molecules. Myosin and actin interact with one another in a complex way (mentioned below) to produce muscle contraction (concentric shortening, eccentric lengthening). </p></li>
<li><p>For energy, triglycerides (fat droplets) and mitochondria, along with glycogen stores are dispersed throughout the sarcomere. Mitochondria and fat droplets can produce energy with and without the to the mitochondria, where enzymes convert this energy into lood supply. With the blood supply, blood droplets energy from food ATP (adenosine triphosphate — the body's main energy currency). Triglycerides (three fatty acid molecules linked to a glycerol molecule) are broken down by triglyceride lipase -- also broken down by mitochondria to provide energy to muscles. Again, this can happen both from the bloodstream and "non-aerobically" (NOT anaerobically, a different thing). When the fat in muscles is directly used by mitochondria, the glycerol  is transported to the liver, turned into glucose. This is important for prolonged energy needs.</p></li>
<li><p>The glycogen stored in sarcomeres is the other non-aerobic method mitochondria gain access to energy.</p></li>
</ul>

<h3>Biochemical Events of Muscle Contraction</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>The myosin molecules (making up the thick filaments) have "heads" that have a kind of attraction to the actin molecules of the thin filaments. In resting state, the attraction is blocked physically by tropomyosin molecules. To start the muscle contraction, the brain sends a neurological signal via the peripheral nerve surrounding the muscle fiber to the motor nerve end plate. This signal releases acetylcholine to a special receptor on the muscle cell, which causes a new electrical signal to travel down the transverse tubules of the muscle cell.</p></li>
<li><p>From this point, (unclear on the mechanism), calcium stored in the sarcoplasmic reticulum is released. This "moves" the tropomyosin molecules (via a binding to troponin-C, a receptor that is attached to the actin/tropomyosin) allowing the myosin heads to attach to the actin molecules.</p></li>
<li><p>At this point, the myosin head goes through a cycle, where in the ATP stored in the myosin head is broken down into ADP and Pi, the myosin head "bends" at a 45 degree angle (potentially there is a different model here, as this doesn't fully account for eccentric contraction), which pulls the actin filaments toward the center of the sarcomere.</p></li>
<li><p>This fully contracted position is called the "rigor complex". To break this rigor complex, mitochondria supplies fresh ATP at the ATP binder on the myosin head, and the calcium is removed from the troponin-C receptor.</p></li>
<li><p>The rate at which this occurs determines the speed the muscle can move. The total number of these "cross bridges" determines the power of the muscle. The speed of the contraction is determined by how fast ATP is bound and split on the myosin head. Power is also determined by the amount of calcium bound to troponin-C receptors.</p></li>
</ul>

<h3>Types of Muscle Fibers</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Type I fibers are usually red due to the higher content of myoglobin, have a higher concentration of mitochondria, and are considered "slow twitch" meaning a lower myosin ATPase activity. Usually endurance athletes have a higher perecentage of these.</p></li>
<li><p>Type II fibers are a little more complex and there is a spectrum, but generally they are white, with a lower myoglobin content and lower mitochondrial concentration. Considered "fast twitch", though IIa fibers can closely resemble Type I. Type IIb are "traditional" Type II fibers.</p></li>
<li><p>During exercise, the brain goes through a recruitement phase where Type I are recruited first, then Type IIa, then Type IIb. </p></li>
<li><p>The body's composition of these fibers are somewhat genetically determined, but exercise can change the makeup here as well. The recruitment of these types and their exhaustion have various explanations, including energy depletion, but also neurological patterns, and the brain's use of different receptors to determine the body's oxygen, temperature, and glucose supply (these receptors help the body to protect itself from brain or heart damage).</p></li>
</ul>

<h3>Concentric and Eccentric Muscle Contractions</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Not much to say here, except that eccentric contractions produce 2x force as concentric contractions, meaning depending on their use they are more likely to be the cause of muscle or tendon injury.</p></li>
<li><p>Weight training (both concentric and eccentric) has been shown to aid in running performance, especially eccentric movement. Runners often benefit from weight training, but not necessarily the other way around (i.e., running can inhibit the ability to gain strength). Most likely strength training helps due to the "neuromuscular adaptations from lifting that ensure muscle activation [during running/racing] remains high."</p></li>
</ul>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapter 10</title>
            <pubDate>2025-06-03 15:16:10</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-10.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapter-10.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h1>Chapter 10: Season-Tailored Training</h1>

<h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<p>After the buildup of information and Daniels-specific training run types, it seems like chapter 10 is the meat of the entire formula. There are other chapters after this, and I may do one final post on the cross country chapter for my own  benefit. But this chapter gives the overall season-training philosophy Daniels suggests with the various training runs in phases for how and why to progress throughout a season.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"The less fit you are, the less intense the training has to be to benefit." (151)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Training for athletes should be relatively tailored, both to the fitness of the athlete, and the time available for training.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"First determine level of fitness based on current mileage and speeds of any workouts that make up training sessions, which allows runners to establish the proper VDOT value for all types of training." (152)</p>
</blockquote>

<h3>Phase Training</h3>

<p>Daniels suggests breaking seasonal training down into phases:</p>

<ul>
<li>Phase I for base training with a focus on foundation and injury prevention</li>
<li>Phase II for introducing initial quality runs</li>
<li>Phase III for transitional quality runs</li>
<li>Phase IV for peak performance/final quality runs</li>
</ul>

<p>In order of importance, the phases are I, IV, II, III, so depending on the amount of time available, the phases should be prioritized roughly in this order, with at least three weeks given to each phase (in order) before moving to the next phase. </p>

<p>[Example: if given 9 weeks for training, 3 weeks should be delegated to phase I, followed by phase II, then phase IV. You would increase/decrease and/or add phase III if given more or less time.]</p>

<p>Another note, if a runner only has three weeks, there's no point in "throwing them into the deep end." Start them like you would any other runner, giving them solid base/foundational training rather than risking injury.</p>

<p>On the flip side, if a runner is already running regularly, you may be able to skip phase I or even phase II depending on the level of fitness.</p>

<p>If you have time for all four phases, the focus or added training type should be as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Phase I</strong>: All E, with a single L run. Adding light strides 3x weekly if you have more than 3 weeks for phase I</li>
<li><strong>Phase II</strong>: 1L, 2E, with 2 added R days. The reason for this is you are only adding one new stressor during the phase (so just adding "running fast"). This is when you'd start to use VDOT to determine training speeds.</li>
<li><strong>Phase III:</strong> 1L, 2E, 1R, 1I for shorter distances. 2I and no R if runners are racing more than 3K. This adds some distance to the speed running, dipping to lactate threshold rather than pure anaerobic running.</li>
<li><strong>Phase IV</strong>: 1L, 1 session with both T &amp; R, 1 race, 2E. This adds the full aerobic pressure along with maintaining speed fitness.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Races are part of training." (156)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>^ so use them in place of an I run.</p>

<p>The first quality workout of the week should be considered the most important workout, regardless of the phase of training. If possible, it should be done on Monday or Tuesday (assuming the L run was on Sunday and race day is Saturday). We're shooting for 2-3 quality runs a week. (quality = T, I, and R sessions)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"The overall plan is designed to intoduce one new stress when moving from one phase of training to the next, and new phases will also provide for maintenance of benefits earned in each previous phase." (160)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Finally, he offers a chart that gives tables for determining speed v. endurance. Using this chart with a runner can help determine whether the runner is "better" at speed or endurance and where to focus during training. But, he also says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"Try working on the weakness first, but if that doesn't  bring positive results, concentrate on your strenght, and that may well improve both strength and weakness." (161)</p>
</blockquote>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>Reading Daniels' Running Formula - Chapters 6 to 9</title>
            <pubDate>2025-06-02 16:12:17</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapters-6-to-9.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/reading-daniels-running-formula-chapters-6-to-9.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <h2>Notes &amp; Quotes</h2>

<p>The remainder of Part I of the book was relatively "common sense information" -- or information that I am personally not particularly interested in. These chapters covered environment/altitude specific training, treadmill training, "fitness training" (i.e., non-competitive training), and training breaks/supplemental training.</p>

<p>The altitude stuff I don't care much about at all. I will likely never be able to bring a team or runners up to Colarado to train (as much as I'd like to), and Daniels seems to indicate that it's not that big of a deal anyway. Moreso, the goal during training should be to mimic predicted race conditions.</p>

<p>I basically skipped the chapter on treadmill training. Again, not much I can do here with my own athletes, and if I'm stuck inside I'm not doing much on the treadmill because it sucks so much.</p>

<p>The fitness training chapter was decent, and will likely help me with some of my on-the-side coaching for brand new runners trying to get fit for local races or personal goals.</p>

<p>The training breaks/supplemental training chapter, again, was relatively common sense information. Although I do think his data on supplemental training for strength was lacking / out of date. I think it's relatively common knowledge in the running world now that strength training for runners should include heavy lifting. Body weight stuff, while it might help a little, will not provide the injury prevention/strength benefits needed to sustain a ton of mileage.</p>

<p>A big note from Daniels on resting is that athletes and coached ought to be very open to resting, both for planned and unplanned periods of time. Unplanned for things like illness/injury and planned for resisting burnout.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
        <item>
            <title>AI Browser? No Thanks</title>
            <pubDate>2025-05-29 08:50:41</pubDate>
            <link>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/ai-browser-no-thanks.html</link>
            <guid>https://cdbaca.github.io/ssg/ai-browser-no-thanks.html</guid>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[ <p>I've been using the Arc browser for the better part of two years now. Mostly because I liked the interface and the ability to make "spaces." It's my personal daily driver for surfing the web. But it was off-putting when The Browser Company announced their "Arc Search" feature that would produce its own AI (haha) generated page to summarize the results. A "search engine that searched for you."</p>

<p>And now TBC announces they'll stop supporting/maintaining Arc to pivot to Dia, an AI-based browser.</p>

<p>Manu <a href="https://manuelmoreale.com/on-browsers-ai-and-the-web">sums it up well</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>"But more importantly, there’s something else about this whole idea of chatting-with-a-computer-to-get-answers-from-the-web that I find incredibly off-putting: the complete lack of potential for serendipity."</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Maybe I'm just not reading the signs. Maybe the CEOs and big companies know better than I do what will work in the market. But whatever this AI-based web hellscape they want is, I'm really not interested in it. The web is for discovery. When all of the weirdness of the internet is wrapped up behind an LLM, it gets dumbed down to the most average, least interesting version of whatever it was in its original form.</p>

<p>Lame.</p>
 ]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>